<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Early descriptions of human Lewy cytopathology in the 1960s and 70s reported filament-rich regions in LBs but also some vesicle/membrane components
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>
 </sup> and occasional reports in the 1980s and 90s confirmed this observation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup> Nonetheless, the acceptance of this insight and its impact on conceptualizing PD pathogenesis and developing PD biomarkers and drugs has been limited so far. This situation may change after a striking recent publication: a detailed analysis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup> of PD brain tissue by correlative light and electron microscopy, a technique that allows immunohistological and EM ultrastructural analysis of the same lesions. The authors found that the majority of human LBs consisted of αS intermingled with clusters of various membranous structures or components (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, right). Of special significance, the authors identified in the core of LBs various vesicle clusters that were coated with high local concentrations of non-fibrillar αS. Surprisingly, only about 20% of all LBs/LNs had large amyloid fibrils (at least 5 nm diameter, at least 25 nm in length; smaller structures were likely not detectable with the method) associated with them, indicating that amyloid-type αS aggregation is not as integral or required a part of PD cytopathology as formerly believed. Raman scattering and infrared spectroscopy showed that the LB core comprised large amounts of lipids, most importantly sphingomyelin and PC, as determined by mass spectrometry. These striking new insights raise the question of why these features of human LBs were apparently overlooked in the past. As the authors point out, the short postmortem intervals of their cases and the special tissue preservation methods they applied may be responsible. Traditional LB analyses (e.g., see ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup>) have largely relied on immunohistochemical staining at the light microscopic level, providing limited resolution.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup> Thus, a bias might have been created in the past for areas that showed the expected rod-like or fibrous structures (see a commentary by Bartels
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup>). The important new findings of Shahmoradian et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup> are based on state-of-the-art imaging techniques and, if confirmed by others, have the potential to change the ways in which we conceptualize and model PD pathogenesis and design therapeutics.
</p>
