<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, the effect of dopaminergic medication on gut microbiome composition has not been studied directly. Nonetheless, the effect of dopaminergic medication can be hypothesized to be substantial, as effects of various medications on gut microbiota composition have been described [
 <xref rid="ref017" ref-type="bibr">17, 35, 36</xref>]. Most microbiome case-control studies in PD concern a cross-sectional sample of already treated PD subjects. Although five studies adjusted for the effects of medications that were differentially prescribed within their PD cohort, or tried to link microbial effects to the Levodopa Equivalent Daily Dose (LEDD), the one-sided introduction of dopaminergic medication as a possible confounder hinders the interpretation of the current microbiome data in PD. Bedarf et al. introduced a cohort that is Levodopa na誰ve. However, all PD subjects were treated using other dopaminergic drugs. Contrary to other publications, no effect from differentially prescribed dopaminergic drugs was reported by Bedarf et al. which the authors attribute to the small sample size of the study. Keshavarzian et al. and Barichella et al. included 12 and 39 treatment-na誰ve PD subjects respectively. Keshavarzian et al. found a difference in microbiome composition between untreated and treated PD subjects, but attributed this to differences in disease duration. Barichella et al. report a lower Lachnospiraceae abundance in untreated PD compared to HC, which was not found in treated subjects. Another treatment-na誰ve sample can be derived from Heintz-Buschart et al. who included 20 polysomnography (PSG) proven iRBD patients as prodromal PD [
 <xref rid="ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Compared to HC, 41 operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were differentially abundant in iRBD of which over 75% showed a similar change as was found in their PD cohort compared to HC. Nonetheless, the extent to which the remaining 25% can be attributed to medication effects, the temporal changes as the disease progresses or a distinct RBD positive clinical subtype, remains to be seen. Larger gut microbiome studies in treatment-na誰ve PD subjects are therefore required to distinguish medication effects from disease specific changes in gut microbiome composition.
</p>
