<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A variety of gastrointestinal determinants of gut microbiome composition have been identified in population-based cohort studies, including gastrointestinal disease and/or surgery, constipation, and dietary influences [
 <xref rid="ref035" ref-type="bibr">35, 36</xref>]. First, gastrointestinal disease and/or surgery were used as exclusion criteria in the microbiome studies in PD with varying stringency. Second, constipation is a known determinant of gut microbiome composition and a common non-motor symptom in PD, with objective measures revealing a prolonged stool transit time in up to 80% of patients [
 <xref rid="ref035" ref-type="bibr">35, 36, 44, 45</xref>]. No direct comparison with idiopathically constipated subjects was performed. However, constipation was assessed in five microbiome studies in PD using questionnaires or an interview, which can underestimate its prevalence [
 <xref rid="ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Where the most objective measurement, using radio-opaque markers [
 <xref rid="ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], can be unattainable for large-scale microbiome studies, more objective measurements of stool frequency and consistency can be obtained through a stool diary and the Bristol Stool Chart [
 <xref rid="ref045" ref-type="bibr">45, 46</xref>]. Also, moist content of the fecal sample can be used as a marker for stool transit time and consistency [
 <xref rid="ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Last, various nutrients exert an influence on gut microbiome composition [
 <xref rid="ref035" ref-type="bibr">35, 36</xref>]. Dietary habits were included as covariate in five studies, with different emphasis such as protein consumption and fruit-vegetable consumption. To minimize recall bias and provide a complete assessment of nutrient intake, food diaries can be used in combination with food frequency questionnaires to obtain more reliable and complete information on dietary habits [
 <xref rid="ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
</p>
