<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The observed PheWAS associations of 
 <italic>APOE</italic> variants with metabolic/cardiovascular traits are not surprising. While vascular and metabolic risk factors such as hypertension, hyperlipidemia /hypercholesterolemia, hyperinsulinemia, and obesity at midlife, diabetes mellitus (DM), and cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases (including stroke, clinically silent brain infarcts and cerebral microvascular lesions) are generally thought to increase the risk of dementia and AD [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], the directional impact of a factor could be age-dependent, for example, hypertension, obesity and hypercholesterolemia are risk factors at middle age (&lt;65 years) for late-life dementia and AD, but protective late in life (age &gt;75 years) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. It seems to be odd that AD patient had a lower risk of developing CAD [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], but it is consistent with a meta-analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] and this meta-analysis also reported that metabolic syndrome decreases the risk of AD. In the MR analysis from this study, AD increased the risk of CAD (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0241552.s009">S9 Table</xref>), but this result was supported by MR Egger method only. Taking age into consideration may help better delineate the relationship. Furthermore, several cardiovascular risk factors demonstrated associations with more rapid cognitive decline as expected, however it was also reported that recent or active hypertension and hypercholesterolemia were associated with slower cognitive decline for AD patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. These epidemiology studies suggested that it appears to be a complex interplay between AD and metabolic/cardiovascular risk factors and conditions, and the occasionally contradictory findings may be due to age of the population, sampling biases and/or other confounding factors. Nevertheless, the Finnish Geriatric Intervention Study to Prevent Cognitive Impairment and Disability (FINGER) study demonstrated that multidomain intervention (diet, exercise, cognitive training, vascular risk monitoring) had beneficiary effect on the primary outcome, i.e. change in cognition as measured through comprehensive neuropsychological test battery (NTB) in an at-risk elderly population (aged 60–77) with CAIDE (Cardiovascular Risk Factors, Aging and Dementia) Dementia Risk Score of at least 6 points and cognition at mean level or slightly lower than expected for his/her age group, suggesting targeting modifiable vascular and lifestyle-related risk factors could improve or maintain cognitive functioning [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The PheWAS analysis suggested the minor allele of rs7412 (defining ε2 allele), a known protective allele for AD (OR = 0.74), was also a protective allele for having high cholesterol, low HDL, having heart metabolic disease or CAD. Similarly, the minor allele of rs429358 (defining ε4 allele), a known risk allele for AD (OR = 2.17), was also a risk allele for having high cholesterol, low HDL, having heart metabolic disease or CAD. Our MR analysis demonstrated that LDL and total cholesterol had a causal relationship to the development of AD using MR Egger. This MR result is however sensitive to the MR methods used as other methods such as weighted mode, weighted median, or simple mode (not pre-specified analyses) did not provide evidence or only provide suggestive evidence for the causal effect of LDL on AD. A recent MR analysis on 24 potentially modifiable risk factors [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] concluded that genetically predicted cardiometabolic factors were not associated with AD as there was no evidence of causal relationship after excluding one pleiotropic genetic variant (not disclosed in the publication) near the 
 <italic>APOE</italic> gene (also near 
 <italic>APOC1</italic> and 
 <italic>TOMM40</italic> genes). The evidence we obtained was far weaker than that reported by Larsson et al., for all variants [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Despite there were few SNPs driving the causal evidence in single variant analysis, leave-one-analysis did not differ substantially from the analysis including all variants for LDL trait except rs7412 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0241552.s010">S1 Fig</xref>). This study opted to report the findings using the inverse variance weighted method (when Egger intercept is not significant) as also adopted by Howard et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], where a minimal of 30 SNPs used in instrument variable was also imposed, or MR Egger regression results (when the intercept is significant). We did not filter out analysis with less than 30 variants. Both compromises are limitations in this study thus those results shall be interpreted with caution. In addition, both IVW and MR Egger methods do not protect against the violation of the MR assumption when the pleiotropic effects act via a confounder of the exposure-outcome association [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
