<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The observed PheWAS associations of rs646776 variant with metabolic/cardiovascular traits are also not surprising. SNP rs646776 was reported to be robustly associated with low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C, 
 <italic>p</italic> = 3 × 10
 <sup>−29</sup>) with each copy of the minor allele decreasing LDL cholesterol concentrations by ~5–8 mg/dl [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. The association was strengthened in a meta-analysis of ~100,000 individuals of European descent for LDL-C (
 <italic>p</italic> = 5x10
 <sup>-169</sup>) and was also detected for total cholesterol (
 <italic>p</italic> = 7x10
 <sup>-130</sup>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. However, which gene is the causative gene for rs646776 effect is less clear despite it was selected to be included in the PheWAS analysis based on the association with plasma progranulin levels. Rs646776 at the 1p13 locus was also strongly associated with transcript levels of three neighboring genes: sortilin (
 <italic>SORT1</italic>) (
 <italic>p</italic> = 3 × 10
 <sup>−26</sup>), cadherin EGF LAG seven-pass G-type receptor 2 (
 <italic>CELSR2</italic>) (
 <italic>p</italic> = 2 × 10
 <sup>−12</sup>) and proline and serine rich coiled-coil 1 (
 <italic>PSRC1</italic>) (
 <italic>p</italic> = 3 × 10
 <sup>−12</sup>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. The conditional analysis suggested that 
 <italic>SORT1</italic> eQTL effect might be the dominant effect [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Rs599839, a SNP in LD with rs646776, was also reported to be associated with CAD [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The minor allele conferring lower level of LDL cholesterol also conferred lower risk of CAD. Rs646776 was also identified in a bivariate analysis to be associated with circulating IGF-I and IGF-binding protein-3 (IGFBP-3) (
 <italic>p</italic> = 6.87 x10
 <sup>-9</sup>) in a meta-analysis of 21 studies including 30,884 adults of European ancestry [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. The growth hormone/insulin-like growth factor (IGF) axis can be manipulated in animal models to promote longevity. IGF related proteins including IGF-I and IGFBP-3 have also been implicated in risk of human diseases including cardiovascular diseases and diabetes. This is particularly interesting given the observation that rs646776 is associated with longevity in the PheWAS analysis.
</p>
