<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is surprising and puzzling to see the effect of AD variants on multiple eye phenotypes especially myopia that have onset in early childhood or teens. The association with age related macular degeneration (AMD) was reported previously [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The AMD association is interesting because the histopathological hallmark of AMD is amyloid-β (Aβ) in optic never drusen [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Drusen of the macula are very small yellow and white spots that appear in one of the layers of the retina named Bruch’s membrane and are remnant nondegradable proteins and lipids (lipofuscin), which is the earliest visible sign of dry macular degeneration. In addition to the amyloid phenotype, AMD and AD also share other common histologic feature such as vitronectin accumulation and immunologic features such as increased oxidative stress, and apolipoprotein and complement activation pathways [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. The common etiopathogenetic and morphological manifestations of AD and age-related eye diseases in amyloid genesis may have a broader implication in understanding the disease mechanism, identifying new biomarkers and treatment [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. A recent study showed that the soft drusen area in amyloid-positive patients was significantly larger than that in amyloid-negative patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Ocular and visual information processing deficit were other possible biomarkers for AD [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Recently it was also reported that thinner retinal nerve fiber layer is associated with an increased risk of dementia including AD, suggesting that retinal neurodegeneration may serve as a preclinical biomarker for dementia [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Risk variant for AD rs429358 in our PheWAS results had a protective effect for AMD and blindness (
 <italic>p</italic> = 9.6 x 10
 <sup>−5</sup>, FDR = 0.004), perhaps reflecting the equilibrium of Aβ in brain vs. retina like the situation between brain vs. CSF. A variety of other visual problems reported in patients with AD have been reviewed in details [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] including loss of visual acuity (VA), color vision and visual fields; changes in pupillary response to mydriatics, defects in fixation and in smooth and saccadic eye movements; changes in contrast sensitivity and in visual evoked potentials (VEP); and disturbances of complex visual functions, though they have not been studied as a risk factor of AD or outcome of having AD. In the MR analysis, we cannot directly test the causal relationship between AMD despite the GWAS with large sample size is available due to standard error of odds ratio was not reported in the paper [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>].
</p>
