<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Subjects with AD risk variant rs1113600 in 
 <italic>CLU</italic> gene had a higher chance of being nearsighted, while subjects with AD risk variant rs429358 in 
 <italic>APOE</italic> gene had a lower chance of being nearsighted. It was reported that wearing reading glasses correlated significantly with high mini-mental state examination for the visually impaired (MMSE-blind) after adjustment for sex and age (OR  =  2.14, 95% CI  =  1.16–3.97, 
 <italic>p</italic>  =  0.016), but reached borderline significance after adjustment for education [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. There was a trend toward correlation between myopia and better MMSE-blind (r  =  -0.123, 
 <italic>p</italic>  =  0.09, Pearson correlation) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. On the other hand, myopia may be a surrogate phenotype for intelligence (or education), as a genetic correlation between myopia and intelligence was shown in a small cohort of 1500 subject (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Larsson et al., suggested that genetically predicted educational attainment was significantly associated with AD per year of education completed (OR = 0.89, 
 <italic>p</italic> = 2.4 × 10
 <sup>−6</sup>) and per unit increase in log odds of having completed college/university (OR = 0.74, 
 <italic>p</italic> = 8.0 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup>), while intelligence had a suggestive association with AD (OR = 0.73, 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.01) [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Our MR analysis did not provide evidence on the causal relationship of myopia phenotype on AD. Furthermore, although genetic variants (rs429358 and rs1113600) are associated with multiple phenotypes, the associations are not necessarily independent of each other. In fact, MR Egger intercept test did not support the independent relationship except for height and a few other traits. Overall, the relationship and interpretation between traits seem to be complex and require further examination.
</p>
