<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, from ∼2005 onward the genetics field began to witness a revolution. The development of methods for highly parallel genotyping and the generation of knowledge resources such as the Human Genome Project and the International HapMap Project provided the tools and blueprint for understanding the influence of common genetic variability on human traits, including disease. Conversely to previous efforts, this work required large sample series, and was particularly amenable to the aggregation of data. This represented a sea change in genetics. Understanding that each center’s individual ability to discover robust association was limited, the groups that were previously in competition with each other, had to devise ways to work together. In many ways the early seeds of the IPDGC were sown by a coordinated effort in genome wide association (GWA) experiments in PD that began in 2008 [
 <xref rid="ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This revealed that sharing, of what were at the time large data, across centers was not only feasible, but necessary, and that when this was done effectively, transformative discoveries could be made. The genesis of the IPDGC came from a rather informal meeting held in Paris in 2009, where a small group of ∼10 investigators established loose criteria for working together. Essentially these were centered on unfettered data sharing, no individual restrictions on the work of each scientist, an understanding that there would be no surprises, and a commitment to help each other on projects. The in-person IPDGC meetings have continued in force over the last decade, with at least one meeting every year hosted by members in Berlin and Tubingen (Germany), Vienna (Austria), London (United Kingdom), Paris, Toulouse and Nice (France), Reykjavik (Iceland), San Diego, Miami (United States of America), Amsterdam (The Netherlands) and Lisbon (Portugal). It is notable that until two years ago there was no external monetary support for these meetings, with each attendee paying their own way. In the last two years, attendance of a dozen or more junior scientists has been sponsored by the Parkinson Foundation, something we are truly grateful for. The last IPDGC meeting included ∼90 attendees, PD scientists across disciplines and from academia, the government, PD foundations, and industry. Here we comment on the history of discovery in IPDGC and then extend this to a view toward the future, and our expectations for the next period of IPDGC research.
</p>
