<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Regardless of the differentiation method, cell cultures can be widely heterogeneous. On average, iPSC-PD studies, which use midbrain patterning protocols, yield 64% neurons and 27% dopaminergic neurons of the total cells (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3j</xref>). Proportions of neurons (bIII-Tub+) and dopaminergic neurons (TH+) vary vastly between studies even when using identical differentiation techniques (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3j</xref>). Quantitative analyses conducted at discordant timepoints along the maturation process may further contribute to differences in reported proportions of cell type between studies. In addition, arbitrary thresholds of immunocytochemical staining may alter the quantification of cell type numbers reported. Some studies exclusively focus on the analysis of dopaminergic neurons, but many others consistently report the presence of astrocytes, neural stem cells and multiple midbrain neuronal subtypes (i.e., glutaminergic and GABAergic) in their cultures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>
 </sup>. Mixed cultures of human neurons and glia are more accurate in representing the neurophysiology of the human brain in vivo but add some variance in the model, which needs to be taken into consideration during experimental planning. For disease modeling, inconsistencies in both study design and analyses between laboratories can hinder the reproducibility of the results. The artificial nature of reprogramming protocols makes it difficult to agree on the superiority of a single protocol. As the field progresses, the gap between the quality of in vitro and in vivo brain tissue will tighten. The methods generating brain tissue as close as possible to their in vivo counterpart will become gold-standard methodologies, which will help to harmonize culture models between laboratories and may help expedite the clinical translation of the most robust and reproducible results. However, in some cases, for example large-scale studies requiring fast and cheap protocols, a trade-off between brain tissue quality and ease of the methods may be necessary.
</p>
