<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2), encodes a large multidomain protein containing kinase and GTPase enzymatic activities. LRRK2 genetic variability is found throughout the gene but pathogenic mutations cluster in the Roc-COR and kinase domains, and account for this common form of familial parkinsonism
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>
 </sup>. All mutations lead to upregulation of LRRK2 kinase activity. Investigations of in vivo dopaminergic function with PET imaging consistently reveal increased dopamine turnover rates in asymptomatic LRRK2 heterozygotes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, those asymptomatic individuals showed reduced DAT levels, measured by the commonly used PET tracer 11C-d-threo-methylphenidate (
 <sup>11</sup>C-MP)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>
 </sup>, suggesting early dysfunction of DAT in the absence of significant loss of dopamine synthesis and storage. In rodent models, temporal overexpression of human LRRK2 p.G2019S in dopaminergic neurons impairs DAT mediated dopamine reuptake
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">126</xref>
 </sup>. Constitutive Lrrk2 p.G2019S knock-in mice also exhibit impairment in striatal dopamine reuptake at various ages
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">127</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>
 </sup>. Although there are limited number of studies that directly examine the role of LRRK2 in DAT regulation, growing evidence has established LRRK2 as an important regulator of intracellular membrane trafficking
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>
 </sup>, at a nexus between actin-dependent and tubulin-dependent cargo transport
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>
 </sup>. Mutant LRRK2 leads to dysregulated endocytic sorting
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>
 </sup> through phosphorylation of Rab proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">134</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>
 </sup> whose coordinated action critically regulates vesicular transport and endosome maturation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">136</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">137</xref>
 </sup>. LRRK2 binding to microtubules is also associated with tau phosphorylation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">138</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>
 </sup>, microtubule acetylation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">140</xref>
 </sup> and impaired axonal transport
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>
 </sup>. Hence, DAT endosomal recycling and axonal trafficking may be dysregulated by chronic LRRK2 hyperactivity. Exploring the increased (or compensatory) dopamine turnover observed in asymptomatic LRRK2 heterozygous individuals may provide mechanistic insight into the physiological and pathological role of LRRK2 in DAT regulation.
</p>
