<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RBD is another research focus of prodromal PD. Approximately 40% of PD patients have RBD and about a half may have developed prior to PD diagnosis [
 <xref rid="ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Unlike olfactory impairment and other prodromal symptoms, clinically diagnosed RBD with polysomnography (PSG) confirmation is very specific to PD or related synucleinopathy [
 <xref rid="ref057" ref-type="bibr">57, 58</xref>]. Clinical studies suggest up to 80% of PSG-confirmed RBD patients eventually develop PD, dementia with Lewy bodies, or multiple system atrophy [
 <xref rid="ref057" ref-type="bibr">57, 58</xref>]. The exact temporal relationship of RBD to PD is yet to be defined, but the leading time is likely beyond a decade. In an extreme example, evidence of RBD was found up to five decades before neurodegenerative diagnoses [
 <xref rid="ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Although this clinical link has been solidly established, the contribution of RBD to PD in the general population is yet to be defined. Clinical diagnosis of RBD requires PSG evidence, which is often infeasible in large population-based studies. Several RBD screening questionnaires have been developed with high sensitivity and specificity in clinic-based validation studies [
 <xref rid="ref060" ref-type="bibr">60–63</xref>]. However, when applied in the general population, they often gave a prevalence of 3–7% for the so-called “probable” RBD (pRBD) [
 <xref rid="ref064" ref-type="bibr">64–67</xref>], much higher than the expected ∼1% for RBD [
 <xref rid="ref068" ref-type="bibr">68, 69</xref>]. This may be largely attributed to false positives from obstructive sleep apnea or RBD mimics; on the other hand, it is also possible that RBD is underdiagnosed in the general population as patients with violent behaviors and physical injuries may be much more likely to end up in sleep clinics than those with mild symptoms [
 <xref rid="ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
