<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">The primary focus of PD research to date has been on neurons and, more specifically, nigrostriatal dopaminergic neurons. This focus is driven in part because the death of dopaminergic neurons is primarily responsible for the motor features of PD, but also because the most prominent and distinctive neuropathological findings in PD are the presence of neuronal inclusions, termed Lewy bodies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> The findings that alpha-synuclein (encoded by the gene 
 <italic>SNCA</italic>) is predominantly expressed in neurons,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> is the major component of Lewy bodies,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> and mutations in 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> give rise to autosomal dominant PD,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup> provide a key link between 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> function, neurons and disease pathogenesis. Furthermore, the identification of risk single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) at the 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> locus through genome-wide association studies (GWAS) of sporadic PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup> provides support for the importance of 
 <italic>SNCA</italic>-related pathways and, by implication, neurons in both sporadic and Mendelian forms of PD. Despite this neuronal focus, there is also growing evidence to suggest the involvement of other cell types in PD pathogenesis. In particular, astrocytes and microglia have been highlighted;
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> for instance, with a recent study demonstrating that blocking the microglial-mediated conversion of astrocytes to an A1 neurotoxic phenotype was neuroprotective in mouse models of sporadic and familial α-synucleinopathy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
