<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>If the burden of sSNVs is uniformly scattered at purely random genomic positions, genes spanning longer portions of the genome are expected to accumulate more sSNVs than genes that are smaller in size. Therefore, this age‐related accumulation of sSNVs may disproportionally affect longer genes. Beyond the effects of healthy aging, a higher degree or acceleration of sSNVs can have neuropathological effects. For example, in Cockayne syndrome, a disease associated with brain atrophy and cognitive decline, patients are affected by higher rates of sSNVs due to impaired DNA repair,
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> and this is especially the case for slow‐ or non‐proliferative cells such as neurons.
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> Although such rare genetic syndromes represent an extreme form of DNA repair dysfunction, they clearly show that genomic maintenance is an active process in neurons. There is substantial evidence for deficiencies in DNA repair in AD as well (reviewed in
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>). Analysis of sSNVs in the hippocampus has also revealed both clock‐like and oxidative stress–induced signatures, suggesting that there are factors that increase the total mutational burden over and above the typical DNA damage as part of normal aging.
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> AD‐vulnerable brain regions belong to the most metabolically active regions of the brain.
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> This high energy demand may make these regions more susceptible to oxidative stress damage as compared to other parts of the brain.
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> Of interest, (long) neuronal genes are known to selectively map to common fragile sites of genomic instability,
 <xref rid="alz12211-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> further increasing their vulnerability to DNA damage.
</p>
