<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Missense mutations in the 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> gene are the most common genetic cause of PD. The 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> G2019S mutation (c.G6055&gt;A) is found in 4% of familial cases and 1% of sporadic cases worldwide. Penetrance of 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutations is age-dependent and estimated to be 24–26% in two large scale studies [
 <xref rid="ref070" ref-type="bibr">70, 71</xref>]. The most frequent 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation G2019S has a very strong founder effect [
 <xref rid="ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In iPSC-derived DA neurons from PD patients with 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> G2019S mutation, there is increased expression of key oxidative stress response genes and 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein. Consequently, DA neurons are more sensitive to caspase-3 activation [
 <xref rid="ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The phenotype on increased oxidative stress is confirmed in an independent study [
 <xref rid="ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. G2019S mutation significantly increases the phosphorylation and activation of extracellular signal regulated kinase 1/2 (ERK1/2) in iPSC-derived DA neurons. Application of the MEK inhibitor PD0325901, which blocks ERK activation, rescues iPSC-derived neurons from degeneration and reduces cell death under oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. The phenotype on increased expression of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein [
 <xref rid="ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] is also confirmed in an independent study, which shows that knockdown of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein reduces the toxicity of 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> G2019S mutation in iPSC-derived DA neurons [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Two studies independently show that 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> G2019S mutation significantly reduces the numbers of neurites and neurite arborization [
 <xref rid="ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], as well as progressive degeneration of neurites when iPSC-derived neurons mature [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> G2019S mutation increases mitochondrial DNA damage [
 <xref rid="ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] and delays the initiation of mitophagy by affecting the pausing of damaged mitochondria being transported on microtubules [
 <xref rid="ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>].
</p>
