<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It should not have been a surprise that the biological interpretation and understanding of complex genetic risk factors would in turn be complicated; however the extent of the challenge that such a problem holds was perhaps unanticipated. The complexity of going from (usually) non-coding SNP associations in GWAs to a mechanistic understanding of that association is a difficult and multi-dimensional problem. Sometimes the gene underlying the association is almost certain (for example, SNPs in both the 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> and 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> locus show association with PD), but even there the effect of the risk haplotype is not immediately obvious. With 
 <italic>SNCA</italic>, the association seems to reflect genetic variability in 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> expression, which makes sense in terms of the pathogenic effect of gene duplications, but the precise mechanism of expression control remains unclear. With 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic>, again, expression control is likely to be involved but this has been difficult to dissect and the effect may in fact be complex and on 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> splicing. With other loci, the locus dissection is more complex still, with it often being unclear as to which gene at the locus underlies the relationship to the disease. Increasingly, simple genetic analysis to prove gene associations at a locus, need to be complemented by whole genome expression studies and bioinformatic analyses designed to understand whether any particular gene fits into pathogenic pathways. Thus, data from many sources need to be integrated: genetic data (SNP associations, plus the occurrence of rare high risk variants), gene expression studies (does the risk SNP correlate with increases or decreases in expression), protein studies (is the protein a binding partner of a known PD gene), function studies (does the protein fit into a pathway already implicated in disease). Because these data are from different fields of investigation it remains a challenge to integrate them and have a consistent and reliable view of the disease mechanism as mediated at any locus. The challenge of integrating diverse datasets is one that complex genetics faces across diseases. During the resolution of these challenges, undoubtedly, mistakes will be made, but as more loci are dissected it should make dissection of subsequent loci easier just as a jigsaw puzzle gets easier the more pieces are filled.
</p>
