<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MSA occurs sporadically, and familial cases of MSA are very rare. MSA is thus considered a sporadic disorder that involves multiple genetic and environmental factors that play roles at the molecular level. This concept raises the question of whether the genetic and environmental backgrounds for the development of MSA vary between populations. Because MSA is categorized as a synucleinopathy, as with Parkinson’s disease,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)
 </sup> genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have been performed to evaluate associations of the α-synuclein gene with MSA. The most recent GWAS enrolled 918 patients of European ancestry with MSA, but demonstrated no association between the α-synuclein gene and MSA.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)
 </sup> This negative result from the largest GWAS was in keeping with a previous study by Ozawa 
 <italic>et al.</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)
 </sup> which examined single nucleotide polymorphisms in patients of European ancestry with MSA. In a Japanese population, mutations in the coenzyme Q2 (
 <italic>COQ2</italic>) gene were identified in multiplex families and sporadic cases of MSA using a combination of linkage analysis and whole-genome sequencing.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)
 </sup>
 <italic>COQ2</italic> encodes parahydroxybenzoate polyprenyl transferase, an enzyme involved in the biosynthesis of coenzyme Q
 <sub>10</sub>. Tracing a path through the discovery of 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> mutations, the MSA Research Collaboration performed linkage analyses on six multiplex families with Japanese MSA, and whole-genome sequencing on a member of a multiplex family in whom the diagnosis of MSA had been confirmed at autopsy. The results showed a homozygous mutation and compound heterozygous mutations in 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> were identified in two multiplex families. Extending the mutational analysis of 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> to sporadic case series of MSA, including 363 patients in a Japanese series, 223 patients in a European series, and 172 patients in a North American series, a common variant (V393A) was detected in Japanese MSA, but not in European or North American MSA. Furthermore, in the Supplementary Material of the paper, the ratio of MSA-C to MSA-P was significantly higher among carriers of 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> variants than among non-carriers. In the most recent GWAS mentioned above, no association was apparent between 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> and 918 patients of European ancestry with MSA,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)
 </sup> indicating that 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> variants contribute little to the development of MSA in European populations. In the Japanese population, the V393A allele was identified in 35 of 726 alleles (4.8%) from MSA patients,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)
 </sup> so the contribution of 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> variants to disease development remains within a minority of Japanese patients with MSA-C. These observations suggest that 
 <italic>COQ2</italic> variants in addition to many other genetic or environmental factors that are yet to be discovered may underlie the increased frequency of the features of MSA-C in Japanese patients. This notion points to the need for further investigations to determine genetic or environmental factors responsible for the increased frequency of MSA-C in Japanese patients.
</p>
