<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human mtDNA is a small, circular 16,569 bp DNA encoding 13 subunits of mitochondrial respiratory chain proteins including seven complex I, one complex III, three complex IV, and two complex V subunits that are essential to the assembly and function of the mitochondrial respiratory chain [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Specific mutations in mtDNA have been found in patients with different forms of parkinsonism associated with mitochondrial disorders [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>–
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and thus, mtDNA mutations are suspected to contribute to complex I deficiency in PD. Three different types of mtDNA alterations, mtDNA point mutations, mtDNA deletions, and mtDNA copy number have been investigated in postmortem brains or peripheral tissues like blood and skeletal muscle of PD patients. Specific mtDNA regions or the entire mtDNA genome were sequenced in several studies, and numerous point mutations were described [
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>–
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. However, no specific rare variant linked to PD was identified so far. There is conflicting reports in the literature describing the association between heteroplasmic variants and PD. Coxhead et al. found an increased mutational burden in both the 
 <italic>SNpc</italic> and frontal cortex of sporadic PD patients and a significant overrepresentation of PD cases harboring nonsynonymous heteroplasmic variants in 
 <italic>MTCOX1</italic>, 
 <italic>MTCOX2</italic>, and 
 <italic>MTCYTB</italic> genes in the 
 <italic>SNpc</italic> [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. These findings could not be replicated in a recent study reporting a high frequency of heteroplasmy in the human brain, which did however not change with age or with PD disease state [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Furthermore, several groups have investigated the association of mtDNA haplogroups, aggregations of specific mtDNA variants, with PD. A reduced risk of PD was found for haplogroups J, K, and T, including a variant in the ND3 subunit of complex I, whereas the superhaplogroup HV showed an increased risk of PD [
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Moreover, not only heteroplasmic point mutations but also heteroplasmic deletions have been investigated, and a high proportion of multiple mtDNA deletions was found to accumulate in the 
 <italic>SNpc</italic> and other brain regions with age, which was significantly more abundant in PD patients [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. A recent study on human brain tissue convincingly showed a reduction of mtDNA copy number in single neurons of PD patients as compared to controls, which was more pronounced in neurons with severe complex I deficiency [
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Interestingly, the MitoPark mouse, generated by direct deletion of mitochondrial transcription factor A (TFAM), which is needed for mtDNA replication, in DA neurons, is characterized by a marked deletion of mtDNA, impairment of oxidative phosphorylation, DA neuron degeneration, and motor deficits that mimic human parkinsonism [
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. These data provide evidence for a direct role of mtDNA alterations in mitochondrial function impairments.
</p>
