<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">On the other hand, metal-gene interdependency (see Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>) explores the influence of metals on gene expression in PD. In copper hub, the expression B2M protein encoding gene with the copper concentration showed negative correlation which suggests that the decreased copper concentration increases the B2M gene expression in PD. Increased B2M has been observed in patients with Alzheimer’s disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> dementia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>, Parkinson’s diseases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>, and Schizophrenia patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Also, Zhang et al. showed B2M induced rat causes cognitive impairments, depression, and anxiety that are closely linked with Parkinson’s disease symptoms. Similar metal-gene interdependency was noticed between magnesium-TARDBP, iron-MEAF2A, aluminum-EFEMP2, and calcium-MMP9, suggesting its possible influence in PD. In addition the association between metal with SOD1 and hsCRP marker showed negative correlation which suggest decreased copper concentration increase the expression of SOD1 and hsCRP in PD (see Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Also, comparing the interdependency between B2M (copper hub protein) with SOD1 and hsCRP exhibits positive correlation (see Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). Trist
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> reports that the maturation of SOD1 is blocked by depletion in copper level in brain specific region of PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. This lead to decreased antioxidant property of SNc dopaminergic neurons against oxidative stress. Hence, inadequate copper concentration likely lead to the accumulation of copper deficient wild type SOD1 in brain. Similar results also obtained in our study that supports the decreased copper concentration causes over expression of B2M, SOD1, and hsCRP leading to PD pathogenesis.
</p>
