<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Background:</title>
  <p>Cognitive decline is a frequent complication of Parkinson’s disease (PD) and the identification of predictive biomarkers for it would help in its management.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Objective:</title>
  <p>Our aim was to analyse whether senescence markers (telomere length, p16 and p21) or their change over time could help to better predict cognitive and motor progression of newly diagnosed PD patients. We also compared these senescence markers to previously analysed markers of inflammation for the same purpose.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Methods:</title>
  <p>This study examined the association of blood-derived markers of cell senescence and inflammation with motor and cognitive function over time in an incident PD cohort (the ICICLE-PD study). Participants (154 newly diagnosed PD patients and 99 controls) underwent physical and cognitive assessments over 36 months of follow up. Mean leukocyte telomere length and the expression of senescence markers p21 and p16 were measured at two time points (baseline and 18 months). Additionally, we selected five inflammatory markers from existing baseline data.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p>We found that PD patients had shorter telomeres at baseline and 18 months compared to age-matched healthy controls which also correlated to dementia at 36 months. Baseline p16 levels were associated with faster rates of motor and cognitive decline over 36 months in PD cases, while a simple inflammatory summary score at baseline best predicted cognitive score over this same time period in PD patients.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p>Our study suggests that both inflammatory and senescence markers (p16) are valuable predictors of clinical progression in PD patients.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
