<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Evidence for native 
  <italic>α</italic>Syn assembly (multimers)
 </italic>. Bartels, Choi and Selkoe proposed in 2011 that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assembles naturally inside cells and occurs as a helical tetramer that resists aggregation [
 <xref rid="ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn was purified from various human sources, including red blood cells, under non-denaturing conditions. Several methods, most prominently analytical ultracentrifugation, sized the purified multimers as principally tetramers while circular dichroism characterized them as helical. Around the same time, tetrameric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn was purified from bacteria under non-denaturing conditions [
 <xref rid="ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn N-acetylation may be critical for the successful purification of helical 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimers from bacteria [
 <xref rid="ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Subsequent attempts of purifying helical 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies led to different results: unsuccessful in red blood cells [
 <xref rid="ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], successful in red blood cells [
 <xref rid="ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], largely unsuccessful in human brain (only evidence for small amounts of multimer) [
 <xref rid="ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], partially successful in human brain (multimeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in fractions of lower purity, but not in the highly pure material) [
 <xref rid="ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Another study probed the native state of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn from human brain by gel filtration coupled with native gradient gel separation, an array of antibodies with non-overlapping epitopes, and mass spectrometry. The authors concluded that metastable higher-molecular weight ‘conformers’ and stable monomers co-exist in the human brain [
 <xref rid="ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-10-jpd201965-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Such a model had heretofore been suggested by a nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR)/computational study [
 <xref rid="ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].
</p>
