<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given the complexity of purification, intact-cell methods became increasingly important. A live-cell crosslinking study provided a large variety of controls to suggest abundant physiological, not pathological 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. A follow-up study [
 <xref rid="ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] revealed not only that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in fresh human brain was shown to be multimeric by crosslinking but also that familial PD-linked mutations such as A30P and E46K decrease multimer:monomer ratios. In another study [
 <xref rid="ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], overexpression of strategic 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn variants that render 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn largely monomeric (plus some dimers) were cytotoxic and prone to forming inclusions in primary rat neurons. Subsequently, it was suggested that lysosomal glucocerebrosidase deficiency overall reduces 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimers and increases monomers [
 <xref rid="ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Intact-cell crosslinking typically traps 60, 80 and 100 kDa species of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn (
 <italic>α</italic>S60, -80 and -100), and their identity is not yet clear. They may be tetramer, hexamer and octamer or could all be tetramers that differ by the exact mode of crosslinking. The 60 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimer is typically the most abundant defined multimeric species of intact-cell crosslinking, consistent with a tetramer (monomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>S: 14.5 kDa; 4× 14.5 kDa = 58 kDa) [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Burré et al. sized crosslinked 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimers in brain slices, brain homogenates and recombinant 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn on charged liposomes as tetramers, octamers and other multimers, including prominent dimers [
 <xref rid="ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. This pattern differed from that typically reported for intact-cell crosslinking (see above). The same group postulated that the loss of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimerization may occur upstream of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn aggregation and neurotoxicity [
 <xref rid="ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Importantly, defined point mutations that abolish 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimer intact-cell crosslinking, also prevented 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mediated Venus/Yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) complementation [
 <xref rid="ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], an orthogonal intact-cell method. Wang et al. used 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mediated Venus YFP complementation in live neurons to demonstrate that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimers cluster synaptic vesicles and attenuate recycling [
 <xref rid="ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Similarly, Burré et al. used fluorescence resonance energy transfer revealing the detection of normal 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn multimers at membranes [
 <xref rid="ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
