<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A key concept to understanding 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn cellular behavior may be context-dependent folding [
 <xref rid="ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. For example, 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn may exists primarily as a monomer in intact enteric neurons while 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn may be present in the brain in a different conformation [
 <xref rid="ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. This view is further supported by the finding that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn (and βSyn) multimers were only efficiently trapped by crosslinking of intact neurons, whereas crosslinking of lysates largely yielded monomers [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. This observation was unique to the synuclein isoforms (control multimeric proteins were trapped both in cells and lysates) and in line with the concept of metastable or ‘dynamic’ multimers, a model also postulated by others [
 <xref rid="ref064" ref-type="bibr">64, 69</xref>]. The requirement of molecular crowding or a limiting factor that holds intracellular multimers together would be a possible explanation for the lysis sensitivity and difficulties in purifying multimeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn. Of note, several independent reports suggest that (re)folding and (re)assembly of helical 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> might be possible: 1) Killinger et al. suggested that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn forms multimers during electrophoresis, possibly due to crowding effects [
 <xref rid="ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], 2) Iljina et al. used arachidonic acid to reconstitute 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> that sized as tetramers [
 <xref rid="ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and 3) Rovere et al. proposed a mechanism in which helical 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn folding at membranes is preserved when 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn comes off membranes and hydrophobic interactions may drive cytosolic assembly that is stable for an undetermined amount of time [
 <xref rid="ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].
</p>
