<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Primordial germ cells that enter the female fetal gonad expand and become oogonia, which initiate meiosis in asynchronous waves from the 12th to the 24th week of gestation 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Fetal oocytes initiate and complete (pre)meiotic S phase and meiotic recombination during prophase I prior to arresting at the dictyate stage (G2/M; 
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>-Female) 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Prior to birth, oocytes undergo nest breakdown and become surrounded by supporting cells (pre-granulosa cells) to form primordial follicles. This is associated with substantial germ cell loss. Of the 5–7 million oogonia, 2 million primordial follicles are left at birth and an estimated 250,000–500,000 are present at the onset of menarche (puberty), and depletion of the ovarian reserve occurs by 50–52 years (menopause). Throughout life, primordial follicles are recruited for growth; however, a single follicle matures to ovulate an egg once per month only from menarche until menopause (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. At ovulation, the oocyte resumes and completes meiosis I, where homologous chromosomes segregate to reduce the genome content by half to form a haploid egg 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Upon fertilization, the oocyte resumes meiosis II and segregates sister chromatids and the zygote is formed (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>-embryo). In human females, meiosis can last up to five decades and the extended dictyate arrest leads to a high degree of genome instability. This is in contrast to males, where stem cell renewal lasts a lifetime and is followed by a relatively short meiotic program to produce haploid sperm 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.
</p>
