<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the discovery of cell-to-cell spreading of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers, targeting extracellular protein aggregates to promote their clearance has been an active area of research. Studies involving both active and passive immunotherapy are being performed in preclinical settings. Developing antibodies that will specifically target the oligomeric forms of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and using them for passive immunotherapy are getting more attraction. However, obtaining highly specific antibodies is a challenging task raising important questions to consider: would antibodies detecting common structural elements of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers be more beneficial? Or should developing antibodies specific to distinct o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies be favored? In addition, several key variables can affect the outcome of such approaches including the delivery route of immunotherapy, internalization or cellular uptake of the antibody and the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> localization of the targeted oligomeric species [
 <xref rid="ref213" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. Detection of o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in the CSF and blood plasma raises the possibility of early detection of pathological changes occurring in the CNS. To this end, probes specifically targeting o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn with high sensitivity and high affinity hold great promise [
 <xref rid="ref214" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. Of note, it is important to indicate here that higher CSF 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn concentrations can be linked to blood contamination due to the expression of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in erythrocytes [
 <xref rid="ref215" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>], thereby requiring strict and rigorous markers for blood contamination and/or a standardized grade system for blood levels in CSF samples. Studies are also being performed to find molecules blocking the endocytosis of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers, thus preventing healthy cells from taking up pathogenic 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species, which could serve as a potential strategy for reducing oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mediated toxicity [
 <xref rid="ref214" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>].
</p>
