<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Molecules that can modulate the aggregation process by decreasing the load of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers have also been considered as therapeutic potential. The diphenyl-pyrazole molecule anle138b [3-(1,3-benzodioxol-5-yl)-5-(3-bromophenyl)-1H-pyrazole], an oligomer modulator was shown to inhibit 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomer formation both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref216" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>]. This molecule strongly inhibited the formation and accumulation of o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and neuronal degeneration thereby suppressing disease progression in the TgA30P PD transgenic mouse model [
 <xref rid="ref216" ref-type="bibr">216, 217</xref>]. Based on spectral emission properties in presence of o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn, the authors proposed that this molecule targets directly o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref216" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>], a hypothesis which was further supported by all-atom molecular dynamic simulations [
 <xref rid="ref218" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. Both studies suggest Anle138b as a promising disease-modifying agent not only for synucleinopathies, but also for other amyloid forming proteins as reported recently for PrP
 <sup>C</sup>, Aβ and tau [
 <xref rid="ref216" ref-type="bibr">216, 218–221</xref>]. Several other molecules such as NPT100-18A and NPT200-11 have also been reported as promising therapeutic agents that modulate o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn formation. Among these, the small molecule 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn misfolding inhibitor, NPT200-11 (Neuropore Therapies Inc./UCB), produced multiple benefits in the TgWT mice overexpressing 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> (line 61) used as model of PD [
 <xref rid="ref203" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>], including attenuation of motor deficits and rescue of striatal dopamine transporter expression [
 <xref rid="ref222" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>]. While the phase 1 clinical trial assessing safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics of NPT200-11 was completed on February 2016 (NCT02606682; see for review [
 <xref rid="ref223" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>]), no results have been reported as of yet. Other promising inhibitors of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn aggregation currently tested in phase 1 clinical trials include PBT434 (Alterity Therapeutic; U1111–1211-0052) and ENT-01 (Enterin; NCT03938922); both started last year. Curcumin, a natural polyphenolic antioxidant derived from turmeric, has demonstrated anti-inflammatory and neuroprotective effects in the Tg2576 AD mouse model despite poor bioavailability and presumably-poor blood-brain barrier penetrance of the parent compound [
 <xref rid="ref224" ref-type="bibr">224–226</xref>]. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic>, curcumin and its analogs have been shown to bind to pre-formed 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers and to reduce their toxicity by modulating their morphologies and biophysical properties [
 <xref rid="ref227" ref-type="bibr">227, 228</xref>]. Molecular chaperones, including heat shock proteins (HSPs), have also been considered as potential therapeutic alternatives against oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mediated toxicity [
 <xref rid="ref229" ref-type="bibr">229</xref>]. Proof of principle studies in which overexpressing the chaperone HSP104 proved to be a safe approach in protecting dopaminergic neurons by disassembling o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in a lentivirus-mediated A30P-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn rat model of PD supported this view [
 <xref rid="ref230" ref-type="bibr">230</xref>]. Molecules regulating HSP70 or HSP90 activity were also shown to be effective by lowering o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn levels and their associated toxicity in a rat model of parkinsonism [
 <xref rid="ref231" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>]. Such molecules might serve as effective therapeutic strategy for synucleinopathies.
</p>
