<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epidemiological, clinical, and animal studies provided a comprehensive picture of the anti-Parkinsonian potential of caffeine. A recent genome-wide association and interaction study (GWAIS) identified
 <italic> GRIN2A</italic>, which encodes an NMDA-glutamate-receptor subunit involved in brain's excitatory neurotransmission, as a PD genetic modifier in inverse association with caffeine intake (
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sub>interaction</sub> = 3 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup>) [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. This result was questioned by another group that performed a reanalysis of the same data by examining the association between coffee and rs4998386 separately in cases and controls. This group found a strong positive association in controls between rs4998386-T and heavy coffee drinking (OR = 1.48, 95% CI [1.23–1.78]). On the contrary, among PD cases, heavy coffee drinking tended to be less frequent in carriers of the rs4998386-T allele, but this association was not statistically significant (OR = 0.82, 95% CI [0.65–1.03]). Therefore, it appeared that the interaction between rs4998386 and coffee consumption was in part explained by a positive association between the rs4998386-T allele and coffee consumption among controls, but not among PD cases [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. An independent study replicated the reported association of a single nucleotide polymorphism,
 <italic> GRIN2A</italic> rs4998386, and its interaction with caffeine intake with PD in patient-control study in an ethnically homogenous population in southeastern Sweden in 193 sporadic PD patients and 377 controls. There was also a strong significance in joint effects of gene and caffeine on PD risk (TC heavy caffeine versus CC light caffeine: OR = 0.38, 95% CI [0.20–0.70], 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.002) and gene-caffeine interaction (OR = 0.998, 95% CI [0.991–0.999], 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>].
</p>
