<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47">The 
 <italic>LINC-PINT</italic> locus was not previously identified in a GWAS of neuropathological AD endophenotypes that included CAA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], however there are several key differences in the approaches used. The prior study included both AD cases and controls, a binary CAA phenotype (presence/absence) was employed, and neither sex nor 
 <italic>APOE</italic>ε4- stratified analyses were reported. We were likewise unable to identify association of the 
 <italic>LINC-PINT</italic> locus in a collection of individuals that did not meet neuropathological criteria for AD (non-AD). However we note that the level of CAA in these individuals is very low and postulate that the 
 <italic>LINC-PINT</italic> variant may not afford discernable protection from vascular amyloid pathology in the absence of ADNC. Alternatively, any protection provided by this 
 <italic>LINC-PINT</italic> variant may be difficult to detect due to the already lower levels of CAA in these non-AD individuals. Previous studies have indicated that 
 <italic>APOE</italic>ε4 and ADNC are differentially associated with CAA when in the presence (CAA type I) or absence (CAA type II) of capillary involvement [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In the collection of AD cases studied here with advanced ADNC (88% Braak stage ≥ 5; 84% Thal phase = 5) a minority of cases (N = 11) had a CAA score of four, indicative of capillary involvement. The removal of these individuals did not substantially impact our key findings. Further studies in expanded cohorts will be needed to evaluate our findings in the context of disease (AD, non-AD, Control), capillary CAA, and disease severity (degree of AD neuropathologic change). The observed association for the 
 <italic>LINC-PINT</italic> variant in AD cases lacking the 
 <italic>APOE</italic>ε4 risk allele highlights the importance of stratification based on risk factors to discover novel loci that behave in a context-specific manner [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].
</p>
