<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Only participants enrolled by 2015 were included in this analysis. A similar approach using the same research database was previously described [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. We tested the association with more than 1000 well-curated phenotypes (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0241552.s002">S2 Table</xref>), which were distributed among different phenotypic categories (e.g. cognitive, autoimmune, psychiatric etc.). GWAS were previously performed on these well-curated phenotypes and confirmed to replicate known associations and not to generate spurious false positives. For our standard PheWAS, we restricted participants to a set of individuals who have &gt; 97% European ancestry, as determined through an analysis of local ancestry [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Briefly, this algorithm first partitioned phased genomic data into short windows of about 100 SNPs. Within each window, we used a support vector machine (SVM) to classify individual haplotypes into one of 31 reference populations. The SVM classifications were then fed into a hidden Markov model (HMM) accounting for switch errors and incorrect assignments as well as generating probabilities for each reference population in each window. Finally, we used simulated admixed individuals to recalibrate the HMM probabilities so that the reported assignments were consistent with the simulated admixture proportions. The reference population data is derived from public datasets (the Human Genome Diversity Project, HapMap, and 1000 Genomes–participants provided informed consent and all data was completely anonymized and de-identified before access and analysis), as well as 23andMe customers who have reported having four grandparents from the same country. A maximal set of unrelated individuals was chosen for each phenotype using a segmental identity-by-descent (IBD) estimation algorithm [
 <xref rid="pone.0241552.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Individuals were defined as related if they shared more than 700 cM IBD, including regions where the two individuals shared either one or both genomic segments identical-by-descent. This level of relatedness (roughly 20% of the genome) corresponded approximately to the minimal expected sharing between first cousins in an outbred population.
</p>
