<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 2011, Singleton and coworkers utilized five GWAS data-sets to identify five novel loci that modify PD risk, at the same time confirming variations in previously reported genes such as SNCA, LRRK2, BST1, HLA-DRB5, GAK and MAPT [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. One of the novel loci was ACMSD, where an SNP (rs6710823) proximal to the 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> gene was found to be significantly associated with PD risk. Several GWAS have been undertaken in different populations since then, in order to identify new, as well as confirm previously reported risk loci. At least four different SNPs in the same region in close proximity to 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> have been identified to be associated with PD risk, demonstrating that variation in this region genuinely affect PD risk [
 <xref rid="ref017" ref-type="bibr">17–20</xref>]. In 2014, Nalls et al. verified and replicated 28 risk variants for PD across 24 loci, with an SNP (rs6430538) close to 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> being one among them (odds ratio (OR): 0.875), in a combined patient cohort size of 13,708 PD patients and 95,282 controls [
 <xref rid="ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The most recent, very large study [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] compared 26,035 PD cases with 403,190 controls (including both novel cohorts and meta-analysis) and verified the same SNP, rs6430538, in proximity of 
 <italic>ACMSD,</italic> to be significantly linked to PD risk (OR:0.88). The study refers to the locus as the 
 <italic>TMEM163</italic> locus because genetic variation at this site was associated with variation in 
 <italic>TMEM163</italic> gene expression in normal brain tissue (in the GTex eQTL database) [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Typically, promoters regulate the expression of multiple genes, both in 
 <italic>cis</italic> and 
 <italic>trans</italic> location, and therefore the same locus still might regulate 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> expression, as well as additional genes. Notably, as noted by the authors of this study [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], currently available eQTL data is insufficient to determine expression during diseases triggers and stages, as well as in multiple cell types of importance. In short, more in-depth transcriptomic and eQTL investigations in specific cell populations, under normal and disease states, are required to determine whether the implicated SNPs in this region increases PD risk via differential 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> expression.
</p>
