<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It has been argued that compensatory mechanisms may effectively counteract nigrostriatal dysfunction at the onset of cellular dysfunction and decline of striatal dopamine, thus delaying the appearance of overt parkinsonism for many years [
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33, 34</xref>]. Although slight motor abnormalities such as reduced arm swing, changes in walking patterns, stiffness, tremor, or bradykinesia may precede clinical PD, such signs, captured by routine clinical assessment for parkinsonism [
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], often referred to as subtle motor impairment or mild parkinsonian signs, may be found in as many as 40% of the elderly population [
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36, 37</xref>]. In several studies mild parkinsonian signs have been associated with both other PD risk markers as well as with an increased risk for incident PD itself [
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16, 37</xref>]. These signs, however, are quite unspecific in the general population. This may be different when motor tests are applied to enriched cohorts with an apriori increased risk for PD. Prospective studies in subjects with idiopathic RBD have shown that in those who converted to clinically defined PD, impaired motor performance was detected 6–9 years before diagnosis using the Purdue Pegboard, alternate-t p and timed up-and-go test [
 <xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Similarly, a more recent study by the same group following 89 idiopathic RBD patients over ten years found a 3.9 fold risk to develop PD, dementia with Lewy-bodies (DLB) or multiple system atrophy (MSA) in those with subtle motor impairment at baseline [
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Using accelerometry-based evaluation of gait and stance, two cross-sectional studies found altered gait variability [
 <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], trunk acceleration and smoothness of sway [
 <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] under challenging conditions in otherwise asymptomatic LRRK2 mutation carriers and subjects with hyperechogenicity of the SN. Noyce and colleagues used an algorithm based on an online survey to categorise participants according to their putative PDrisk [
 <xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] in the definition of their prospective PREDICT-PD study cohort [
 <xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In a cross-sectional baseline analysis, the 100 highest-risk participants had significantly reduced tapping speed in a novel computer keyboard-tapping task versus the 100 lowest-risk participants [
 <xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Quantifiable motor tests may therefore eventually become useful as a screening element to select at-risk subjects for further secondary screens with more specific tests like DAT imaging.
</p>
