<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Our analysis of 385 iPSC-derived cell lines from 67 published studies reveals that many PD neuronal phenotypes are shared between genetically heterogeneous familial and sporadic patients (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Notably, impairments in mechanisms involved in cellular waste recycling, mitochondrial function, neuronal morphology and physiology, and sensitivity to reactive oxygen species (ROS) are most common across patient lines with varying genetic predispositions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). The studies measured cellular phenotypes that occurred either spontaneously or in response to chemicals mimicking cellular aging and stress (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, c</xref>). It is important to note that the frequency of reported phenotypes in our meta-analysis may be biased because only few studies (~19%, 13/67) reported negative results (absence of phenotypes)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, most cell lines were not systematically phenotyped without prior hypothesis and thus, there is likely to be an ascertain bias in these phenotypes. Less hypothesis-driven multimodal or omics analysis will help to address such bias
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>
 </sup>. Phenotypes caused by genomic predispositions allude to crosstalk and impairments in multiple pathways that act collectively to mediate selective degeneration of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>) and will be discussed in detail below.
</p>
