<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The QPN (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rpq-qpn.ca/en/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rpq-qpn.ca/en/</ext-link>) collects data and samples through 4 main channels: the QPN Questionnaire (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Material</xref>), medical records of patients enrolled in the QPN Participant Registry, research projects facilitated by the QPN (described later), and the NeurO C-BIGR (see Methods). In addition, other data are being collected for all patients, or in some cases for subgroups of patients, such as genetic, imaging, neuropsychological and neuropsychiatric data etc. Genetic data are being collected from all patients for whom DNA is available (currently &gt;800 patients, out of &gt;1,200 patients that have been enrolled by the completion of this paper), including genotyping using a custom single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array with &gt;700,000 SNPs (Backbone of the OmniExpress array with custom content of the NeuroX SNP-chop, Illumina, Inc.), and targeted next generation sequencing of ∼50 PD-related genes, including 
 <italic>GBA</italic>, 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic>, 
 <italic>SNCA, MAPT</italic> and others [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23–25</xref>]. For a large number of patients (currently  400), peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) are being collected, and iPSCs and neuronal models are being generated by the MNI-iPSC platform (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mniopenresearch.org/articles/3-1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://mniopenresearch.org/articles/3-1</ext-link>) for specific studies as required. These data and bio-samples are being made available by applying for specific research projects through the QPN website and obtaining approval from the QPN scientific committee and the tissue and data committee of the Neuro C-BIGR. The success of our model may encourage funding of similar initiative, preferably in under-represented parts of the world where clinical and genetic data on PD patients are less available.
</p>
