<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Glycation, via the Maillard reaction, named after Louis C. Maillard who first described the browning processes in food processing [
 <xref rid="ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], involves the non-enzymatic reaction of reducing carbohydrates and amino compounds. In fact, it is not a single reaction but a complex series of reactions that was studied for decades, mainly in the context of food browning and is lately also receiving attention due to its role in neurodegenerative diseases [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14, 15</xref>]. These Maillard reactions were characterized and grouped into a scheme [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In the first step, a carbonyl group (from glucose or other reactive carbonyl species) condenses with an amino or thiol group of amino acids, nucleic acids or amino lipids, giving rise to an early glycation product termed Amadori compound. In the second step of the reaction, the intermediate Amadori compound is rearranged and breaks down in one of several possible chemical pathways. A variety of different carbonyl and dicarbonyl intermediate products, including glyoxal and methylglyoxal (MGO) are formed, and can exist free or bound to proteins. Lastly, higher molecular weight species (advanced glycation end products (AGEs)) are formed from these lower molecular weight intermediates [
 <xref rid="ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Importantly, other pathways and mechanisms including oxidative stress also contribute to the formation of reactive carbonyl species [
 <xref rid="ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. As mentioned above, glycation can affect various biomolecules. While proteins are important targets of glycation (the N-terminal residue, the amino group of lysine residues, and the guanidinium group of arginine residues can be subject to Maillard modifications), DNA [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19, 20</xref>] and lipids [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] can also be subject to glycation.
</p>
