<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Gliosis is a cardinal feature in post mortem brains of PD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> as well as a prodromal feature in the early-stage PD patients and DLB patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Several cytokines with stimulatory properties—for example, IL-6 and TNF-α—are increased in PD patient sera and are correlated with the severity of the nonmotor symptoms in PD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Recent genome-wide association studies have also uncovered genetic overlaps in PD patients and patients suffering from autoimmune disorders
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. In mouse models of synucleinopathy, we, as well as other groups, have reported robust inflammation in the end-stage mice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>, and treatment with immunomodulatory agents prevented αSyn pathology
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. These lines of evidence generally point to inflammatory signaling as a possible etiological factor in synucleinopathies. Our study was designed to test whether Il-10 overexpression initiated before the onset of neuropathology or phenotypes would be able to suppress inflammation and ameliorate αSyn pathologies in the M83 model. Our approach in this study was to use recombinant AAVs to express Il-10 based on its future translational potential as a vector for gene therapy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Further, the AAV gene targeting approach allowed us to restrict Il-10 expression to the CNS, thereby limiting its effect only to the target organ and minimizing off-target effects on peripheral immunity. Contrary to our expectations, we uncovered a detrimental effect of intraspinal Il-10 expression in our synucleinopathy models. We specifically found that Il-10 overexpression in the spinal cord of homozygous M83+/+ mice leads to gliosis, moribund condition, and early death. In the second model where hemizygous M83+/− mice were seeded peripherally with preformed αSyn fibrils, we found that Il-10 expression similarly led to reduced lifespan. In both cases, Il-10-mediated accelerated death was not accompanied by increased αSyn inclusion pathology in mice phenotypically matched for paralysis with control cohorts, revealing an interesting dichotomy between neurodegenerative cascade and proteinopathy in the context of neuroinflammation. Previously, we have reported that AAV-Il-10 worsened Alzheimer’s disease (AD) pathology without affecting lifespan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Intracranial Il-10 expression in this model worsened amyloid β pathology by reducing microglial phagocytic activity and increasing ApoE sequestration within the extracellular amyloid β plaques
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. On the other hand, intraspinal AAV-Il-10 (the same construct used in this study and ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>) expression delayed paralysis and increased lifespan in the SOD1 model of ALS through moderating inflammatory chemokine signaling pathways
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, the phenotypic and neuropathologic outcomes of Il-10 signaling were widely disparate in these different neurodegenerative models, in spite of the fact that these experiments were performed on similar genetic backgrounds of mixed C57Bl6 lineage. Taken together, these observations serve as exemplars of the immunoproteostasis paradigm, whereby the same immune mediator can differentially influence the pathologic outcome based on the type of neurodegenerative proteinopathy and the context of the proteinopathy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
