<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Our study opens up an intriguing question surrounding the relative roles of immune cells in the αSyn aggregate-seeded model. Extensive immunohistochemical examination of microglial and astrocytic proliferation showed that, in spite of having predominantly immunosuppressive properties in the peripheral immune system
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, vIl-10 robustly upregulated microglial number in the spinal cord and midbrain of αSyn-seeded mice coinciding with increased intracellular αSyn inclusions and parenchymal αSyn levels. First, this would suggest that preconditioning the CNS of a neurodegenerative proteinopathy model with a cytokine having immunosuppressive properties does not necessarily dampen gliosis. Second, it is tempting to suggest that chronic immunosuppression can result in reduced microglial clearance of αSyn leading to intracellular pathologies, which then leads to increased microgliosis as a form of non-cell-autonomous response to the escalating proteinopathy. This would be consistent with our earlier report where we found that inflammatory preconditioning of the CNS by Interleukin-6 restricted the seeding and transmission of αSyn in the brain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Such non-cell-autonomous effects of immune cells on neuronal proteinopathy is especially apparent in mouse models of ALS
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. It is noteworthy that Il-10 itself did not increase microgliosis in the brain or spinal cord or promoted synucleinopathy in the seeded model. Interestingly, neither Il-10 nor vIl-10 triggered astrogliosis in the spinal cord relative to GFP-expressing control mice. This highlights a clear disconnect between how microglia and astrocytes respond to the immune stimulus in different areas of the neuraxis. Such differential proliferation properties of microglia and astrocytes in response to vIl-10 and Il-10 underscores the complex role of immune signaling in neurodegenerative cascades. Future work based on spatial profiling techniques or single-cell-based techniques could clarify how microglial and astrocytic functions are differentially regulated in a spatial–temporal context and contribute to the pathologic trajectory of synucleinopathies.
</p>
