<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The fact that LRRK2 is a large multidomain protein suggests that it has numerous functions within the cell. However, its physiological roles are still poorly understood, as are the aspects of its functions that are relevant for PD. In-line with the hypothesis that mitochondrial and lysosomal dysfunction underlie PD, an emerging body of data supports a key role for LRRK2 at these organelles. Work has shown that patient-derived fibroblasts from G2019S carriers display abnormal mitochondrial morphology and function [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Likewise, this same LRRK2 mutation has been shown to increase mitochondrial DNA damage in human-derived cells [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The abnormal mitochondrial phenotype is also present in mice with aged G2019S knock-in animals displaying hallmarks of impaired fission and altered dynamics [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Mutations of LRRK2 have also been shown to alter lysosomal function (
 <xref rid="BST-49-551F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> — lysosomal function). In various 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models of the G2019S mutation, enlarged lysosomes were reported, suggesting a strong link between LRRK2 and lysosomal function [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. A recent 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study with neuronal primary cultures identified LRRK2 as an interactor with the a1 subunit of the Vacuolar ATPase [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. In that article, the authors show that the R1441C mutation, but not the G2019S, leads to an increased lysosomal pH and consequently a decreased lysosomal function, though this effect appears independent of the kinase activity of LRRK2. In contrast, it was also reported that the G2019S mutation modestly alters lysosomal morphology and acidification, and that this effect is dependent on the kinase activity of LRRK2 [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Here, the defect in lysosomal function disrupted Cathepsin B and L mediated turnover and led to an accumulation of insoluble α-synuclein. Furthermore, LRRK2 kinase activity has also been reported to reduce GBA1 activity in neurons derived from patients, through its substrate Rab10, and this effect was dependent on LRRK2 kinase activity [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Additionally, LRRK2 kinase activity plays a key role in phagosome maturation and lysosomal trafficking [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>] and recent work has shown LRRK2 interacts with the motor protein adaptor JIP4 at lysosomes to regulate lysosomal tubulation in a process termed LYTL (lysosomal tubulation/sorting driven by LRRK2 [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]) (
 <xref rid="BST-49-551F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> — fusion with the lysosome, and 
 <xref rid="BST-49-551F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). In relation to intracellular trafficking and the cytoskeleton, LRRK2 PD mutants have previously been shown 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> to display a higher microtubule association compared with WT LRRK2 [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. This was recently confirmed with the high-resolution structure of the catalytic portion of LRRK2, showing microtubule binding through its WD40 domain [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Lastly, microtubule-based signalling and ciliogenesis was disrupted in LRRK2 R1441C knock-in mice, which displayed decreased ciliation in cholinergic neurons in the striatum [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Taken together, these data suggest an important link between LRRK2 and microtubules, which in turn could have consequences for mitochondria and lysosomes.
</p>
