<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The above evidence suggests that impaired stress-induced Parkin-dependent mitophagy could be a contributing factor to PD pathology. However, we have previously shown that mitophagy occurs 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> in the absence of overt stress, under so-called basal conditions, in a manner that is independent of PINK1 and Parkin [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. It is reasonable to assume that both impaired stress-induced mitophagy and impaired basal mitophagy can lead to the accumulation of dysfunctional mitochondria and reduced cellular health. If so, then compromised basal mitophagy could also be an important contributing factor for PD development. This may well be the case, as we recently showed that LRRK2 kinase activity inversely correlates with basal levels of mitophagy in specific organs and cell types 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="BST-49-551F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> — basal mitophagy). Using mitophagy (
 <italic>mito</italic>-QC) and autophagy (
 <italic>auto</italic>-QC) reporter mice we were able to show that the common pathogenic G2019S LRRK2 mutation, which results in increased kinase activity, reduced basal mitophagy in cells and tissues of clinical relevance, including midbrain DA neurons and microglial cells [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. In contrast, the absence of LRRK2 resulted in increased basal mitophagy in these same cell types. Interestingly, this phenomenon was not observed in all cell types, implying cell, and tissue-specific consequences for LRRK2 activity. Importantly though, using a next-generation LRRK2 inhibitor, GSK3357679A, we were able to correct the mitophagy defect in LRRK2 G2019S-expressing mice and restore mitophagy to wild type levels in both DA neurons and microglia. The effect of LRRK2 on mitophagy potentially appears to be selective, as general macroautophagy seems to be largely unaffected both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>] and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. This suggests a significant disruption of lysosomal function is not occurring.
</p>
