<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A major question remaining concerns how LRRK2 kinase activity regulates basal mitophagy (and indeed how it regulates other cellular processes). It is not yet clear whether LRRK2 activity plays a direct mitophagic role via regulating autophagy machinery, or more indirect through disruption of mitochondrial movement/function or membrane trafficking in general. However, a subset of Rab GTPases were recently identified to be key substrates of the LRRK2 kinase [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Rab GTPases are master regulators of vesicular trafficking and thus ideally placed to regulate and influence auto-lysosomal pathways [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Their interaction with LRRK2 has been extensively reviewed recently [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Notably, LRRK2 has been shown to phosphorylate Rab12 [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>] and SQSTM1/p62 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Rab12 is a positive regulator for autophagy that regulates mTORC1 activity, a sensor for nutrient availability and key inhibitor of starvation-induced autophagy [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Additionally, Rab12 has also been shown to directly interact with autophagosomes and influence their trafficking [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. p62 was the first autophagy cargo receptor described in mammals and is thought to be important in regulating the incorporation of cellular components into forming autophagosomes [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Thus, LRRK2 substrates are known to regulate autophagy but further work is needed to determine if, and how, their regulation by LRRK2 impacts this process.
</p>
