<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">Genome instability leading to 
 <italic>de novo</italic> single nucleotide variants, insertion/deletions, 
 <italic>de novo</italic> copy number variants and aneuploidies are inferred to occur both in the germline 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> as well as during the mitotic divisions in the preimplantation embryo 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>; however, the vast majority of these genomic constellations are unlikely to be seen in live births. 25% of all clinically-recognized pregnancies end in loss and at least half of these are due to aneuploidy, including those affecting chromosomes that are not seen in live births 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Continuous improvements of single-cell sequencing technologies are providing new insights into the origins and incidence of genomic changes that are generated in human germ cells and preimplantation embryos 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> (
 <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>; 
 <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). With increased genetic testing of preimplantation embryos, new estimates suggest that at least half of blastocyst embryos have genomic alterations that may explain the high incidence of preclinical pregnancy losses 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. These are mainly aneuploidies as well as very large copy number variants (10 Mpb or larger). More recently, CRISPR-Cas9 has been used for genome editing in human embryos; whilst its use for heritable genome editing remains highly controversial, as a research tool it will facilitate our understanding of DNA repair capacity in human embryos 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>.
</p>
