<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">Beyond association studies and GI dysbiosis, PD and IBD patients exhibit similar intestinal and peripheral phenotypes especially in the context of inflammation and gut permeability that are summarized in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. PD and CD patients exhibit increased intestinal permeability potentially due to disruptions and decreased expression of tight junction proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. In CD, tight junction proteins present distinct patterns of distribution with claudin-2 highly upregulated in inflamed epithelium, and claudin-3 and -4 downregulated and redistributed in diseased epithelial cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. In parallel, claudin-5 and -8 are downregulated and localized away from the tight junction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>, while occludin and zona occludens-1 (ZO-1) are significantly reduced in CD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. IFNγ contributes to decreased ZO-1 and occludin by causing increased internalization of the proteins away from the epithelium membrane in CD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. In PD, studies have shown similar phenotypes with a reduction of occludin and redistribution of both occludin and ZO-1 in colonic biopsies from PD patients relative to healthy controls
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>; however, further studies are needed to fully assess the epithelial barrier of PD patients. We would predict that the severity of disruption in the intestinal tight junction proteins may be correlated with disease pathology which may serve as a potential biomarker for PD prior to the onset of disabling motor PD symptoms.
</p>
