<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A staged process was followed to generate a consensus statement about PD care in MENASA countries. The methodology applied to synthesize the assessed needs was adapted from that used previously by a European expert group in multiple sclerosis (MS) [
 <xref rid="ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In brief, the following steps were undertaken:
 <list list-type="simple" id="list0005">
  <list-item id="listitem0005">
   <label>1)</label>
   <p>Taskforce members were asked to complete strength, weaknesses, opportunities, threats (SWOT) analysis about PD care in the MENASA countries. The SWOT analysis was based on pilot data obtained from a previously conducted MDS survey [
    <xref rid="ref010" ref-type="bibr">10, 11</xref>]. The majority of the members who participated in the SWOT analysis are clinicians (
    <italic>n</italic> = 11), one is a specialist PD nurse, and another is a physiotherapist PD researcher. The two allied health professionals are from countries (Jordan and Saudi Arabia) where clinicians from the same countries are also members of the task force. Additionally, all members have extensive experience working with people with PD and are very knowledgeable of the current situation in their respective countries [
    <xref rid="ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]; thus, this step was essential to provide needed data.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="listitem0010">
   <label>2)</label>
   <p>Following the SWOT analysis, members were invited to participate in 2 teleconferences and one face-to-face workshop, these occurred between February 2017 and October 2017. Discussions on the first teleconference, which was followed by the face-to-face workshop, focused on the SWOT analysis outcome as well as published literature. This cross-check method between the SWOT analysis and the literature overview helped to identify the most critical goals, unmet needs, and areas for development in PD care.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="listitem0015">
   <label>3)</label>
   <p>The second teleconference in particular, which was conducted at the end, focused on prioritizing critical goals and unmet needs of the consensus statement based on a voting system. This means the task force needs to establish what is considered a list of needs and priorities in the advancement of the Movement Disorders field in general and PD care in specific in the region. To accomplish this important step, each member of the task force was asked to use five votes. These votes can be allocated in any combination among the items listed in 
    <xref rid="jpd-10-jpd191751-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> (items were formulated based on the task force SWOT analysis and the survey results [
    <xref rid="ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]). This process meant that multiple votes could be allocated to one item, and in this case, prioritization of relative item importance could be established.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
