<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>cis</italic>‐acting spatial eQTLs were also found to regulate 143 genes, including genes with published connections to PD. Some of these genes might modulate the disease process and progression as the 3 noncoding 
 <italic>cis</italic> SNPs (rs9628662, rs762488, rs2009578) within the 
 <italic>GBA</italic> locus form a haplotype that is significantly correlated with age of symptom onset and the age at diagnosis. Individuals who are homozygous for minor/alternate genotype alleles display a ~ 5‐year delay of symptom onset and diagnosis, while heterozygous individuals show an intermediate degree of disease delay (~2.9 years for onset and 2.4 years for diagnosis), suggestive of a transcriptional dose‐effect (Fig. 
 <xref rid="mds28144-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). Surprisingly, despite acting as spatial eQTLs, these SNPs do not regulate 
 <italic>GBA</italic> expression in the brain. However, they do modulate the expression of other genes within the brain that include 
 <italic>DNAJC6</italic> [
 <italic>PARK19</italic>], 
 <italic>MSTO1</italic>, 
 <italic>NF1</italic>, 
 <italic>PRKG1</italic>, 
 <italic>RANBP3</italic>, 
 <italic>RUSC1</italic>‐
 <italic>AS1</italic>, 
 <italic>S100A1</italic>, 
 <italic>THBS3</italic> (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="mds28144-supitem-0006" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>), some of which are PD associated (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="mds28144-supitem-0006" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>). Moreover, these spatial eQTLs also regulate expression of 
 <italic>GBA</italic> and other genes in peripheral tissues (Fig. 
 <xref rid="mds28144-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Therefore, the mechanism of the haplotype‐specific delayed disease onset/diagnosis could result from (1) altered expression of potential modifier genes in the central nervous system and/or peripheral tissues, (2) increased 
 <italic>GBA</italic> expression in the blood, (3) decreased 
 <italic>GBA</italic> expression in peripheral tissues other than blood, or (4) a combination of these.
</p>
