<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-0640</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7330713</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00539</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring the Genomic Architectures of Health, Physical Traits and Antisocial Behavioral Outcomes: A Brief Report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tielbeek</surname><given-names>Jorim J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/837527"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boutwell</surname><given-names>Brian B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/838537"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Department of Complex Trait Genetics, Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research, Amsterdam Neuroscience, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</institution>, <addr-line>Amsterdam</addr-line>, <country>Netherlands</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Criminal Justice and Legal Studies, School of Applied Sciences, University of Mississippi</institution>, <addr-line>University, MS</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>John D. Bower School of Population Health, University of Mississippi Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Jackson, MS</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: No&#x000e8;lia Fern&#x000e0;ndez-Castillo, Centre for Biomedical Network Research (CIBER), Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Lisabeth Fisher DiLalla, Southern Illinois University Carbondale, United States; Riley L. Marshall, Southern Illinois University, United States, in collaboration with reviewer LD; Hyun Ruisch, University of Groningen, Netherlands</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Brian B. Boutwell, <email xlink:href="mailto:bbboutwe@olemiss.edu" xlink:type="simple">bbboutwe@olemiss.edu</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Behavioral and Psychiatric Genetics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychiatry</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>539</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Tielbeek and Boutwell</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tielbeek and Boutwell</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A widely replicated finding across the behavioral sciences is that antisocial behaviors correlate with an array of health problems. Less clear, however, is the precise nature of this association. There is reason to suspect that a direct causal link exists between incarceration&#x02014;a consequence of some antisocial behaviors&#x02014;and certain negative health outcomes, for instance. However, it might be the case that broader phenotypes like antisocial behavior may correlate with certain health and physiological traits at a genomic level. We explore this possibility from a theoretical vantage point, while also presenting some preliminary data from existing secondary sources. Tentatively, no significant genetic correlations emerged across a host of health, physiological, and wellbeing outcomes after correction for multiple testing. However, more work is needed exploring this topic. We propose that future studies should make use of larger, more diverse samples and examine the genetic overlap between homogeneous clusters of antisocial behavioral subtypes and disease traits or symptoms.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>genetic correlation analysis</kwd><kwd>genome wide association analysis</kwd><kwd>antisocial behavior</kwd><kwd>disease traits</kwd><kwd>comorbidity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="37"/><page-count count="6"/><word-count count="3402"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Prior research has produced well-replicated associations between various health maladies (both psychological and medical) and a range of antisocial behaviors (ASB) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Overtly aggressive forms of behavior in particular are correlated with an array of diseases; chronic and acute, communicable and non-communicable, and including diabetes, hepatitis, asthma, hyperlipidemia, cancer, and various attendant medical complications such as sepsis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Children and adolescents with psychiatric diagnoses such as attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)&#x02014;a key risk factor for crime and ASB&#x02014;are at an increased risk for adverse health outcomes that can include sleep apnea, diabetes, and obesity (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>While the evidence regarding phenotypic correlation seems clear, less apparent is whether some covariance between ASB and health indicators also exists at a genomic level (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). This becomes possible owing to several reasons, including but not limited to the diffuse heritability of quantitative human traits, as well as arguments made regarding the possibility of &#x0201c;omnigenic&#x0201d; influences in nature (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The purpose of this brief report, then, is to shed light on possible associations between ASB and a wide swath of relevant health, physiological, and disease traits. The findings to come in this area, regardless of their precise outcome, are important as they will have key implications for research on this topic. To the extent that a genetic correlation exists across traits it both suggests a shared etiology for health and ASB, and also highlights the need to better understand mechanistic pathways from genetic to phenotypic variation (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Correlated genetic factors must also be controlled in epidemiological and observational studies seeking to explore causal effects running from ASB to health or vice versa (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). An absence of a genetic correlation is also of interest, as it suggests areas where genetic influences are less pleiotropic, and thus will necessarily shape the search for other trait relevant variants for both sets of outcomes independently. Below, we first examine some of the indirect evidence bearing on the current focus. We then transition to the work being done directly on the genomics of antisocial behavior, and discuss reasons why overlap between ASB and health/wellbeing may exist.</p><sec id="s1_1"><title>The Correlations Between Health, Disease, and ASB-Relevant Outcomes</title><p>There may exist some shared genetic variance between ASB and health/physiological maladies, but empirical evidence on this question is largely lacking or absent entirely. To be sure, there is reason to suspect that such an association <italic>might</italic> exist. Both sets of outcomes&#x02014;ASB and health&#x02014;are moderately heritable (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Given the pleiotropy that exists in the genome, moreover, it seems reasonable to hypothesize that some of the variants associated with health and ASB overlap (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Finally, phenotypic correlations often reflect genetic correlations to some extent (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). This last point is not fundamental to the hypotheses being tested per se, however, does seem broadly relevant when considering possible overlapping genomic architectures between outcomes correlated at a phenotypic level.</p><p>To illustrate our point, consider the limited results gleaned from prior genome wide association (GWA) based studies which relate to the current topic. As we mentioned above, certain cognitive traits/psychological disorders (i.e., ADHD) can function to increase the risk of ASB while also presenting concurrently with certain health maladies (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Hagenaars and colleagues (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) provide a general summary regarding genomic correlations between cognitive traits and health [we direct interested readers specifically to their supplementary tables, and studies such as Brainin et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and Kovacic et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)]. It should be reiterated, though, that the studies referenced are illustrative, yet only indirectly related to our current focus. Most research to date has not examined the genomic architectures of ASB directly, thus cannot directly elucidate the research question of interest here.</p></sec><sec id="s1_2"><title>Better Characterizing the Genomics of Antisocial Behavior</title><p>Indeed, to best address the current question a necessary first step involved examining the genomic architectures of various antisocial behaviors. While well-powered genome wide association studies (GWAS) have become widely available in general, comparatively less effort has been focused on antisocial behavioral phenotypes (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The result, to date, has meant somewhat limited statistical power when examining antisocial behavioral phenotypes (compared to health/disease outcomes). Nonetheless, work in the area is growing, and to address the power problems (as well as other previous limitations), several consortia were formed combining several datasets in order to increase efficiency of research in this area.</p><p>Examples of these far-reaching collaborations studying the genetics of ASB include: ACTION (Aggression in Children: Unraveling gene&#x02013;environment interplay to inform Treatment and InterventION strategies), the Agressotype consortium, BroadABC (Broad Antisocial Behavior Consortium) and EAGLE (Early Genetics and Lifecourse Epidemiology). Using consortia data, we have previously meta-analyzed GWAS data of the non-overlapping cohorts of the BroadABC and EAGLE groups (combined N = 31,968) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Despite the identification of a few promising genetic loci (such as chr1:rs2764450; chr2: rs11126630; chr11:rs11215217; and chrX: rs41456347) these large collaborative GWA efforts have not yet produced robust and reproducible genetic variants associated with ASB (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>Still, these consortia have demonstrated a polygenic contribution of common variants to antisocial behavior and revealed genetic overlap of antisocial behavior with several psychological, psychiatric and addictive outcomes. We demonstrated preliminary evidence of a genetic correlation between reproductively relevant traits and ASB, for instance. In particular, genetic correlation analyses suggested that alleles associated with higher reproductive output were positively correlated with alleles associated with ASB, whereas alleles associated with giving birth later in life were negatively associated (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Moreover, in a study using a similar research design we found preliminary support for a genetic correlation of ASB with lifetime cannabis use and cigarettes per day, but not with weekly alcohol consumption or ever smoking (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods and Results</title><p>The current brief report expands on the research just mentioned. To maximize sample size, this study included population-based cohorts with a broad range of antisocial measures, covering both aggressive and non-aggressive domains of antisocial behavior, and with different age groups represented [age ranges for EAGLE included 3 to 15 years old, and BroadABC included ages ranging between 7 and 56 years old; additional details are provided elsewhere, see Pappa et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>); Tielbeek et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)]. This brief report represents our first exploration examining the genetic overlap of antisocial behavior, utilizing combined summary data from two consortia [for more detail, see Pappa et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), Tielbeek et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)] with 71 traits derived from the centralized database LD Hub (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) (see Footnote <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>).</p><p>We should momentarily elaborate on the selection and inclusion of health and physiological measures. As mentioned, there are a host of health, physiological, and disease relevant outcomes correlated across numerous prior studies with ASB (see above). As additional GWA summary statistics have become publicly available (see Footnote 1), we opted to cast a wide net when analyzing the possible shared genomic architectures of ASB and health/disease/physiology (as opposed to numerous papers, each smaller in scope).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> While desirable in some respects, this approach also further necessitates the need to guard against the possibility of chance findings. With this point in mind, we uncovered no significant (&#x003b1; &#x0003c; 0.0007) genetic correlations after a Bonferonni correction was applied to the data (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Genetic correlations (r<sub>g</sub>) between 71 traits (anthropometric, autoimmune, cancer, glycemic, hematological, hormone, kidney, lipids, metal, neurological, sleeping) and broad antisocial behavior.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait Category</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenotype</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r<sub>g</sub>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNP h<sup>2</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child birth length</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.746</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child birth weight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.490</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body fat</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood obesity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extreme bmi</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extreme height</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.575</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extreme waist-to-hip ratio</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.623</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.353</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height_2010</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.599</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity class 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity class 2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity class 3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.216</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.122</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.250</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hip circumference</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infant head circumference</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.122</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist-to-hip ratio</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference in height between adolescence and adulthood age 14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.069</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.474</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference in height between childhood and adulthood age 8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.120</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.581</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sitting height ratio</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height Females at age 10 and males at age 12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.026</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.886</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth weight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.136</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.260</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eczema</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crohns disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory Bowel Disease (Euro)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.228</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.133</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerative colitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.391</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asthma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rheumatoid Arthritis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.122</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple sclerosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systemic lupus erythematosus</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.629</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary biliary cirrhosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.549</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Celiac disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.265</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary sclerosing cholangitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.556</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung cancer (all)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.636</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung cancer (squamous cell)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.463</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung adenocarcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.688</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamous cell lung cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.727</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type 2 Diabetes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.143</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting glucose main effect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting insulin main effect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.276</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.202</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting proinsulin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.274</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2hr glucose adjusted for BMI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMA-B</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.213</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycemic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMA-IR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.270</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemotological</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.416</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemotological</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean platelet volume</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.396</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemotological</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet count</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.130</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hormone</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leptin_adjBMI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.101</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hormone</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leptin_not_adjBMI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.803</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urinary albumin-to-creatinine ratio (non-diabetes)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.191</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.240</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.426</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic Kidney Disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.508</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum creatinine (non-diabetes)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.177</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum creatinine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.144</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum cystatin c</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.207</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urinary albumin-to-creatinine ratio</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.939</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transferrin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.396</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.573</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alzheimers disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parkinsons disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.419</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.338</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.575</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.073</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.630</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia<sup>a</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia<sup>b</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.133</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excessive daytime sleepiness</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.289</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SNP (single nucleotide polymorphism); h<sup>2</sup>: narrow-sense heritability based on all SNPs; r<sub>g</sub>: genetic correlation with ASB. Asterisks (*) indicate a nominal significant genetic correlation (p&#x0003c;.05). for a, see (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>); for b, see (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Consideration of findings reaching a level of nominally significant (&#x003b1; &#x0003c; 0.05) results revealed that&#x02014;with increasing sample size&#x02014;anthropometric risk factors such as high waist-to-hip ratio (r<sub>g</sub> = 0.30, P = 0.016) may correlate with genetic risk of ASB. Moreover, the potential positive genetic overlap of ASB with insomnia (r<sub>g</sub> = 0.43, P = 0.026) and HOMA-IR (Homeostatic Model Assessment for Insulin Resistance, r<sub>g</sub> = 0.57, P = 0.034) is noteworthy [for a related reference, see also Rolling et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)], as well as the negative genetic correlation with autoimmune diseases ulcerative colitis (r<sub>g</sub> = &#x02212;0.39, P = 0.038) and primary sclerosing cholangitis (r<sub>g</sub> = &#x02212;0.56, P = 0.030). It is key to emphasize, however, that although we report the above moderate to strong genetic correlations, they may in fact reflect <italic>false positive</italic> findings&#x02014;as they did <italic>not</italic> survive correction for multiple testing. The large standard errors, it is worth noting, reflect the relatively low GWAS sample size for ASB, rendering these results in need of further replicative efforts with larger sample sizes. Finally, in an effort to be as exhaustive as possible beyond our initial analyses, and by making use of the same LD Hub web interface, we calculated the genetic correlations of ASB with an additional 597 health and physiologically relevant traits of the UK Biobank which also recently became available (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">
<bold>Supplementary Table S1</bold>
</xref>; see also our footnote above concerning the inclusion of these additional traits). Similar to our primary findings, none of these correlations survived correction for multiple testing (&#x003b1; &#x0003c; 8.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>What this preliminary exploration suggests is that ASB and various health outcomes share virtually no genomic overlap, beyond what might be considered at this point as &#x0201c;nominally significant.&#x0201d; Moreover, these findings further suggest that phenotypic associations between ASB and health/physiological outcomes are perhaps phenotypically causal, or mutually impacted by some third <italic>environmental</italic> variable (i.e., spurious, but owing to environmental variables which might include a range of factors such as socioeconomic status, educational attainment, etc.). Keeping that mind, we have several recommendations for future research endeavors examining the overlap of ASB and health/physiological adversities.</p><sec id="s3_1"><title>Enlarging and Diversifying Samples</title><p>With growing sample sizes, future polygenic risk scores (PRS) will improve in their prediction of antisocial behavioral traits on the basis of genetic data. Moreover, future PRS for disease outcomes may still be capable of elucidating the risk of ASB and vice versa [see Demontis et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)]. Well-powered PRS, such as for Type 1 Diabetes, have great clinical and research potential and have been found useful for classifying adult incident diabetes type and improving newborn screening (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Despite the great potential of PRS and precision medicine, a major limitation is the Eurocentric bias and the lack of diversity in genetic studies. Indeed, the underrepresentation of non-European populations in GWAS is problematic as it limits the generalizability and predictive value of PRS for these populations (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3_2"><title>Examining Homogeneous Clusters</title><p>Genetic correlations are computed on the basis of GWA summary statistics of the traits of interest. GWA research designs in psychopathology often employ sum-scores or case-control status summarizing a list of items or symptoms. Items included in these types of composite scores can vary considerably, with some examples including: &#x02018;hit others when provoked&#x02019;, &#x02018;blamed others&#x02019; and &#x02018;had trouble keeping a job&#x02019;, yet all of them load on the broader construct of antisocial behavior (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Prior work on neuroticism, however, suggested that the items included were genetically heterogeneous, and thus argued that future studies should examine the trait from the standpoint of homogeneous clusters of relevant alleles (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). To that end, future scholars may find the framework of genomic SEM (structural equation modeling) useful in delineating homogenous clusters (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Taken together, then, the above recommendations will likely be worthwhile, as it will be important to examine genetic overlap between GWAS summary stats of <italic>subtypes</italic> of ASB (or even on the item level) with disease traits or symptoms in future research.</p></sec><sec id="s3_3"><title>Exploring Causality</title><p>With the help of well-powered GWAS it has become increasingly clear that most genes influence multiple biological pathways and traits&#x02014;a phenomenon commonly termed pleiotropy (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Owing to this issue, it becomes crucial to overcome unmeasured confounding and distinguish between causal and spurious risk factors (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Despite many epidemiological studies being non-experimental, a research technique called Mendelian randomization (MR)&#x02014;which is a version of the commonly utilized design known as instrumental variables&#x02014;can strengthen causal inference by considering genes as the instruments in the design (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Stated differently, MR studies operate by making use of genetic variants as proxies for the actual (environmental) risk factor of interest (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The number of studies utilizing this approach is expanding rapidly, but as a note of caution (echoed previously in prior work) future MR studies on this topic should carefully assess the plausibility of the underlying assumptions when implementing the technique, and preferably combine various MR methods whenever possible (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3_4"><title>Mechanisms and Gene&#x02013;Environment Interplay</title><p>For the traits that might evince <italic>preliminary</italic> evidence of a genetic correlation (if the nominal levels of significance are meaningful), much more work&#x02014;with more statistical power&#x02014;is needed to understand the mechanisms of such associations. We hesitate to speculate widely, but one possibility could be that the genetic influences shared across traits operate widely on immune system functioning as well as general functioning in the central nervous system. The downstream effect then would be the emergence of both psychological and physiological conditions at certain points in the life course (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Additionally, one cannot discount the relevance of gene&#x02013;environment interplay in two forms: gene&#x02013;environment interaction (G &#x000d7; E) and gene&#x02013;environment correlation (rGE) [in general, see Leppert et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>); Ruisch et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>); Ruisch et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)].</p><p>Indeed, one can envision scenarios such that the impact of trait relevant genes is calibrated based on exposure to environmental insults, including disease or infectious agents [i.e., G &#x000d7; E; for indirectly related examples see Ruisch et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>); Ruisch et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)]. Moreover, traits which vary in part because of genetic variation&#x02014;in this case ASB&#x02014;might perhaps operate to increase risk of exposure to infectious agents or more broadly, situations where health outcomes could be compromised (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Future research on this topic will doubtless benefit from exploring the relevancy of rGEs for the intersection of health and ASB. Finally, we should note that interaction with other alleles at additional loci, too, will likely be important for understanding the complex underpinnings of these phenotypes and why their genomic architectures could potentially overlap. In short, the number of research hypotheses awaiting investigation in this area is long, detailed, and it would seem, quite timely.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s4"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation, to any qualified researcher.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>BB was responsible for the conception of the work and drafted the first version. JT performed the statistical analyses and revised it critically for important intellectual contents. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version. </p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>With additional health traits&#x02014;which we became aware of after our initial round of peer review&#x02014;included in the supplementary tables. We opted to expand our focus to include these traits as a result of both reviewer feedback, and the relevancy of the traits for the current research question.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>2</label><p>We wish to thank an anonymous reviewer for prompting us to consider expanding our focus, given the wider associations between antisocial behavioral outcomes and health/physiologically relevant variables.</p></fn></fn-group><sec id="s7" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00539/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00539/full#supplementary-material</ext-link>
</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnert</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Juvenile incarceration and health</article-title>. <source>Acad Ped</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.acap.2015.09.004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chertoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Alnuaimat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prisoners in the United States Likely to Have Higher Odds of Death From Sepsis</article-title>. <source>Chest</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>152</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>682&#x02013;3</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2017.06.034</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Promoting health equity to prevent crime</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<page-range>91&#x02013;4</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2018.05.009</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Salas-Wright</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Poor nutrition and bullying behaviors: A comparison of deviant and non-deviant youth</article-title>. <source>J Adol</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adolescence.2017.03.008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macalino</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumantera</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hepatitis C infection and incarcerated populations</article-title>. <source>Int J Drug Policy</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>103&#x02013;14</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2003.10.006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rolling</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Velez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaegers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence and correlates of diabetes among criminal justice&#x02013;involved individuals in the United States</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2019.05.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31301945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Incarceration as a key variable in racial disparities of asthma prevalence</article-title>. <source>BMC Pub Health</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>290</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-10-290</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20509891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Angriman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffeis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Isnard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Konofal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecendreux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and obesity: a systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutrit</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>524&#x02013;37</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408390701540124</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demontis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattheisen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Als</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Agerbo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Discovery of the first genome-wide significant risk loci for attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0269-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30478444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Schizophrenia and rheumatoid arthritis: a review</article-title>. <source>Schiz Res</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>181&#x02013;92</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0920-9964(92)90001-L</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000fc;rgens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>HIV and incarceration: prisons and detention</article-title>. <source>J Int AIDS Soc</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1758-2652-14-26</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21595957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An Expanded View of Complex Traits: From Polygenic to Omnigenic</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>169</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>1177&#x02013;86</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.05.038</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polderman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Benyamin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Leeuw</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bochoven</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Meta-analysis of the heritability of human traits based on fifty years of twin studies</article-title>. <source>Nat Genes</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>47</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>702</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3285</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutwell</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaver</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>On the consequences of ignoring genetic influences in criminological research</article-title>. <source>J CJ</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>471&#x02013;82</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcrimjus.2014.08.003</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Correlation and causation in the study of personality</article-title>. <source>Eur J Person</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>372&#x02013;90</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/per.1863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagenaars</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Liewald</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Shared genetic aetiology between cognitive functions and physical and mental health in UK Biobank (N= 112 151) and 24 GWAS consortia</article-title>. <source>Mol Psych</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1624</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2015.225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Conduct disorder and oppositional defiant disorder in a national sample: developmental epidemiology</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>609&#x02013;21</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2004.00250.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Salas-Wright</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence and correlates of psychiatric disorders among former juvenile detainees in the United States</article-title>. <source>Comp Psy</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<page-range>107&#x02013;16</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2015.02.012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brainin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuomilehto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiss</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bath</surname><given-names>PMW</given-names></name><name><surname>Teuschl</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Post-stroke cognitive decline: An update and perspectives for clinical research</article-title>. <source>Eur J Neurol</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.12626</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25492161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacic</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuster</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The links between complex coronary disease, cerebrovascular disease, and degenerative brain disease</article-title>. <source>Ann NY Acad Sci</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>1254</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06482.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22548575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Sklar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>10 years of GWAS discovery: biology, function, and translation</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genes</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>101</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2017.06.005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tielbeek</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Polderman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rautiainen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association studies of a broad spectrum of antisocial behavior</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psy</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>74</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>1242&#x02013;50</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.3069</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tielbeek</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Popma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Polderman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Exploring the genetic correlations of antisocial behaviour and life history traits</article-title>. <source>BJPsych Open</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>467&#x02013;70</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjo.2018.63</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tielbeek</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vink</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Polderman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Popma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Posthuma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Verweij</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genetic correlation of antisocial behaviour with alcohol, nicotine, and cannabis use</article-title>. <source>Drug Alc Depend</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>187</volume>:<page-range>296&#x02013;9</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.03.020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pappa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>St Pourcain</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Benke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavadino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakulinen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nivard</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A genome-wide approach to children's aggressive behavior: The EAGLE consortium</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Genes Pt B: Neuropsychiatr Genes</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>171</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>562&#x02013;72</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32333</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Erzurumluoglu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsworth</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haycock</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>LD Hub: a centralized database and web interface to perform LD score regression that maximizes the potential of summary level GWAS data for SNP heritability and genetic correlation analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>272&#x02013;9</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw613</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammerschlag</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Leeuw</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sniekers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taskesen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association analysis of insomnia complaints identifies risk genes and genetic overlap with psychiatric and metabolic traits</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>49</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1584</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3888</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28604731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlasac</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bechtold</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association analyses of sleep disturbance traits identify new loci and highlight shared genetics with neuropsychiatric and metabolic traits</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3749</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27992416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Development and standardization of an improved type 1 diabetes genetic risk score for use in newborn screening and incident diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>200&#x02013;7</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc18-1785</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical use of current polygenic risk scores may exacerbate health disparities</article-title>. <source>Nat Genes</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>584</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0379-x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Posthuma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Sluis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Item-level analyses reveal genetic heterogeneity in neuroticism</article-title>. <source>Nat Comm</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>905</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03242-8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grotzinger</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhemtulla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vlaming</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallard</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genomic structural equation modelling provides insights into the multivariate genetic architecture of complex traits</article-title>. <source>Nat Hum Behav</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>513&#x02013;25</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-019-0566-x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koellinger</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vlaming</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mendelian randomization: the challenge of unobserved environmental confounds</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidem</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>665&#x02013;71</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyz138</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbord</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Timpson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mendelian randomization: using genes as instruments for making causal inferences in epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Stats Med</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1133&#x02013;63</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.3034</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leppert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Havdahl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Riglin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Association of Maternal Neurodevelopmental Risk Alleles with Early-Life Exposures</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>76</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>834&#x02013;42</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2019.0774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruisch</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Glennon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Buitelaar</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Interplay between genome-wide implicated genetic variants and environmental factors related to childhood antisocial behavior in the UK ALSPAC cohort</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>269</volume>:<page-range>741&#x02013;52</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00406-018-0964-5</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruisch</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faraone</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Oosterlaan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Buitelaar</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Aggression based genome-wide, glutamatergic, dopaminergic and neuroendocrine polygenic risk scores predict callous-unemotional traits</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>761&#x02013;9</page-range>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-020-0608-0</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>