<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">
 <italic>Personalised genomic medicine</italic> aims to tailor a treatment to an individuals’ genetic needs. This is expected to revolutionise disease treatment by using targeted therapy and treatment tailored to the individual to achieve the most effective outcome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], as illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. This form of genomic medicine was made feasible due to advances in computational biotechnology and its implementation into the health care system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>], illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, alongside biological advancements that include the mapping of human genetic variation across the world through parallel global efforts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. However, it remains a futuristic vision rather than an everyday reality, due to the multiple obstacles that genetic studies face in deciphering complex genotype-phenotype relationships [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. One of the notorious difficulties in the field is the variation among population subgroups, which is often due to their genomic background [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Personalisation to the ancestral group-level is a more realistic short-term goal, yet being well-represented in genomic datasets is the exception rather than the rule. For example, an individual of Aramean ancestry living in the UK would be matched to only a handful of individuals in the UK Biobank. Similarly, individuals from Transcaucasia may be considered either “Europeans” or “Asians” and poorly represented by either, as their populations resemble an older admixture between these continental groups [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. The development of personalised medicine is, therefore, an area particularly affected by a lack of diversity in biobanks. 
</p>
