<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Parkinsons Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Parkinsons Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>NPJ Parkinson's Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2373-8057</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7979923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41531-021-00169-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Il-10 signaling reduces survival in mouse models of synucleinopathy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9034-0273</contrib-id><name><surname>Cockey</surname><given-names>Samuel G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McFarland</surname><given-names>Karen N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>Emily J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>Mieu M. T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez De La Cruz</surname><given-names>Elsa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>Pedro E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ceballos-Diaz</surname><given-names>Carolina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosario</surname><given-names>Awilda M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Levites</surname><given-names>Yona R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borchelt</surname><given-names>David R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>Todd E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giasson</surname><given-names>Benoit I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6226-3776</contrib-id><name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>Paramita</given-names></name><address><email>pchakrabarty@ufl.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15276.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8091</institution-id><institution>Center for Translational Research in Neurodegenerative Disease, </institution><institution>University of Florida, </institution></institution-wrap>Gainesville, FL USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15276.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8091</institution-id><institution>Norman Fixel Institute for Neurological Diseases, University of Florida, </institution></institution-wrap>Gainesville, FL USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15276.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8091</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurology, </institution><institution>University of Florida, </institution></institution-wrap>Gainesville, FL USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15276.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8091</institution-id><institution>McKnight Brain Institute, University of Florida, </institution></institution-wrap>Gainesville, FL USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15276.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8091</institution-id><institution>Department of Neuroscience, </institution><institution>University of Florida, </institution></institution-wrap>Gainesville, FL USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417467.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0443 9942</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Department of Neuroscience, Mayo Clinic, </institution></institution-wrap>Jacksonville, FL USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>30</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD) and related synucleinopathies are characterized by chronic neuroinflammation leading to the premise that anti-inflammatory therapies could ameliorate synucleinopathy and associated sequelae. To test this idea, we used recombinant adeno-associated viruses (AAV) to express the anti-inflammatory cytokine, Interleukin (Il)-10, in Line M83 transgenic mice that expresses the PD-associated A53T mutant human &#x003b1;-synuclein (&#x003b1;Syn). Contrary to our expectations, we observed that intraspinal Il-10 expression initiated at birth upregulated microgliosis and led to early death in homozygous M83+/+ mice. We further observed that Il-10 preconditioning led to reduced lifespan in the hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice injected with preformed &#x003b1;Syn aggregates in hindlimb muscles. To determine the mechanistic basis for these adverse effects, we took advantage of the I87A variant Il-10 (vIl-10) that has predominantly immunosuppressive properties. Sustained intraspinal expression of vIl-10 in preformed &#x003b1;Syn-aggregate seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice resulted in earlier death, accelerated &#x003b1;Syn pathology, pronounced microgliosis, and increased apoptosis compared to control mice. AAV-vIl-10 expression robustly induced p62 and neuronal LC3B accumulation in these mice, indicating that Il-10 signaling mediated preconditioning of the neuraxis can potentially exacerbate &#x003b1;Syn accumulation through autophagy dysfunction in the neurons. Together, our data demonstrate unexpected adverse effects of both Il-10 and its immunosuppressive variant, vIl-10, in a mouse model of PD, highlighting the pleiotropic functions of immune mediators and their complex role in non-cell autonomous signaling in neurodegenerative proteinopathies.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Chronic inflammation</kwd><kwd>Parkinson's disease</kwd><kwd>Neuroimmunology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100000065</institution-id><institution>U.S. Department of Health &#x00026; Human Services | NIH | National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NS099738</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>Paramita</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100008276</institution-id><institution>UF | UF Health | College of Medicine, University of Florida (UF College of Medicine)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100000864</institution-id><institution>Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson&#x02019;s Research (Michael J. Fox Foundation)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson&#x02019;s Research (Michael J. Fox Foundation)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">&#x003b1;-synucleinopathies are a heterogeneous group of disorders that are characterized by intracellular accumulation of &#x003b1;-synuclein (&#x003b1;Syn). These disorders, such as Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD), multiple systems atrophy (MSA), and dementia with Lewy body (DLB), are associated with robust neuroinflammation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Genome-wide association studies and transcriptome analysis have uncovered increased genetic risk of PD in patients carrying specific variants of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class II genes and the LRRK2 gene, suggesting that immune pathways influence disease pathogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Several studies have reported increased inflammatory plasma cytokines as well as altered T-cell profiles in PD patients associated with specific inflammatory cytokines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Preclinical modeling studies in &#x003b1;Syn transgenic mice have shown that &#x003b1;Syn activates immune cells by binding to Toll-like receptors and receptors on T cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. These studies confirmed that extracellular &#x003b1;Syn functions as damage-associated molecular patterns (DAMP), resembling pathogen-associated agents that trigger innate immunity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Collectively, cohort analysis data, as well as experimental modeling studies, strongly suggest pathological synergism between chronic neuroinflammation and synuclein proteinopathy leading to the premise that neuroinflammation is a molecular driver in synucleinopathies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">A major immuno-regulator during pathogen infections in the peripheral immune system is interleukin (Il)-10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Il-10 modulates the activity of monocytes and macrophages leading to suppression of inflammatory cytokine expression and establishing anti-inflammatory conditions that foster tissue repair following pathogenic virulence. Based on the hypothesis that chronic neuroinflammation underlies the etiology of synucleinopathy and extracellular &#x003b1;Syn has DAMP-like properties, anti-inflammatory mediators such as Il-10 would be expected to ameliorate &#x003b1;Syn proteinopathy by dampening neuroinflammation. To test this hypothesis, we injected adeno-associated viruses (AAV) expressing Il-10 into neonatal homozygous Line M83+/+ mice or neonatal hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice injected with preformed &#x003b1;Syn aggregates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Contrary to our expectations, we found that Il-10 preconditioning reduced lifespan in both mouse models, without altering the pathological burden of &#x003b1;Syn. As Il-10 can have pleiotropic properties, we next used the anti-inflammatory variant, I87A variant (v)-Il-10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, to fully characterize this unexpected outcome of Il-10 signaling. We found that sustained expression of vIl-10 in hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice seeded with preformed &#x003b1;Syn aggregates was also detrimental but in a manner distinct from Il-10 and more consistent with accelerated &#x003b1;Syn pathology. We further identified neuronal autophagic dysfunction as a possible mechanism underlying the injurious outcome of vIl-10 signaling in &#x003b1;Syn-aggregate-seeded mice. Together these studies document the unexpected adverse effects of Il-10 preconditioning in mouse models of &#x003b1;Syn pathology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Il-10 increases microgliosis and accelerates death in homozygous M83+/+ mice</title><p id="Par4">Recent evidence has established that a robust inflammatory milieu is associated with neurodegenerative phenotype in several proteinopathies, including Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Therefore, we wanted to examine whether suppressing inflammation would have a beneficial effect on proteinopathy and survival in the transgenic Line M83 mice that expresses the PD-associated A53T mutant human &#x003b1;Syn (<italic>SNCA</italic>). Since Il-10 has been shown to attenuate Th1 type immune response and moderate macrophage/monocyte activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, we hypothesized that Il-10 expression would regulate inflammation leading to suppression of &#x003b1;Syn pathologies and extending lifespan in these mice. We used recombinant AAV serotype 1 to express mouse Il-10 under the control of hybrid chicken &#x003b2;-actin promoter, which was injected in the lumbar segment of the spinal cord of neonatal mice as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. For the initial dose-finding study, we tested three different doses of AAV-Il-10 delivered into the lumbar spinal cord of nontransgenic (nonTG) mice on neonatal day P0 (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a&#x02013;c</xref>). We found that injection of the highest dose (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>10</sup> viral genomes) resulted in consistent levels of Il-10 protein detectable in the soluble lysates of the spinal cord and CSF (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a, b</xref>), suggesting that the Il-10 was being secreted following cellular production. Further experiments were conducted using this high dose. We did not find reproducibly detectable amounts of Il-10 in the serum of these injected mice (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1c</xref>). Injection of this highest dose of Il-10 also resulted in increased astrocytosis in the brains of nonTG mice as revealed by GFAP immunoblotting and immunohistochemistry (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1d&#x02013;f</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">To test the effect of Il-10 signaling on synucleinopathy, we delivered AAV-Il-10 and AAV-green fluorescent protein (GFP) into the spinal cords of neonatal homozygous M83+/+ mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. We detected 7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.6&#x02009;ng/ml of Il-10 protein in the soluble fraction of spinal cord lysates of AAV-Il-10 injected mice compared to 0.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x02009;ng/ml of Il-10 protein in control mice injected with AAV-GFP (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 mice/group; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). As these mice aged, the Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice exhibited an abnormal phenotype marked by hunched posture, loss of body weight (&#x0003e;20%), labored breathing, and unusually high instances of sudden death. Compared to the GFP-expressing control cohort that exhibited ~20% death by 250 days of age, the median age of survival of Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice was 138 days (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). We found that Il-10 expression resulted in increased microgliosis (measured by cd11b immunoreactivity) in the cortex and midbrain areas relative to phenotypically matched AAV-GFP mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>; cortex, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; midbrain, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Microgliosis was not significantly upregulated in either thoracic or lumbar segments of spinal cords of the Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). Astrocytosis (measured by GFAP immunoreactivity) was upregulated in the cortex of Il-10-expressing mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while midbrain and spinal cord did not show significant changes compared to GFP-expressing control mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d, e</xref>). We wanted to examine whether the early death triggered by Il-10 was accompanied by the accelerated formation of &#x003b1;Syn inclusions in the CNS of M83+/+ mice. We used the pSer129-&#x003b1;Syn epitope-specific antibody to detect pathologic &#x003b1;Syn inclusions and the p62 antibody as a general marker of autophagy failure and protein aggregation in these tissues. Using the pSer129-&#x003b1;Syn-specific 81A antibody (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f&#x02013;h</xref>) or anti-p62 antibody (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1i&#x02013;k</xref>), we did not observe any significant induction of &#x003b1;Syn pathology in the Il-10-expressing mice compared to GFP-expressing controls, suggesting that Il-10-mediated immune dysregulation can cause neurotoxicity and accelerated death independent of obvious proteinopathy abnormalities.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Intraspinal Il-10 expression accelerates death in homozygous M83 mice.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Intraspinal expression of AAV-Il-10 leads to early mortality in M83+/+ mice. The median age of survival of Il-10-expressing mice was 138 days, and the median age for the AAV-GFP-expressing mice was undefined (log-rank test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15&#x02013;16 mice/group). <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Microgliosis (cd11b staining) in the brain (<bold>b</bold>, cortex and midbrain) and spinal cord (<bold>c</bold>, thoracic and lumbar segment) of M83+/+ mice. <bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold> Astrocytosis (GFAP staining) in the brain (<bold>d</bold>, cortex and midbrain) and spinal cord (<bold>e</bold>, thoracic and lumbar segment) of M83+/+ mice. <bold>f</bold>&#x02013;<bold>k</bold> Representative images from anti-81A (<bold>f</bold>&#x02013;<bold>h</bold>) and anti-p62 (<bold>i</bold>&#x02013;<bold>k</bold>) antibody-stained tissue. Immunostaining analysis is shown from the midbrain (<bold>f</bold>, <bold>i</bold>), the thoracic segment of the spinal cord (<bold>g</bold>, <bold>j</bold>), and the lumbar segment of the spinal cord (<bold>h</bold>, <bold>k</bold>). Scale bar: 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 mice/group; two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test. <bold>l</bold>&#x02013;<bold>p</bold> Volcano plot (<bold>l</bold>) showing differential expression of genes in the thoracic spinal cords of Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice compared to GFP-expressing controls. Red dots, significantly changed genes, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; gray dots, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05. To avoid skewing the graph, the <italic>x</italic> axis is limited to a range of &#x02212;3 to +3 and as a result, Il-10 data is not shown (log2 FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.49; <italic>P</italic>adj value&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.64&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;51</sup>). Gene ontology analysis of overrepresented categories using a list of significantly changed genes from panel l (<italic>P</italic>adj&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; dotted line) (<bold>m</bold>). <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 mice/group. FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. <italic>P</italic>adj&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>P</italic> values adjusted for multiple comparisons. <bold>n</bold>&#x02013;<bold>p</bold> M1, M2-, and DAM-phenotype profile of microglia in Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice compared to GFP-expressing M83+/+ control mice. **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 mice/group. In the box plot, the whiskers extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e683"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">To understand the mechanism underlying Il-10-induced early death, we used a custom NanoString codeset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> to analyze gene expression changes in the thoracic spinal cords of Il-10 and GFP-expressing M83+/+ mice that showed end-stage sickness and paralysis phenotype. We identified several genes that were upregulated in the Il-10 mice&#x02014;Fcgr2b, Ccl8, Chil3, Ccl5, Fcgr4, Ms4a6d, Abca1, Ptprc (Cd45), and Apoe&#x02014;that broadly indicated an immune response associated with phagocytosis related pathways and Fc gamma receptor signaling pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1l, m</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Il-10 was upregulated (log2 fold change&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.49; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.64&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;51</sup>) in these mice but was omitted from the volcano plot in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1l</xref> as it skewed the plot (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1l</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). We were curious whether the accelerated death phenotype in Il-10-expressing mice was mediated via transcriptional upregulation of the human <italic>SNCA</italic> transgene driven by mouse prion promoter. We found that Il-10 expression did not change the levels of the <italic>SNCA</italic> transgene (log2 fold change&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.16; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.55) in AAV-Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice relative to AAV-GFP-expressing M83+/+ mice (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). To establish the specific type of microglial profile associated with sustained Il-10 expression in M83+/+ mice, we calculated gene expression scores corresponding to the prevalence of inflammatory phenotype (M1 phenotype), anti-inflammatory phenotype (M2 phenotype), and neurodegeneration-specific damage-associated microglial phenotype (DAM phenotype). These scores were imputed based on expression levels of a set of genes that uniquely characterize each of these phenotypes (reviewed in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1n&#x02013;p</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Compared to GFP-expressing M83+/+ mice, we observed that Il-10-expressing mice showed a transcriptional profile consistent with M2-type signature (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1o</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). We did not observe any significant changes in the M1-type or DAM signature (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1n, p</xref>). We next compared the top altered genes in the Il-10-expressing M83+/+ mice (normalized to GFP-expressing M83+/+ mice) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) with paralyzed aged M83+/+ mice (normalized to nonTG mice) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). A number of common genes were identified in both groups, such as Fcgr2b, Fcgr4, Ccl5, and Ms4a6d, that are involved in immune signaling (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). Such commonalities between these two groups suggest that Il-10-mediated immune dysfunction reinforced the neurodegenerative cascade in the M83+/+ model.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Il-10 expression reduces lifespan in preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice</title><p id="Par7">Next, we examined whether Il-10 preconditioning would modulate the induction and prion-like transmission of &#x003b1;Syn pathology in hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice. In this model, preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils injected into the gastrocnemius muscle of 2-month-old M83+/&#x02212; mice leads to progressive induction of &#x003b1;Syn pathology along the spinal axis and midbrain, with hindlimb paralysis occurring ~4 months after injection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">Neonatal M83+/&#x02212; mice were injected with AAV-Il-10 or AAV-GFP in the lumbar spinal cord and aged to 2 months when they were injected bilaterally in the hindlimb muscle with preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). As the control for preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibril injection, mice were injected with the vehicle, PBS, in their hindlimb muscle. Biochemical analysis of the spinal cord lysates of mice revealed that at end stage, the &#x003b1;Syn-seeded AAV-Il-10 and AAV-GFP-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice had 4.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4&#x02009;ng/ml and 1.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06&#x02009;ng/ml of Il-10 protein, respectively (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 mice/group; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). In the &#x003b1;Syn-seeded cohorts, we observed that Il-10 reduced lifespan compared to the control group expressing GFP (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>; median survival of Il-10 mice&#x02009;=&#x02009;112 days and control mice&#x02009;=&#x02009;124.5 days post injection; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). Non-seeded control mice (injected with vehicle PBS) expressing AAV-GFP or AAV-Il-10 did not develop paralysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Intraspinal expression of AAV-Il-10 leads to accelerated mortality in &#x003b1;Syn-aggregate-seeded hemizygous M83<bold>+</bold>/&#x02212; mice.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Schematic summarizing the experimental procedure (top panel). M83+/&#x02212; neonates were injected intraspinally (Spc) with AAV-Il-10 or AAV-GFP (control). Mice were aged to 2 months and injected intramuscularly (IM) with preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils or PBS (vehicle control). Mice were aged to paralysis. The median age of survival of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded Il-10 or GFP-expressing mice was 112 days and 124.5 days post &#x003b1;Syn seeding respectively (log-rank test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10&#x02013;18/group). <bold>b&#x02013;</bold><bold>n</bold> NanoString analysis of the &#x003b1;Syn or vehicle (PBS)-seeded thoracic spinal cords of M83+/&#x02212; mice expressing Il-10 or GFP. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Volcano plot of differentially expressed genes (<bold>b</bold>) and gene ontology pathway analysis of overrepresented functional categories (<bold>c</bold>) accompanying Il-10 overexpression in M83+/&#x02212; spinal cords (<italic>P</italic>adj&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; dotted line). To avoid skewing the volcano plot, the <italic>x</italic> axis is limited to a range of &#x02212;2.5 to +4 and as a result, Il-10 data is not plotted (log2 FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.537; <italic>P</italic>adj value&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.9e-07). <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> M1-, M2-, and DAM-type microglial profiling in Il-10-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice. Two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test, *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. <bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold> Volcano plot of differentially expressed genes (<bold>g</bold>) and gene ontology pathway analysis of overrepresented functional categories (<bold>h</bold>; <italic>P</italic>adj&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, dotted line) in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded Il-10-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice vs vehicle-seeded Il-10-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice. <bold>i</bold>&#x02013;<bold>k</bold> M1-, M2-, and DAM-type microglial profiling in Il-10-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice in the presence or absence of intramuscular (IM) &#x003b1;Syn seeding. <bold>l</bold>&#x02013;<bold>n</bold> M1-, M2-, and DAM-type microglial profiling in Il-10 vs GFP-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 mice/group. Red dots significantly changed genes, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and gray dots, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05 in volcano plots after adjusting for multiple testing and FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. In the box plot, the whiskers extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e886"/></fig></p><p id="Par9">Using the custom neurodegeneration NanoString codeset, we examined gene expression changes in M83+/&#x02212; mice expressing Il-10. First, we examined the gene expression changes in PBS injected (non-seeded) M83+/&#x02212; mice injected with AAV-Il-10 or AAV-GFP. We found that Il-10 expression leads to upregulation of various immune genes, such as complement factors, Ccl8, Fcgr2b, and Trem2 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Il-10 was also robustly upregulated (log2 fold change&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.53; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.89&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>) in these mice but was omitted from the volcano plot in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> as it skewed the plot (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). GO pathway analysis indicates that Il-10 expression induced robust inflammatory signaling characteristic of macrophage activation and presence of an antigenic stimulus (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Neither M1-type nor M2-type gene expression signatures were significantly enhanced in these mice, though there was a suggestive trend in the M2 signature (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d, e</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32 for M2). Interestingly, we observed that Il-10 expression led to induction of DAM signature (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), primarily driven by increased expression of Trem2.</p><p id="Par10">Next, we compared the gene expression changes in Il-10-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice that had been seeded with preformed &#x003b1;Syn aggregates relative to Il-10-expressing non-seeded (PBS injected) M83+/&#x02212; mice (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). Here, we found that &#x003b1;Syn seeding in the presence of Il-10 results in an exacerbated inflammatory milieu characterized by increased Lyz2, Msr1, Ctsd, and Tyrobp (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). Overall, GO pathway analysis indicated reduced metabolic processes at different cellular and physiologic levels, indicative of a degenerative signature (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2h</xref>). There were no significant changes in M1-, M2-, or DAM-type profiles in the &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice compared to mice injected with PBS vehicle control (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i&#x02013;k</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">When we compared the DEG in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice expressing Il-10 to &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice expressing GFP at end stage, we observed that both the DEGs were extremely similar to each other such that there were no differentially expressed genes that could be identified from this comparison (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>). Consistent with this observation, microglial profiling analysis did not show significant levels of difference between the two groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2l&#x02013;n</xref>). To understand this neurodegenerative cascade, we performed an additional comparison. There were ten genes that were significantly altered in response to &#x003b1;Syn seeding in Il-10-expressing mice (Il-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice normalized to Il-10-expressing non-seeded mice) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). When we compared this list with genes altered in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded naive M83+/&#x02212; mice normalized to non-seeded mice (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>), we found that the differentially expressed genes (except for Il-10) were represented in both the cases (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). The similarities in the list of altered genes indicate that the cellular pathways affected by Il-10 preconditioning synergized with the normally ongoing neurodegenerative cascade in the &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>An immunosuppressive variant of cellular Il-10 reduces lifespan in preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice</title><p id="Par12">Il-10 has pleiotropic properties&#x02014;in addition to its well-recognized immunosuppressive properties, it also has immunostimulatory functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. For example, Il-10 can exert stimulatory effects on lymphocytes, murine thymocytes, and murine mast cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Indeed, our gene expression data identified several genes indicative of an activated immune signature, such as Ccl8, Ly86, and Itgam, in Il-10-expressing mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). In order to understand whether the unexpected detrimental phenotype in Il-10-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice was related to the immunosuppressive or immunostimulatory function of Il-10, we decided to use a variant Il-10 (vIl-10) that lacks immunostimulatory function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">Some viruses have appropriated the immunosuppressive properties of Il-10 by expressing close homologs that could be beneficial in preserving viral pathogenesis through ineffective host immune response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. One such homolog, produced by the Epstein Barr Virus and called <italic>BCRF-I</italic>, encodes a single point mutation in cellular Il-10 (I87A Il-10), referred to as vIl-10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. This vIl-10 has lost the stimulatory activities of cellular Il-10 while retaining its immunosuppressive properties. In the next experiment, we delivered AAV-vIl-10 into neonatal M83+/&#x02212; mice, aged these to 2 months, seeded with preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils in the hindlimb muscle and aged them to paralysis. Analysis of the RIPA-soluble spinal cord lysates showed that the vIl-10 levels in the AAV-vIl-10 and control mice were 5.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91&#x02009;pg/ml and 0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13&#x02009;pg/ml, respectively (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 mice; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007). In this cohort of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice, we observed that vIl-10 expression resulted in an accelerated paralysis phenotype (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0019). This data shows that an anti-inflammatory variant of Il-10 robustly reduces survival in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Intraspinal expression of AAV-vIl-10 leads to early mortality in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83<bold>+</bold>/&#x02212; mice.</title><p>M83+/&#x02212; neonates were intraspinally injected with AAV-vIl-10 or sham injected, aged to 2 months, and then injected with &#x003b1;Syn fibril in hindlimb muscles at 2 months of age. The median age of survival of vIl-10-expressing mice was 78 days post &#x003b1;Syn fibril injection, while the median age of sham injected mice was 96 days (log-rank test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0019, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 mice/group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig3_HTML" id="d32e1036"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>vIl-10 expression exacerbates microgliosis in preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice</title><p id="Par14">We next conducted an extensive neuropathological analysis to characterize how Il-10 and vIl-10 expression modulate the induction and transmission of the &#x003b1;Syn pathology in hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice. We examined microgliosis using cd11b antibody in the spinal cords (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a&#x02013;d</xref>) and brains (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e&#x02013;h</xref>) of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice. Contrary to our expectation that vIl-10 would dampen gliosis, we observed robust microgliosis in vIl-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice in both thoracic and lumbar segments of the spinal cord compared to control GFP-expressing PBS-injected mice, GFP-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice or Il-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 against all groups in the thoracic segment; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c, d</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 against control and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 against &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice in the lumbar segment). While vIl-10 expression also enhanced microgliosis in the midbrain area (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4g, h</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 compared to Il-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared to GFP-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice), there was no difference observed in the cortex relative to other mouse cohorts (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e, f</xref>). We did not observe increased microglia numbers in the Il-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice relative to control &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice in the spinal cord and the brain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a&#x02013;h</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Intraspinal vIl-10 expression induces microgliosis but not astrogliosis in spinal cords of &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded hemizygous M83<bold>+</bold>/&#x02212; mice.</title><p>Neonatal M83+/&#x02212; mice were injected with AAV-GFP, AAV-Il-10, or AAV-vIl-10 and were aged to 2 months when they were injected with preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils in the muscle. PBS (vehicle) injection was the control for &#x003b1;Syn fibril injection and is represented by the immunohistochemistry panel on the far left of each panel. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>h</bold> Representative cd11b staining patterns and immunostaining analysis (% immunoreactivity burden) for microgliosis in thoracic segment of the spinal cord (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>), lumbar segment of the spinal cord (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>), cortex (<bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold>), and midbrain (<bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold>). <bold>i</bold>&#x02013;<bold>p</bold> Representative GFAP staining and immunostaining analysis (% immunoreactivity burden) for astrogliosis in thoracic segment of the spinal cord (<bold>i</bold>, <bold>j</bold>), lumbar segment of the spinal cord (<bold>k</bold>, <bold>l</bold>), cortex (<bold>m</bold>, <bold>n</bold>), and midbrain (<bold>o</bold>, <bold>p</bold>). The whiskers in the box plot extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6&#x02013;7 mice/group; one-way ANOVA; ****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001; ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Scale bar, 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig4_HTML" id="d32e1172"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Il-10 expression suppresses astrocytosis in spinal cords of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice</title><p id="Par15">We observed a complex pattern of astrocytosis in the &#x003b1;Syn-seeded hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4i&#x02013;p</xref>). GFAP immunostaining in the thoracic and lumbar spinal cord showed that compared to PBS injected GFP-expressing hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice, &#x003b1;Syn seeding induced astrocytosis in GFP-expressing mice as expected (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4i&#x02013;l</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 in the thoracic segment and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 in the lumbar segment). Within the &#x003b1;Syn-seeded cohorts, compared to GFP or vIL-10-expressing mice, expression of Il-10 reduced astrocytosis in the lumbar spinal cord (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4k, l</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 against GFP and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 against vIl-10), and there was a suggestive lowering trend in the thoracic spinal cord (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4i, j</xref>). In general, we observed that vIl-10 did not induce astrocytic proliferation in the spinal cord compared to the GFP-expressing mice that were seeded with preformed fibrils (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4j, l</xref>). In the brain, &#x003b1;Syn seeding, by itself, did not significantly alter astrocytosis in GFP-expressing mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4m&#x02013;p</xref>). In the cortex, the Il-10-expressing mice had a higher astroglial burden compared to all other groups examined including vIl-10-expressing mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4m, n</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 relative to vIl-10 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 relative to control seeded mice), consistent with our data in non-seeded homozygous M83+/+ mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). In the midbrains of mice seeded with preformed fibrils, we observed that vIl-10 expression caused the highest level of astrocyte proliferation compared to non-seeded (PBS-injected) and &#x003b1;Syn-seeded control mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4o, p</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 against non-seeded mice; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 against seeded GFP-expressing and Il-10-expressing mice respectively). This finding suggests that there is a selective vulnerability of astrocytes in different areas of the neuraxis to Il-10- and vIl-10-mediated signaling.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>vIl-10 worsens pathological pSer129-&#x003b1;Syn inclusion pathology and increases &#x003b1;Syn levels</title><p id="Par16">As both Il-10 and vIl-10 caused accelerated paralysis in hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice seeded with preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils, we next examined if this phenotype correlated with exacerbated &#x003b1;Syn proteinopathy. Consistent with our previous data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, injection of preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils in the gastrocnemius muscle of adult hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice expressing AAV-GFP induced pSer129-&#x003b1;Syn reactive intracellular inclusions in the thoracic spinal cord, lumbar spinal cord, and midbrain compared to GFP-expressing non-seeded mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a&#x02013;f</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). These &#x003b1;Syn inclusions resemble Lewy bodies (LB) and were not observed in control GFP-expressing mice injected with the vehicle PBS (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, c, e</xref>). Expression of Il-10 did not alter the levels of pSer129-&#x003b1;Syn immunoreactive LB-type pathology in the spinal cord or brain, compared to GFP-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b, d, f</xref>). On the other hand, intraspinal vIl-10 expression dramatically increased &#x003b1;Syn inclusion pathology in the thoracic and lumbar spinal cords compared to GFP-expressing and Il-10-expressing seeded mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b, d</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 in thoracic; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 in lumbar segment respectively). In the midbrains of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice, the &#x003b1;Syn pathology burden was similar between all three cohorts (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>vIl-10 induces pathological &#x003b1;Syn inclusions and parenchymal &#x003b1;Syn accumulation in &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded hemizygous M83<bold>+</bold>/&#x02212; mice.</title><p>Neonatal M83+/&#x02212; mice were injected with AAV-GFP, Il-10, or vIl-10 and were aged to 2 months when they were injected with &#x003b1;Syn fibrils in the muscle. PBS (vehicle) injection was the control for &#x003b1;Syn fibril injection and is represented by the immunohistochemistry panel on the far left (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>e</bold>). Representative images and % immunoreactivity burden analysis of 81A antibody (specific to pSer129-&#x003b1;Syn epitope) stained tissue from the thoracic and lumbar segment of the spinal cord (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>d</bold>) and midbrain (<bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold>). Representative images and % immunoreactivity burden analysis from 15-4E7 antibody (specific to the C terminus of &#x003b1;Syn) stained spinal cord (<bold>g</bold>&#x02013;<bold>j</bold>) and midbrain (<bold>k</bold>, <bold>l</bold>). In the box plot, the whiskers extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02013;7 mice/group; one-way ANOVA; ****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001; ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Scale bar, 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig5_HTML" id="d32e1338"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">The role of soluble &#x003b1;Syn in synucleinopathies is unclear. While features like LBs, that are characterized by clusters of aggregated &#x003b1;Syn inside neurons, are clearly neurotoxic, some studies have indicated that even modest increases in soluble &#x003b1;Syn protein levels can lead to cellular dysfunction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Indeed, the early age of disease onset and disease progression severity in patients with duplication of wild-type &#x003b1;Syn loci indicates that simple intracellular accumulation of &#x003b1;Syn protein may have a profound pathogenic effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. To investigate whether Il-10-associated signaling pathways affect the accumulation of total &#x003b1;Syn levels, we used an antibody specific to the C terminus of human &#x003b1;Syn, antibody 15-4E7, that was characterized previously in our lab<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Compared to both GFP and Il-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice, we observed that vIl-10-expressing mice showed higher levels of 15-4E7-immunoreactive intracellular &#x003b1;Syn staining in both the thoracic and lumbar segments of the spinal cord (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g&#x02013;j</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 relative to Il-10 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 relative to GFP for the thoracic segment; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 relative to Il-10 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 relative to GFP for the lumbar segment). Most of these stained structures were intracellular with some degree of parenchymal staining visible (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g, i, k</xref>). Increased parenchymal staining with 15-4E7 antibody in the midbrain of vIl-10-expressing mice compared to GFP-expressing mice (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) and Il-10-expressing mice (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) indicates dramatic accumulation of extracellular &#x003b1;Syn in this brain area (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5k, l</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>vIl-10 induces cell death in spinal cords of &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice</title><p id="Par18">We wanted to examine whether Il-10-mediated signaling pathways resulted in cell death in the brain and spinal cord. Since peripheral &#x003b1;Syn seeding induced midbrain &#x003b1;Syn pathology in our mice, we first quantified whether this led to a loss in dopaminergic neurons in these mice. Using tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) as the marker of dopaminergic cell bodies in the substantia nigra, we did not observe dopaminergic cell loss in any of our &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mouse cohorts compared to the control mice receiving vehicle injection (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, b</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Cell death analysis in &#x003b1;Syn aggregate-seeded hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Midbrains of vehicle-injected AAV-GFP-expressing M83+/&#x02212; mice or &#x003b1;Syn aggregate-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice expressing AAV-GFP, AAV-Il-10, or AAV-vIl-10 were stained for tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) (<bold>a</bold>), and the number of TH-positive dopaminergic neuronal cell bodies was manually counted (<bold>b</bold>). Scale bar, 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;m (main panel), 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m (inset). <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3&#x02013;6 mice/group; one-way ANOVA. <bold>c</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> Cell death was analyzed in the lumbar spinal cord of M83+/&#x02212; mice. Punctate Fluoro-Jade C staining was observed in the vIL-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice indicated by arrows (<bold>c</bold>, top panel). The bottom panel depicts a dual-color image incorporating the nuclear stain DAPI. The number of Fluoro-Jade C-labeled puncta was manually counted (<bold>d</bold>). Anti cleaved caspase 3 antibody was used to stain the spinal cord (<bold>e</bold>, top panel) and accompanying spinal ganglia (<bold>e</bold>, bottom panel) of mice. The number of cleaved caspase 3-positive cells from the spinal cord and spinal ganglia (arrows, <bold>e</bold>) was manually counted (<bold>f</bold>). In the box plot, the whiskers extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median. Scale bar, 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;m (<bold>c</bold>), 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m (<bold>e</bold>). <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02013;7 mice/group. One-way ANOVA, ****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig6_HTML" id="d32e1452"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">We also assessed the effects of the Il-10 signaling pathways on cell death in the spinal cords of M83+/&#x02212; mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c&#x02013;f</xref>). We used two different reagents to investigate cell death in these mice. Fluoro-Jade C is an anionic dye used to detect degenerating or necrotic neurons and processes, irrespective of the type of death pathway involved<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Histochemical staining revealed increased Fluoro-Jade C punctate staining in the lumbar spinal cords of seeded vIl-10-expressing mice compared to control GFP-expressing mice or Il-10-expressing mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c, d</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). Such punctate staining is consistent with dying dendritic or axonal terminals. We further probed for activated caspase 3 to detect apoptotic cells in the lumbar spinal cords of seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e, f</xref>). We found sparse activated caspase 3 immunopositive cells in the gray matter of the spinal cord as well as the spinal ganglia of vIl-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e, f</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), albeit to a lesser extent than observed with Fluoro-Jade C technique. None of the other &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice demonstrated any detectable Fluoro-Jade C or activated caspase 3 reactivity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d, f</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>vIl-10 increases autophagy dysfunction in &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice</title><p id="Par20">We wanted to explore whether the increased parenchymal accumulation of soluble or cell-free &#x003b1;Syn, as well as intracellular inclusion pathology, could be due to impaired autophagic clearance in the seeded M83+/&#x02212; mice. Because of previously reported data that IL-10 can inhibit autophagy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, we reasoned that this might explain mechanistically the effect of Il-10-mediated worsening of &#x003b1;Syn proteinopathy. Using p62 as a marker of autophagic dysfunction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, we observed that &#x003b1;Syn seeding induced modest p62 accumulation in the spinal cords of GFP and Il-10-expressing mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a&#x02013;d</xref>) and the midbrain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7e, f</xref>) compared to non-seeded genotype-matched and age-matched M83+/&#x02212; mice. vIl-10, on the other hand, resulted in a profound upregulation of intracellular p62-immunoreactive inclusions in the thoracic and lumbar spinal cords (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a&#x02013;d</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 relative to Il-10, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 relative to GFP) as well as in the midbrain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7e, f</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 relative to Il-10, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 relative to GFP) of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Accumulation of autophagic markers in vIl-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice.</title><p>Neonatal M83+/&#x02212; mice were injected with AAV-GFP, Il-10, or vIl-10 and were aged to 2 months when they were injected with &#x003b1;Syn fibrils in the muscle. PBS (vehicle) injection was the control for &#x003b1;Syn fibril injection and is represented by the immunohistochemistry panel on the left of each panel. Representative images of anti-p62/sequestosome antibody-stained tissue and immunostaining analysis (% immunoreactivity burden) from the thoracic spinal cord (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>), lumbar spinal cord (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>), and midbrain (<bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold>) are shown. Representative images from MAP1LC3B antibody-stained tissue and immunostaining analysis (% immunoreactivity burden) derived from the thoracic spinal cord (<bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold>), lumbar spinal cord (<bold>i</bold>, <bold>j</bold>), and midbrain (<bold>k</bold>, l) are shown. Of note, 2/5 mice in the Il-10-expressing seeded mice showed LC3B staining in the spinal cord. <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02013;7 mice/group; one-way ANOVA; ****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001; ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Scale bar, 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m. In the box plot, the whiskers extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median. <bold>m</bold> Representative images from the lumbar spinal cord showing robust localization of LC3B (arrows, middle panels) in ChAT-immunopositive neurons (arrows, top panel) but not in GFAP-immunopositive astrocytes, MBP-immunopositive oligodendrocytes, or CD68-immunopositive microglia of vIl-10-expressing Line M83+/&#x02212; mice seeded with &#x003b1;Syn fibril. The right panels show merged images of LC3B (detected with Alexa fluor 488&#x02009;nm) with cell type-specific markers (detected with Alexa fluor 594&#x02009;nm). Slides were counterstained with DAPI. Inset in ChAT panel (right) denotes triple-color merged image from M83+/&#x02212; mice seeded with &#x003b1;Syn fibril showing no detectable LC3B. Arrows (denoting LC3B signal) in MBP- and CD68-stained panels do not colocalize with oligodendrocyte or microglia, respectively. Scale bar, 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig7_HTML" id="d32e1585"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">To further confirm autophagic disturbance in these mice, we assessed the levels of microtubule-associated protein 1 light chain 3 &#x003b2; (MAP1LC3B)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> or LC3B, a key regulatory component of autophagic degradation pathway. Cytoplasmic and nuclear accumulation of LC3B indicates abnormalities in autophagosome assembly, which is widely used for the detection of dysfunctional autophagy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Anti MAP1LC3B staining revealed sparse staining in the thoracic and lumbar spinal cords of Il-10-expressing &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7g&#x02013;j</xref>) but not in the midbrain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7l</xref>). On the other hand, vIl-10 expression led to nuclear staining and diffuse cytoplasmic staining suggestive of accumulation of autophagic debris. Compared to GFP-expressing mice seeded with &#x003b1;Syn, vIl-10 mice showed increased LC3B levels in the thoracic and lumbar segments of spinal cords (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7g&#x02013;j</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 in the thoracic spinal cord, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 in the lumbar spinal cord), whereas there was a trend toward increased LC3B staining in the midbrains (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7k, l</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.22 relative to control &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice). To identify which cells preferentially accumulated LC3B in response to vIl-10, we performed a co-immunofluorescence analysis localizing LC3B in motor neurons (stained with choline acetyltransferase, ChAT), astrocytes (stained with GFAP), oligodendrocytes (stained with myelin basic protein, MBP), and microglia (stained with CD68). Representative images from the lumbar spinal cord of vIL-10-expressing mice seeded with &#x003b1;Syn fibrils showed robust LC3B staining in the ChAT-immunopositive neurons (arrows, top panel, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7m</xref>). None of the other cell types tested (astrocytes, oligodendrocytes, and microglia) show appreciable LC3B colocalizing with the cell type-specific markers (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7m</xref>). Together, these observations indicate that preconditioning the neuraxis with Il-10-related immunosuppressive signaling can lead to exacerbation of &#x003b1;Syn proteinopathy via altering neuronal autophagic pathways.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par22">Gliosis is a cardinal feature in post mortem brains of PD patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> as well as a prodromal feature in the early-stage PD patients and DLB patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Several cytokines with stimulatory properties&#x02014;for example, IL-6 and TNF-&#x003b1;&#x02014;are increased in PD patient sera and are correlated with the severity of the nonmotor symptoms in PD patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Recent genome-wide association studies have also uncovered genetic overlaps in PD patients and patients suffering from autoimmune disorders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. In mouse models of synucleinopathy, we, as well as other groups, have reported robust inflammation in the end-stage mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, and treatment with immunomodulatory agents prevented &#x003b1;Syn pathology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. These lines of evidence generally point to inflammatory signaling as a possible etiological factor in synucleinopathies. Our study was designed to test whether Il-10 overexpression initiated before the onset of neuropathology or phenotypes would be able to suppress inflammation and ameliorate &#x003b1;Syn pathologies in the M83 model. Our approach in this study was to use recombinant AAVs to express Il-10 based on its future translational potential as a vector for gene therapy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Further, the AAV gene targeting approach allowed us to restrict Il-10 expression to the CNS, thereby limiting its effect only to the target organ and minimizing off-target effects on peripheral immunity. Contrary to our expectations, we uncovered a detrimental effect of intraspinal Il-10 expression in our synucleinopathy models. We specifically found that Il-10 overexpression in the spinal cord of homozygous M83+/+ mice leads to gliosis, moribund condition, and early death. In the second model where hemizygous M83+/&#x02212; mice were seeded peripherally with preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils, we found that Il-10 expression similarly led to reduced lifespan. In both cases, Il-10-mediated accelerated death was not accompanied by increased &#x003b1;Syn inclusion pathology in mice phenotypically matched for paralysis with control cohorts, revealing an interesting dichotomy between neurodegenerative cascade and proteinopathy in the context of neuroinflammation. Previously, we have reported that AAV-Il-10 worsened Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (AD) pathology without affecting lifespan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Intracranial Il-10 expression in this model worsened amyloid &#x003b2; pathology by reducing microglial phagocytic activity and increasing ApoE sequestration within the extracellular amyloid &#x003b2; plaques<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. On the other hand, intraspinal AAV-Il-10 (the same construct used in this study and ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>) expression delayed paralysis and increased lifespan in the SOD1 model of ALS through moderating inflammatory chemokine signaling pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Thus, the phenotypic and neuropathologic outcomes of Il-10 signaling were widely disparate in these different neurodegenerative models, in spite of the fact that these experiments were performed on similar genetic backgrounds of mixed C57Bl6 lineage. Taken together, these observations serve as exemplars of the immunoproteostasis paradigm, whereby the same immune mediator can differentially influence the pathologic outcome based on the type of neurodegenerative proteinopathy and the context of the proteinopathy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par23">To disentangle the pleiotropic actions of Il-10 in the &#x003b1;Syn fibril-seeded M83+/&#x02212; mouse model, we used a naturally occurring variant vIl-10 that has predominantly immunosuppressive properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Contrary to our expectation that this vIl-10 would ameliorate synucleinopathy, we observed dramatic upregulation of gliosis, accumulation of soluble &#x003b1;Syn and pathological &#x003b1;Syn aggregates, and neuronal-predominant autophagic impairment in vIl-10-expressing mice compared to control mice. This unexpected effect on autophagy impairment is consistent with previous observations that Il-10 can impair lymphocyte- and dendritic cell-mediated autophagy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Interestingly, while vIl-10 and Il-10 both reduced lifespan in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83 mice, only vIl-10 exacerbated intracellular and parenchymal &#x003b1;Syn accumulation. Though our data primarily suggests that the injurious outcome of vIl-10 signaling in the &#x003b1;Syn model is mediated by neuronal autophagic impairment and a failure to clear neuronal &#x003b1;Syn, it is also possible that this phenotype can be influenced partly by vIl-10-induced microgliosis. Taken together, our study points to a novel aspect of immune signaling in synucleinopathies, whereby Il-10 conditioning can exacerbate the pathologic landscape through a combination of cell-autonomous and non-cell-autonomous means, as shown in other models of neurodegenerative diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par24">Our study opens up an intriguing question surrounding the relative roles of immune cells in the &#x003b1;Syn aggregate-seeded model. Extensive immunohistochemical examination of microglial and astrocytic proliferation showed that, in spite of having predominantly immunosuppressive properties in the peripheral immune system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, vIl-10 robustly upregulated microglial number in the spinal cord and midbrain of &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice coinciding with increased intracellular &#x003b1;Syn inclusions and parenchymal &#x003b1;Syn levels. First, this would suggest that preconditioning the CNS of a neurodegenerative proteinopathy model with a cytokine having immunosuppressive properties does not necessarily dampen gliosis. Second, it is tempting to suggest that chronic immunosuppression can result in reduced microglial clearance of &#x003b1;Syn leading to intracellular pathologies, which then leads to increased microgliosis as a form of non-cell-autonomous response to the escalating proteinopathy. This would be consistent with our earlier report where we found that inflammatory preconditioning of the CNS by Interleukin-6 restricted the seeding and transmission of &#x003b1;Syn in the brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Such non-cell-autonomous effects of immune cells on neuronal proteinopathy is especially apparent in mouse models of ALS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. It is noteworthy that Il-10 itself did not increase microgliosis in the brain or spinal cord or promoted synucleinopathy in the seeded model. Interestingly, neither Il-10 nor vIl-10 triggered astrogliosis in the spinal cord relative to GFP-expressing control mice. This highlights a clear disconnect between how microglia and astrocytes respond to the immune stimulus in different areas of the neuraxis. Such differential proliferation properties of microglia and astrocytes in response to vIl-10 and Il-10 underscores the complex role of immune signaling in neurodegenerative cascades. Future work based on spatial profiling techniques or single-cell-based techniques could clarify how microglial and astrocytic functions are differentially regulated in a spatial&#x02013;temporal context and contribute to the pathologic trajectory of synucleinopathies.</p><p id="Par25">Given the rich dataset implicating chronic neuroinflammation in PD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, our data seem somewhat counter-intuitive. To illustrate this point, our data do not agree with at least two earlier studies where IL-10 showed a beneficial effect in acute toxin models of PD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. In the first study, human IL-10 infusion was shown to reverse lipopolysaccharide-mediated dopaminergic neurodegeneration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, and in the second study, AAV-IL-10 rescued toxin-induced reductions in dopamine levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Unlike the experimental models used in our study, these acute toxin models of PD used in these previous studies do not capture the gradual physiological process that is inherent in neurodegenerative synucleinopathies&#x02014;thus, any direct comparisons would necessitate cautious interpretation. These acute toxin models also cause both neurodegeneration and neuroinflammation that are relatively nonspecific in nature in that neither of these models robustly recapitulate PD-type protein aggregation and extranigral pathology. In addition, because of their fast trajectory, these models cannot fully recapitulate the insidious nature of synucleinopathies as observed in our peripherally seeded M83+/&#x02212; model. Using Il-10 infusion is also ineffective as a therapy, as IL-10 has an extremely short half-life (2.0&#x02013;4.5&#x02009;h) that can severely limit the efficacy of the experimental paradigm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Taken together, it would seem that the outcomes of Il-10 signaling in mouse models that recapitulate PD-relevant proteinopathy as reported in our study are physiologically distinct from the acute toxin models of dopaminergic neurodegeneration.</p><p id="Par26">In conclusion, we have revealed an unexpected detrimental outcome following the expression of Il-10 and vIl-10 in mouse models of synucleinopathy. While the adverse effects of Il-10 occurred without exacerbation of &#x003b1;Syn pathology, expression of vIl-10 shortened lifespan via microgliosis, autophagic impairment, and accumulation of &#x003b1;Syn in &#x003b1;Syn-seeded mice. Our data demonstrate that immunosuppressive conditioning of the neuraxis exacerbates the pathologic landscape by altering intracellular protein-quality maintenance in conjunction with dysfunctional microgliosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Animals</title><p id="Par27">All animals were treated ethically as per protocols approved by the University of Florida Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee regulatory policies. Animals were maintained in specific pathogen-free conditions on a 12-h circadian cycle with unlimited access to food and water. Experiments were performed using standard blinding protocols of NC3R. Homozygous Line M83+/+ (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and hemizygous Line M83+/&#x02212; (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) express the human &#x003b1;Syn (<italic>SNCA</italic>) gene with the A53T mutation under control of the mouse prion protein promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Intramuscular (IM) injection of preformed &#x003b1;Syn fibrils in M83+/&#x02212; mice lead to induction of &#x003b1;Syn inclusions and paralysis within ~4 months of fibril injection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Mice used for all analyses were phenotype-matched for paralysis and moribund condition.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>&#x003b1;Syn fibril preparation and IM injection</title><p id="Par28">Recombinant mouse &#x003b1;Syn was expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified using size-exclusion and ion-exchange chromatography, as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. In total, 5&#x02009;mg/ml mouse &#x003b1;Syn protein solubilized in sterile PBS (Invitrogen) was incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with continuous shaking at 1050&#x02009;rpm. &#x003b1;Syn fibril formation was validated using K114 fluorometry, as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Immediately before injection, mouse &#x003b1;Syn fibrils were diluted to 1&#x02009;mg/ml in sterile PBS and fragmented by water bath sonication for 1&#x02009;h<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Two-month-old M83 +/&#x02212; mice were anesthetized with isoflurane. After shaving the back of the hindlimb, a 10-&#x003bc;l Hamilton syringe with a 27-gauge needle was inserted ~1&#x02009;mm into the gastrocnemius muscle to deliver 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g of &#x003b1;Syn fibril or 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of sterile PBS in each hindlimb<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>AAV preparation and injection</title><p id="Par29">GFP and murine Il-10-expressing recombinant AAVs plasmids have been generated previously and described earlier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. I87A vIl-10 was a kind gift from Dr. Scott Loiler and Dr. Terrence Flotte at the University of Florida. AAV serotype 1 was packaged by methods described earlier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Briefly, AAV vectors expressing GFP, Il-10 and, vIl-10 under the control of the cytomegalovirus enhancer/chicken beta-actin (CBA) promoter, a woodchuck hepatitis virus post-transcriptional regulatory element (WPRE), and the bovine growth hormone polyA were transfected in HEK293T cells using linear polyethylenimine (PEI, Polysciences). Cells were co-transfected with the helper plasmid pDP1rs. After 4 days, the packaged virus was purified from the cell lysates using a discontinuous Iodixanol gradient followed by buffer exchange in sterile PBS. The genomic titer was determined by quantitative PCR as described earlier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. AAVs were then aliquoted and stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until further use. For neonatal injections, AAV was diluted in sterile 1&#x000d7; DPBS, pH 7.2 to 1E13 vector genomes per ml, and used immediately as described earlier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Briefly, neonatal mice were cryoanesthetized for 3&#x02013;4&#x02009;min, resulting in the body temperature being lowered to &#x0003c;10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and injected with AAV using 10-&#x003bc;l syringes (1 inch, 33 gauge, 30 degrees beveled needle; Hamilton Company). In total, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of AAV was slowly injected into the midline, which can be seen as a white line down their back, about 5&#x02009;mm from the base of the tail. Injected pups were allowed to recover on a heated pad and returned to their home cage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Tissue processing and immunohistochemistry</title><p id="Par30">Mice were euthanized with CO<sub>2</sub> inhalation as per humane conditions and subsequently perfused using ice-cold saline containing heparin. Each spinal cord (cervical, thoracic, and lumbar segments) was divided into three sections&#x02014;12&#x02009;mm from the proximal section (containing cervical and thoracic segments, referred to as &#x0201c;thoracic&#x0201d; henceforth), 4&#x02009;mm from the midline (containing thoracic segment), and 12&#x02009;mm from the distal section containing lumbar segment (referred to as &#x0201c;lumbar&#x0201d; henceforth). The proximal and distal sections were fixed in 10% normal buffered formalin, while the midline section was flash-frozen for RNA analysis or biochemical analysis. Following paraffin processing, spinal cord fragments representing the thoracic and lumbar sections of each mouse were each serially dissected every ~2&#x02009;mm into three to four coronal sections and embedded in a paraffin block. Each paraffin block representing the thoracic or lumbar spinal cord was cut at 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;m thickness and used for immunohistochemistry. The entire brain was fixed in 10% normal buffered formalin. Each brain was then sectioned coronally distanced at 4&#x02009;mm using a brain matrix and processed for paraffin embedding. Thus, each brain slide contained four coronal sections representative of various anatomical levels of the whole brain. The brain paraffin blocks were sectioned at 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;m thickness. Paraffin-embedded tissues were immunostained using primary antibodies (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>) followed by detection with ImmPRESS Polymer Reagents (Vector Laboratories) and visualized using 3,3&#x02032;-diaminobenzidine (Vector Laboratories). Briefly, slides were deparaffinized, subjected to antigen retrieval, treated with 3% hydrogen peroxide, and blocked in 2% FBS prepared in 0.1&#x02009;M Tris buffer (pH 7.6) in preparation for primary antibody incubation overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Following secondary antibody incubation on the subsequent day, the sections were counterstained with Mayer&#x02019;s hematoxylin (Sigma), dehydrated, and mounted in Cytoseal 60 (Fisher Scientific). Stained slides were scanned using a whole-slide imager (Aperio ScanScope CS, Leica Biosystems) and images visualized using the Aperio ImageScope software (Leica Biosystems). Quantification of immunostaining was done using the Positive Pixel count program configured to detect brown color (ImageScope, Aperio Technologies). The total number of brown pixels (positive) divided by the total number of pixels (positive+negative) was represented as a % immunoreactivity burden. For the spinal cord, the % immunoreactivity values on all serial sections on each slide were counted for any given sample and averaged for the cohort. For brain sections, the immunoreactivity value from bilateral midbrain or cortex areas were tabulated. For cleaved caspase 3, the total number of positive cells was counted as the staining pattern was sparse. The total number of cells on each slide were counted for any given sample and averaged for the cohort. For co-immunofluorescence staining, the method used was identical as described above, except that slides were not incubated in hydrogen peroxide, Alexa Fluor-conjugated secondary antibodies (1:500; Invitrogen) were used to detect signal, and slides were counterstained and mounted with 4&#x02019;,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Southern Biotech). Images were captured using an Olympus BX60 Microscope fitted with an Olympus DP71 camera. Analyses were done on phenotype-matched mice. For the M83+/+ cohort, Il-10-expressing mice typically were 4&#x02013;6 months old and controls were typically 8&#x02013;12 months old (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), whereas for &#x003b1;Syn-seeded M83+/&#x02212; cohort, end-stage paralyzed mice typically aged 5&#x02013;7 months were used (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Biochemical analysis of the injected spinal cord</title><p id="Par31">Biochemical analysis was done using the thoracic spinal cord segment. The frozen tissue was cryopulverized in liquid nitrogen and divided into aliquots for protein extraction or RNA extraction. The cryopulverized tissue was homogenized in RIPA buffer containing protease and phosphatase inhibitors (Pierce), and homogenates were cleared by centrifugation at 22,000&#x02009;rpm at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min (TLA-55 rotor, Beckman Coulter). Il-10 and vIl-10 levels were analyzed using RIPA-solubilized protein lysates using mouse-specific BD OptiEIA kits (BD Biosciences) as per the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. GFAP immunoblots were done using RIPA-solubilized lysates using anti-rabbit GFAP antibody (1:500, Dako) as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. All blots derive from the same experiment and processed in parallel.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Quantification of TH neurons in the substantia nigra (SN)</title><p id="Par32">Quantification of TH neurons were done based on a previously published protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Dopaminergic neurons stained with the anti-TH polyclonal antibody (Millipore, 1:1000) were counted manually. Serial sections were cut at 10 &#x003bc;m intervals and slides containing the SN were delineated. Every 10th section was used for manual counting, whereby the number of TH neurons in the sections were averaged as representative of this particular area. The final count is a summation from each mouse and then averaged for each cohort.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Fluoro-Jade C staining</title><p id="Par33">Paraffin-embedded slides were deparaffinized, rehydrated, and incubated at room temperature in 0.06% KMnO<sub>4</sub> solution for 10&#x02009;min. Slides were incubated in 0.0001% Fluoro-Jade C (EMD Millipore) dissolved in 0.1% acetic acid for 10&#x02009;min with gentle shaking. Slides were washed, counterstained with DAPI, and dried on a slide warmer at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min. Slides were cleared in xylene for 1&#x02009;min and then mounted using Cytoseal 60 mounting medium (Fisher Scientific). Slides were imaged using an Olympus BX51 microscope mounted with a DP71 Olympus digital camera. One slide was stained per mouse (each slide contained 2&#x02013;4 lumbar spinal cord coronal sections). The total number of Fluoro-Jade C-labeled puncta was manually counted for all the spinal cord sections of any one sample and then averaged for each cohort.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>RNA isolation and NanoString analysis</title><p id="Par34">RNA was extracted from cryopulverized aliquots of the thoracic spinal cords obtained from the midline section. For the M83+/+ group, all mice displayed moribund condition (average age of 3&#x02013;4 months for Il-10 group and 8 months for GFP group). For the preformed &#x003b1;Syn seed-injected M83+/&#x02212; cohort, the analyses were done on the end-stage paralyzed mice (average age of 5&#x02013;7 months). RNA was extracted, and 100&#x02009;ng of the total RNA was analyzed on a custom NanoString codeset as described earlier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Raw count data for each sample was exported from RCC files using nSolver version 4.0. All samples passed QC analysis in nSolver. Count data were imported into R version 3.6 and Bioconductor version 3.9. Count matrices were normalized and differentially expressed genes were analyzed with DESeq2 version 1.24.0 using default normalization parameters and housekeeping genes included in the custom gene panel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. For gene ontology analysis, a false discovery rate (FDR) of less than 0.05 was used as a cutoff for significantly changed genes. Goseq version 1.36.0 was used for gene ontology analysis using the list of genes included on the custom NanoString array as background for analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The <italic>P</italic> values reported were adjusted for multiple comparisons (<italic>P</italic>adj). Graphs were generated with ggplot2 version 3.2.0. To calculate the M1-, M2-, and DAM-type signature, we used the geometric means of a set of genes previously identified to be increased under these specific conditions (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Geometric means, rather than arithmetic means, were used so as to reduce the effects of outliers which can skew the values. Briefly, the geometric mean of the counts for the selected genes within each list for each sample was calculated and then within the group, the mean and standard deviation of that value was calculated for the group score followed by a pairwise two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test to test the significance of the association.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Statistics</title><p id="Par35">For statistical comparisons, we used one-way ANOVA, multiple <italic>t</italic> test with adjustments for multiple comparisons, or two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test depending on the variables tested. Graphical data are plotted as box and whiskers plot, with the whiskers extending from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median. Graphical representation of data was done using Prism 6 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA), and final images were created using Adobe Photoshop CC (Adobe Systems).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par36">Further information on research design is available in the <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">Nature Research Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec23"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41531_2021_169_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Figure and Tables</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41531_2021_169_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41531-021-00169-8.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by NIH grant NS099738 (P.C.), the University of Florida Moonshot Initiative (P.C.), and Michael J Fox Foundation (T.E.G.).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>S.G.C., E.J.K., M.M.T.B., E.G.D.L.C., and P.C. performed mouse experiments and data analysis; K.N.M. and C.C.D. collected NanoString data and performed analysis; P.E.C. generated recombinant AAV constructs; A.W.R. assisted in AAV production; T.E.G., B.I.G., and Y.R.L. assisted in initiation and development of the project; P.C. and D.R.B. participated in data interpretation and paper writing. All authors have read the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data are contained in this paper and Supplementary information files. All materials used to generate the data will be available following the execution of the institutional material transfer agreement.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p>R Codes will be available on request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par37">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Parkinson disease and the immune system&#x02014;associations, mechanisms and therapeutics</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41582-020-0344-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32332985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32332985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doorn</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microglial phenotypes and toll-like receptor 2 in the substantia nigra and hippocampus of incidental Lewy body disease cases and Parkinson&#x02019;s disease patients</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol. Commun.</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>90</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25099483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25099483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamza</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Common genetic variation in the HLA region is associated with late-onset sporadic Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Nat. Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.642</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20711177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20711177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Parkinson Disease Genomics, C.</collab></person-group><article-title>Imputation of sequence variants for identification of genetic risks for Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: a meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2011</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)62345-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21292315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nalls</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Large-scale meta-analysis of genome-wide association data identifies six new risk loci for Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3043</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25064009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25064009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindestam Arlehamn</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alpha-Synuclein-specific T cell reactivity is associated with preclinical and early Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1875</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15626-w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32313102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32313102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sulzer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>T cells from patients with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease recognize alpha-synuclein peptides</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>546</volume><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22815</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28636593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28636593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuron-released oligomeric alpha-synuclein is an endogenous agonist of TLR2 for paracrine activation of microglia</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1562</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2534</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23463005?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23463005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathological &#x003b1;-synuclein transmission initiated by binding lymphocyte-activation gene 3</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>6307</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aah3374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAMPs and DAMPs: signal 0s that spur autophagy and immunity</article-title><source>Immunol. Rev.</source><year>2012</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2012.01146.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22889221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22889221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hirsch, E. C. &#x00026; Standaert, D. G. Ten unsolved questions about neuroinflammation in Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease. <italic>Movement Disord.</italic>10.1002/mds.28075 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Crellin</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdez</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hymowitz</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation and functions of the IL-10 family of cytokines in inflammation and disease</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-031210-101312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21166540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21166540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giasson</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuronal alpha-synucleinopathy with severe movement disorder in mice expressing A53T human alpha-synuclein</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(02)00682-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12062037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12062037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacino</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intramuscular injection of alpha-synuclein induces CNS alpha-synuclein pathology and a rapid-onset motor phenotype in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>10732</fpage><lpage>10737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1321785111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25002524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorrentino</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Motor neuron loss and neuroinflammation in a model of alpha-synuclein-induced neurodegeneration</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Dis.</source><year>2018</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2018.09.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30195075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30195075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotenko</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pestka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bromberg</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single amino acid determines the immunostimulatory activity of interleukin 10</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2000</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.191.2.213</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10637267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10637267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-10 encoded by viruses: a remarkable example of independent acquisition of a cellular gene by viruses and its subsequent evolution in the viral genome</article-title><source>J. Gen. Virol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.058966-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24225498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24225498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayers</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Widespread and efficient transduction of spinal cord and brain following neonatal AAV injection and potential disease modifying effect in ALS mice</article-title><source>Mol. Ther.</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mt.2014.180</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25228069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25228069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-10 alters immunoproteostasis in APP mice, increasing plaque burden and worsening cognitive behavior</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2015</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.11.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25619653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25619653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butovsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microglial signatures and their role in health and disease</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41583-018-0057-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30206328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30206328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosser</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-10: new perspectives on an old cytokine</article-title><source>Immunol. Rev.</source><year>2008</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2008.00706.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19161426?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19161426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groux</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cottrez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The complex role of interleukin-10 in autoimmunity</article-title><source>J. Autoimmun.</source><year>2003</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-8411(03)00044-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12791313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12791313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santin</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-10 increases Th1 cytokine production and cytotoxic potential in human papillomavirus-specific CD8(+) cytotoxic T lymphocytes</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>4729</fpage><lpage>4737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.74.10.4729-4737.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10775611?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10775611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemani</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased expression of alpha-synuclein reduces neurotransmitter release by inhibiting synaptic vesicle reclustering after endocytosis</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2010</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2009.12.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20152114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20152114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of kindreds with parkinsonism and alpha-synuclein genomic multiplications</article-title><source>Ann. Neurol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.10846</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14755720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14755720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel panel of alpha-synuclein antibodies reveal distinctive staining profiles in synucleinopathies</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0184731</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0184731</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28910367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28910367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmued</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stowers</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalett</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluoro-Jade C results in ultra high resolution and contrast labeling of degenerating neurons</article-title><source>Brain Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>1035</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2004.11.054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15713273?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15713273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-10 inhibits the starvation induced autophagy in macrophages via class I phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) pathway</article-title><source>Mol. Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2010.10.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21095008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21095008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santarelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STAT3 activation by KSHV correlates with IL-10, IL-6 and IL-23 release and an autophagic block in dendritic cells</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>4241</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep04241</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24577500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24577500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autophagy receptors and neurodegenerative diseases</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2017.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28169082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28169082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Martinet, W., Roth, L. &#x00026; De Meyer, G. R. Y. Standard immunohistochemical assays to assess autophagy in mammalian tissue. <italic>Cells</italic><bold>6</bold>, 10.3390/cells6030017 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croisier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dexter</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Graeber</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microglial inflammation in the parkinsonian substantia nigra: relationship to alpha-synuclein deposition</article-title><source>J. Neuroinflamm</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-2094-2-14</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extrastriatal spreading of microglial activation in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: a positron emission tomography study</article-title><source>Ann. Nucl. Med.</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12149-016-1099-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27299437?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27299437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iannaccone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo microglia activation in very early dementia with Lewy bodies, comparison with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Parkinsonism Relat. Dis.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parkreldis.2012.07.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindqvist</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Non-motor symptoms in patients with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease&#x02014;correlations with inflammatory cytokines in serum</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e47387</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047387</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23082161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23082161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witoelar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide pleiotropy between Parkinson disease and autoimmune diseases</article-title><source>JAMA Neurol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>780</fpage><lpage>792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2017.0469</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28586827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28586827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-17A exacerbates neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration by activating microglia in rodent models of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Brain Behav. Immun.</source><year>2019</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2019.07.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31351185?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31351185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gordon, R. et al. Inflammasome inhibition prevents alpha-synuclein pathology and dopaminergic neurodegeneration in mice. <italic>Sci. Transl. Med.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 10.1126/scitranslmed.aah4066 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naso</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomkowicz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>WL</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Strohl</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adeno-associated virus (AAV) as a vector for gene therapy</article-title><source>BioDrugs</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40259-017-0234-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28669112?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28669112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Harnessing immunoproteostasis to treat neurodegenerative disorders</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2019</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1003</fpage><lpage>1015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2019.02.027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30897353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30897353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kankel</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SWS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofengeim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the genetics and non-cell autonomous mechanisms underlying ALS/FTLD</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ.</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41418-018-0060-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29459769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29459769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Giasson</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory pre-conditioning restricts the seeded induction of alpha-synuclein pathology in wild type mice</article-title><source>Mol. Neurodegen.</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13024-016-0142-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-10 protects against inflammation-mediated degeneration of dopaminergic neurons in substantia nigra</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Aging</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>894</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2006.04.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21887889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21887889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joniec-Maciejak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The influence of AAV2-mediated gene transfer of human IL-10 on neurodegeneration and immune response in a murine model of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Pharm. Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pharep.2014.03.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huhn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacodynamics of subcutaneous recombinant human interleukin-10 in healthy volunteers</article-title><source>Clin. Pharm. Ther.</source><year>1997</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-9236(97)90065-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Absence of nigral degeneration in aged parkin/DJ-1/PINK1 triple knockout mice</article-title><source>J. Neurochem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2009.06350.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19694908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19694908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25516281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene ontology analysis for RNA-seq: accounting for selection bias</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>R14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-2-r14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20132535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20132535</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>