<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Parkinson’s disease</italic>. An emerging view emphasizes o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn as the key mediators in synucleinopathies. Soluble 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomeric species associated with polyunsaturated fatty acids have been detected in human PD and DLB brain tissues, as well as in human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-expressing transgenic mouse brain tissues. It has been suggested that unlike saturated fatty acids, increased levels of polyunsaturated fatty acids promote 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomerization in PD brains [
 <xref rid="ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Elevated levels of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomeric assemblies have been detected in the postmortem brain tissues of PD [
 <xref rid="ref087" ref-type="bibr">87–89</xref>], notably putative ∼60 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn tetramers [
 <xref rid="ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Oligomers of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn were also detected from the blood plasma and CSF of PD patients present at an increased level compared to controls [
 <xref rid="ref090" ref-type="bibr">90–92</xref>]. Hence, 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers, as well as a ratio of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers to total 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn have been proposed as biomarkers for early diagnosis of PD and PD with dementia [
 <xref rid="ref093" ref-type="bibr">93, 94</xref>]. Oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn has also been detected at an increased level from CSF of PD patients by using a highly sensitive electronic biosensor. This technique enabled the distinction of AD and PD pathologies from cognitively normal control subjects based on the detection of CSF 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomer levels [
 <xref rid="ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Although the exact mechanism by which 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers exert their toxic effects is still unknown, the presence of these oligomeric assemblies in the extracellular body fluids indicates their release from affected brain regions and opens up the intriguing possibility of subsequent propagation of these assemblies between cells. Exocytosis via exosomes has been implicated in the spreading of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in cell culture [
 <xref rid="ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. The cellular release of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers via exosomes was suggested as an alternate pathway for survival upon failure of their clearance via autophagosomes 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>].
</p>
