<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Alzheimer’s disease</italic>. Accumulating evidence demonstrates the occurrence of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn pathology, LB and Lewy neurites (LN), in 40–55% of AD brains [
 <xref rid="ref003" ref-type="bibr">3, 13, 15, 106</xref>]. Despite this observation, very few groups have measured the relative abundance of soluble 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn aggregates in postmortem AD brain tissue. Using an agnostic view about the nature of the apparent inter-relationship between 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and AD pathology, Larson and colleagues found an approximate two-fold increase over controls in soluble monomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn levels in intracellular-enriched (IC) lysates from AD brains in the absence of LB cytopathology [
 <xref rid="ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Importantly, the abundance of soluble 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn monomers in temporal cortices translated into a better biological correlate of AD-associated cognitive impairment than soluble Aβ and tau levels [
 <xref rid="ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Because the abundance and concentration of amyloid proteins directly regulate the aggregation state of said molecules, the same group hypothesized that oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn might be elevated in parallel to the increase in IC monomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn. Using a biochemical approach relying on homotypic and heterotypic enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISA), denaturing and non-denaturing electrophoreses, and size-exclusion chromatography combined with extensive immunoreactivity profiling, the same group identified increases in 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers in AD brain tissue by 25–75% with the largest accumulation in 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers corresponding to ∼35 kDa species (68% increase vs. controls) and to ∼56 kDa species (44% increase vs. controls) [
 <xref rid="ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. The nature of these dimeric and tetrameric assemblies was further confirmed using antibodies differentially detecting aggregated forms of various amyloid proteins (i.e., A11, OC, Officer) or antibodies specific to 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers (i.e., Syn33 and F8H7). Importantly, the elevation of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers in temporal cortex was also observed in additional cortical domains, namely angular, calcarine and entorhinal cortices although with distinct observed profiles for each 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomer [
 <xref rid="ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>].
</p>
