<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">αSyn binding to vesicular membranes is important, because it influences oligomerization and pathological aggregation. Evidence suggests that non-pathological αsyn is involved with vesicular dynamics in cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> and regulation of the presynaptic vesicle pool.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup> αSyn–lipid interactions may have a vesicle tethering function. It has been proposed that the broken α-helical N-terminus can function to tether intracellular vesicles via a “double-anchor” mechanism.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup> The biological significance of αsyn-mediated clustering is unknown; however, it could serve to promote the exchange of lipids between adjacent vesicles
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup> and possibly promote vesicle fusion.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup> αSyn preferentially binds to membranes with lipid-packing defects
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup> and high curvature.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup> In the neurons, αsyn is densely clustered around intracellular vesicles and vesicular tubule structures, most prominently at the nerve terminal.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>
 </sup> When incubated with small (~10–30 nm) unilamaller vesicles, the N-terminal of αsyn adopts an extended α-helical conformation as it coats the vesicular surface and a broken α-helical conformation when interacting with micelles.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup> The interaction between the N-terminus of αsyn with lipid membranes is driven by electrostatic interactions between positively charged residues and lipid phosphate head group.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>
 </sup> When membrane bound, the N-terminus residues (1–26) of αsyn rigidly bind to the membrane and the internal segment (residues 26–97) acts to sense lipid properties and regulates binding affinity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup> Interestingly, the hydrophobic stretch of residues 71–82 are required for pathological aggregation of αsyn
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>
 </sup> and, therefore, lipid-sensing properties of αsyn and pathological aggregation occur through the same functional domain. It is not clear whether mutation of the N-terminus results in a toxic gain of function or loss of function.
</p>
