<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Many cellular functions have been attributed to αsyn and membrane interactions, including soluble N‐ethylmaleimide sensitive factor attachment protein receptor (SNARE) complex assembly and exocytosis; however, the exact cellular function of αsyn remains unclear.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>
 </sup> αSyn interacts with SNARE proteins at the vesicle surface.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
 </sup> αSyn binding to membranes promotes SNARE complex formation and may function as a SNARE chaperone protein.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>
 </sup> Vesicular membrane-binding promotes the oligomerization of αsyn.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup> In vitro phospholipids can also increase the rate of pathological aggregation (i.e., β-sheet confirmations) by decreasing lag time of primary nucleation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>
 </sup> The effect of lipids on αsyn aggregation is dependent on lipid to protein ratio, with a low ratio promoting aggregation and higher ratio being inhibitory.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>
 </sup> This bimodal phenomenon probably results from a lack of monomer available for oligomer elongation when the lipid ratio is too high. Interestingly, increasing αsyn expression, presumably shifting the intracellular lipid to protein ratio, promotes aggregation of αsyn in cells. Notably, it has been hypothesized that reducing monomeric αsyn is an important therapeutic target.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
