<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">αSyn may have a more generalized cellular function as an effector of lipid dynamics, and not as a factor of a specific subprocess or pathway. To highlight this concept, consider the curious relationship between αsyn and erythropoiesis (i.e., red blood cell differentiation) for which others have hypothesized αsyn that may have an underlying redundant mechanism in the two cells of different linage.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>
 </sup> αSyn is highly expressed in erythrocytes under the control of transcription factor GATA1.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>
 </sup> During the terminal step of erythropoiesis, α-syn expression dramatically increases and remains elevated in the mature erythrocyte.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>
 </sup> αSyn is then found associated with phospholipids and vesicle membranes in the mature erythrocyte.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>
 </sup> Thus, which of the proposed cellular functions does αsyn perform during erythropoiesis? One likely explanation is that αsyn plays a role in the dramatic intracellular lipid organization, analogous to asymmetric cytokinesis, which occurs prior to the phenomenon of enucleation. Enucleation is the process by which organelles are condensed and extruded from the cell to form a mature erythrocyte. Indeed, just prior to enucleation αsyn can be found associated with lipids of the cell, particularly the nucleus and ER, which are key players in enucleation. αSyn accumulates at the site of nuclear extrusion,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>
 </sup> suggesting it is directly involved with enucleation lipid dynamics. Concurrently, SNARE machinery is decreased in the erythrocyte, suggesting that the potential involvement of αsyn in lipid dynamics during enucleation is independent of hypothesized SNARE functions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>
 </sup> However, if αsyn is involved in this cellular phenomenon, it is non-essential or interchangeable with beta or gamma synucleins, as only minor phenotypic abnormalities of erythrocytes are observed in α-syn-knockout models.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
