<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Inflammation is another prominent biological feature of PD with activated microglia present in several brain areas, e.g., such as the olfactory bulb, basal ganglia and cortex [
 <xref rid="ref063" ref-type="bibr">63–67</xref>]. Furthermore, interleukin-2 (IL-2) and infiltrating immune cells are increased in PD brain [
 <xref rid="ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] and IL-6 is elevated in plasma [
 <xref rid="ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. High levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines in CSF are associated with more severe fatigue, cognitive difficulties and depression in PD [
 <xref rid="ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Thus, ample evidence links intracerebral and systemic inflammation to PD. In addition, numerous animal models of PD also exhibit inflammation [
 <xref rid="ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Importantly, inflammation and the kynurenine pathway are directly linked. For example, interferon-
 <italic>γ</italic> (IFN-
 <italic>γ</italic>) and IL-6 increase the activity of IDO (indoleamine-2, 3 dioxygenase), the rate-limiting enzyme of the pathway. Elevated IDO activity promotes conversion of tryptophan to kynurenine, which is further metabolized to quinolinic acid (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-7-jpd171240-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Because ACMSD limits the formation of quinolinic acid by catalyzing the production of another metabolite, ACMSD can potentially reduce neurodegeneration that occurs during neuroinflammation. High levels of quinolinic acid have also been observed during neurotropic infections [
 <xref rid="ref070" ref-type="bibr">70–73</xref>]. Interestingly, epidemiological studies have linked neurotrophic infections and PD [
 <xref rid="ref074" ref-type="bibr">74, 75</xref>]. Notably, alpha-synuclein is suggested to serve to protect neurons against pathogen infections [
 <xref rid="ref076" ref-type="bibr">76, 77</xref>]. Viral infection of neurons can result in increased alpha-synuclein expression and genetic deletion of alpha-synuclein can lead to increased viral titer in the brain and exacerbated neuronal injury in experimental models of viral encephalitis [
 <xref rid="ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Induction of alpha-synuclein by viral pathogens is not just restricted to the central nervous system. Stolzenberg et al. demonstrated that alpha-synuclein expression within the enteric nervous system was induced by norovirus and associated with mucosal inflammation in the small intestine [
 <xref rid="ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Additionally, alpha-synuclein exhibits both antibacterial and anti-fungal activity, and it can protect neurons against Escherichia coli, Staphylococcus aureus and several strains of fungi [
 <xref rid="ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Of direct relevance to these findings, the gut microbiome is increasingly implicated in PD pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Alterations in the gut microbiota has been suggested to initiate a chronic immune response and increase trafficking of alpha-synuclein aggregates via the vagus nerve to the brain stem, thereby triggering PD pathology in the brain via a prion-like mechanism [
 <xref rid="ref082" ref-type="bibr">82, 83</xref>]. Recently, transfer of gut microbiome from PD patients was found to accelerate the development of microglial activation, alpha-synuclein pathology and motor deficits in mice overexpressing alpha-synuclein [
 <xref rid="ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Altogether, these studies connect inflammation and alpha-synuclein aggregation pathology, and suggest that microbial pathogens might play a role as triggers of PD.
</p>
