<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Detailed clinical information contains motor and non-motor signs of movement disorders and can be filtered according to a number of different demographic, clinical or genetic criteria. Summary statistics are readily generated by the MDSGene online tool and allow for unprecedented and easy-access data mining. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-8-jpd181505-g001">Fig. 1</xref> shows an output file of the summary statistics tool using PARK-LRRK2 as an example. The first two MDSGene Systematic reviews are based on this resource and cover recessive (PARK-Parkin, PARK-PINK1, PARK-DJ1 [
 <xref rid="ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]) and dominant forms of inherited PD (PARK-SNCA, PARK-LRRK2, PARK-VPS35 [
 <xref rid="ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], respectively. Another feature of MDSGene is its ‘signs and symptoms’ function. Considering all signs and symptoms reported in MDSGene, an optional number of clinical features can be selected in order to obtain suggestions on possible genetic diagnoses using the ‘signs and symptoms tool’. For example, when selecting ‘parkinsonism’, ‘early-onset’, and ‘dyskinesia’, the most likely genetic cause underlying this constellation of signs is given as a 
 <italic>Parkin</italic> mutation, followed by 
 <italic>PINK1</italic> and 
 <italic>DJ-1</italic> mutations based on the frequency of these mutations in the database. This aspect of the tool will become functional for other phenotypes as data for more movement disorders are collected and uploaded. For instance, as ataxias are not yet part of MDSGene, the tool may suggest an episodic ataxia as the most likely option when selecting ‘ataxia’ as a sign, whereas, in reality, a dominantly or inherited, non-episodic ataxia would be the much more likely diagnosis. In addition, an algorithm is currently being adapted for this tool taking into account frequencies of individual signs and symptoms among cases with mutations in each gene in conjunction with mutation frequency.
</p>
