<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">DNA sequencing was performed using two vendors: Macrogen and USUHS. For samples sequenced at Macrogen, one microgram of each DNA sample was fragmented by the Covaris System and further prepared according to the Illumina TruSeq DNA Sample preparation guide to obtain a final library of 300–400 bp average insert size. Libraries were multiplexed and sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq X platform. For samples sequenced by USUHS, DNA samples were processed using the Illumina TruSeq DNA PCRFree Sample Preparation kit, starting with 500 ng input and resulting in an average insert size of 310 bp. USUHS processed single-libraries on single lanes on HiSeq X flow cells, and the Macrogen protocol used multiplexing. Paired-end read sequences were processed in accordance with the pipeline standard developed by the Centers for Common Disease Genomics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The GRCh38DH reference genome was used for alignment as specified in the FE standardized pipeline [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The Broad Institute’s implementation of this FE standardized pipeline, which incorporates the GATK [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] Best Practices is publicly available and used for WGS processing. Single-nucleotide (SNV) and InDel variants were called from the processed WGS data following the GATK [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] Best Practices [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] using the Broad Institute’s workflow for joint discovery and variant quality score recalibration (VQSR). For quality control, each sample was checked using common methods for genotypes as well and sequence-related metrics. Using Plink v1.9 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], each sample’s genotype missingness rate (&lt; 95%), heterozygosity rate (exceeding ± 0.15 
 <italic>F</italic>-stat), and gender were checked. The King v2.1.3 kinship tool (8) was used to check for the presence of duplicate samples. Sequence and alignment related metrics generated by the Broad’s implementation of the FE standardized pipeline were inspected for potential quality problems. This included the sample’s mean sequence depth (&lt; 30×) and contamination rate (&gt; 2%), as reported by VerifyBamID (9), and single nucleotide variant count as reported by Picard’s CollectVariantCallingMetrics (&lt; 3 StDev) based on the sample’s genomic vcf (gvcf). Principal components (PCs) were created for each dataset using PLINK. For the PC calculation, variants were filtered for minor allele frequency (&gt; 0.01), genotype missingness (&lt; 0.05), and HWE (
 <italic>P</italic>≥1E−6), and minor allele count &lt; 3. GCTA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] was used to remove cryptically related at the level of first cousins or closer (sharing proportionally more than 12.5% of alleles).
</p>
