<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The task force agreed that one solution is the regional promotion of training opportunities in movement disorders (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). An understanding of the medical education infrastructure and options available in each country will be needed to tailor education programs accordingly. Where possible, integration of movement disorders into medical school curricula may maximize the number of physicians receiving a minimum amount of training in movement disorders. Including movement disorders training for general physicians will also be essential [
 <xref rid="ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In countries where formal sub-specialty training is available establishing, promoting, and supporting fellowships in movement disorders will allow for additional advanced (sub-specialty) training. Facilitating access to high-quality educational courses and encouraging neurologists to participate should be liaised with health authorities and neurological societies in MENASA countries. Possible formats could include sponsored programs that would allow health care providers from MENASA countries to train in established movement disorders centers. Creating symposia and congresses aimed at providing updates in the field would be another means of improving education on movement disorders among MENASA healthcare providers. The provision of online courses may be particularly helpful in improving access to such educational opportunities. In countries where continuing medical education (CME) is necessary for the renewal of medical licenses, incentivizing physicians with CME opportunities may be useful. Toward this goal of advancing education and training in the field of movement disorders, there have been recent efforts to establish a center-to-center movement disorders training program through MDS [
 <xref rid="ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Additionally, a series of educational courses in the field of PD and movement disorders were coordinated in the region through the MDS [
 <xref rid="ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]; some of these were online courses. These courses provided a platform to initiate a structured evidence-based educational process to deliver skills for better comprehensive care of PD in the region. Recently, MDS has formed the Middle East Working Group for PD and movement disorders to address these issues more thoroughly [
 <xref rid="ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
