<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Intraspinal expression of AAV-Il-10 leads to accelerated mortality in αSyn-aggregate-seeded hemizygous M83
   <bold>+</bold>/− mice.
  </title>
  <p>
   <bold>a</bold> Schematic summarizing the experimental procedure (top panel). M83+/− neonates were injected intraspinally (Spc) with AAV-Il-10 or AAV-GFP (control). Mice were aged to 2 months and injected intramuscularly (IM) with preformed αSyn fibrils or PBS (vehicle control). Mice were aged to paralysis. The median age of survival of αSyn-seeded Il-10 or GFP-expressing mice was 112 days and 124.5 days post αSyn seeding respectively (log-rank test, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 10–18/group). 
   <bold>b–</bold>
   <bold>n</bold> NanoString analysis of the αSyn or vehicle (PBS)-seeded thoracic spinal cords of M83+/− mice expressing Il-10 or GFP. 
   <bold>b</bold>, 
   <bold>c</bold> Volcano plot of differentially expressed genes (
   <bold>b</bold>) and gene ontology pathway analysis of overrepresented functional categories (
   <bold>c</bold>) accompanying Il-10 overexpression in M83+/− spinal cords (
   <italic>P</italic>adj &lt; 0.05; dotted line). To avoid skewing the volcano plot, the 
   <italic>x</italic> axis is limited to a range of −2.5 to +4 and as a result, Il-10 data is not plotted (log2 FC = 10.537; 
   <italic>P</italic>adj value = 5.9e-07). 
   <bold>d</bold>–
   <bold>f</bold> M1-, M2-, and DAM-type microglial profiling in Il-10-expressing M83+/− mice. Two-tailed 
   <italic>t</italic> test, *
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. 
   <bold>g</bold>, 
   <bold>h</bold> Volcano plot of differentially expressed genes (
   <bold>g</bold>) and gene ontology pathway analysis of overrepresented functional categories (
   <bold>h</bold>; 
   <italic>P</italic>adj &lt; 0.05, dotted line) in αSyn-seeded Il-10-expressing M83+/− mice vs vehicle-seeded Il-10-expressing M83+/− mice. 
   <bold>i</bold>–
   <bold>k</bold> M1-, M2-, and DAM-type microglial profiling in Il-10-expressing M83+/− mice in the presence or absence of intramuscular (IM) αSyn seeding. 
   <bold>l</bold>–
   <bold>n</bold> M1-, M2-, and DAM-type microglial profiling in Il-10 vs GFP-expressing αSyn-seeded M83+/− mice. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3 mice/group. Red dots significantly changed genes, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and gray dots, 
   <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05 in volcano plots after adjusting for multiple testing and FDR &lt; 0.05. In the box plot, the whiskers extend from the minimum to maximum values, with the midline representing the median.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41531_2021_169_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e886" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
