<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Today, biobanks are known as massive scale datasets containing many hundreds of thousands of participants from specified populations. Biobanks have brought enormous power to association studies. Although it was unclear whether these new databases would deliver their most ambitious promises, the potential of biobanks in enabling personalised treatment was noted before the technology matured. It was initially expected that these databases would lead to the rapid discovery of a better genetic understanding of complex disorders, allowing for personalised treatments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, it is now clear that this expectation was exaggerated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. For example, a comprehensive review of the genomics of hypertension on its way to personalised medicine concluded that despite the wealth of identified genomic signals, actionable results are lacking [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. No new drugs for the treatment of hypertension were approved for more than two decades. Moreover, the tailoring of therapy to each patient has not progressed beyond considering self-reported African ancestry and serum renin levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Another example is autism, the most extensively studied (40 years) and heavily funded ($2.4B in NIH funding over the past ten years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]) mental disorder with nearly three dozen biobanks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Despite these major efforts at understanding the disorder, there is still no single genetic test for autism, not to mention genetic treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. These gloomy reports of the state of knowledge in two of the most studied complex disorders, which typically harness massive biobanks, were not what the biobank enthusiasts envisioned at the beginning of the century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].
</p>
