<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Back then, both private and government-sponsored banks began amassing tissues and data. For example, Generation Scotland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] includes DNA, tissues and phenotypic information from nearly 30,000 Scots [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]; the 100,000 Genomes Project sequenced the genomes of over 100,000 NHS patients with rare diseases, aiming to understand the aetiology of their conditions from their genomic data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]; and the UK Biobank project sequenced the complete genomes of over half a million individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] with the aim of improving the prevention, diagnosis and treatment of a wide range of diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Pending projects include the Genome Russia Project, which aims to fill the gap in the mapping of human populations by providing the whole-genome sequences of some 3000 people, from a variety of regions of Russia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Biobanks are not without controversy. In Iceland, deCODE genetics has created the world’s most extensive and comprehensive population data collection on genealogy, genotypes and phenotypes of a single population. However, the economic value of the genomic data remained largely inaccessible, and the company filed for bankruptcy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The experience of deCODE highlighted the risks in entrusting private companies to manage genomic databases, promoting similar efforts to have at least partial government control in the dozens of newly founded biobanks (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]), as illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Moreover, as the use of biobanks is expanding beyond their locality, for example, in the case of rare conditions where samples need to be pooled from multiple biobanks, the view of biobanks should be changed from locally-managed resources to more global resources. These should adhere to international standards to increase the accuracy of association studies and the use of biobanks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. 
</p>
