<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Genome-wide association studies (GWAS), and newer whole-genome sequencing (WGS) studies, are the most recent in a series of strategies to determine the genetic underpinning of complex human diseases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. GWAS evolved from hypothesis-driven candidate gene association studies (CGAS) during the last quarter of the 20th century. As technology developed, unbiased, genome-wide searches became possible. Nevertheless, like CGAS, these were originally intended to produce two types of valuable knowledge. Firstly, researchers hoped to uncover the underlying molecular mechanisms by which a disease originates, and in particular, identify all relevant genes and gene variants (i.e., disease causality). Secondly, genetic associations were expected to provide useful diagnostic markers for both public and individual health decisions. Unfortunately, it has turned out to be harder than expected to make the leap from statistical risk associations to mechanistic insight, and very few experiments are done based on GWAS results
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. Instead, emphasis (or at least progress) has shifted to favor the second objective. Polygenic risk scores are being increasingly refined to give higher confidence predictions of disease risk for people of increasingly diverse populations. The utility of this has been reviewed
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. For some diseases, including diabetes, breast cancer, and coronary heart disease, polygenic risk informs treatment options and helps to stratify disease subtypes. However, in the case of Parkinson’s Disease (PD) and similar diseases (Multiple System Atrophy, Dementia with Lewy bodies, Progressive supranuclear palsy, for example), our understanding of the disease is too limited, and treatment options too few, for polygenic scoring to currently have practical use. There is no treatment that alters disease course and management for the related diseases is essentially identical. Hence, for PD, predictive genetic diagnostics will remain largely irrelevant to patients without other major advancements. These include more treatment targets and a more detailed understanding of all of the many relevant biological pathways underpinning pathogenesis. Notably, these topics closely match the predicted but unrealized value in GWAS
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. But, as several recent comment papers have suggested or implied, for the PD field to make headway it must reorient its conceptualization of existing GWAS results and funding agencies should place greater emphasis on post-GWAS research
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. Here, we argue that, in the PD field, the potential for, and difficulty in acquiring, GWAS-based disease insight is underappreciated by those who are not themselves engaged in post-GWAS research; this is partially due to underinvestment in mechanistic follow-up studies and the resulting dearth in testable hypothesis.
</p>
