<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alternatively, there is a strong hypothesis that neuronal ATP deficiency, such as that which accompanies mitochondrial dysfunction, is involved in PD etiology.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
  <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]
 </sup> One facet of ATP deficiency is that UA levels are generally lower in individuals in whom ATP consumption is likely to be decreased, such as infirm elderly or those with low physical functioning or nutritional status.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
  <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]
 </sup> Thus, hypouricemia observed in neurodegenerative diseases including PD is possibly due to a decrease in ATP use due to ATP deficiency. In support of that, analyses of brain FDG-PET (Fluorodeoxyglucose-Positron Emission Tomography) to model differences between healthy controls and PD patients identified Parkinsons disease-related patterns.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]
 </sup> Those patterns were defined by hypometabolism (decreased glucose use) across much of the cerebral cortex (including frontal, premotor, parietal, and occipital regions) and hypermetabolism (increased glucose use) in relatively smaller portions of the brain (parts of the cerebellum, pons, thalamus, and basal ganglia).
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]
 </sup> Since brain glucose is mainly used for ATP regeneration, the larger decrease in glucose metabolism observed in PD patients is likely to reflect a decrease in ATP regeneration. In other words, it suggests that both ATP regeneration and ATP use in the brain are decreased in PD. As further support, studies using the cybrid method identified decreased mitochondrial function in platelets from PD patients, and levels of hypoxanthine (Hyp), the degradation product of Ino via purine nucleotide phosphorylase, were reported to be decreased by 42% in unmedicated PD patients compared to controls.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]
 </sup>
</p>
