<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">Notably, growing evidence implicates the role of lysosomal dysfunction in both autoimmune disorders and neurodegenerative diseases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. In the context of PD, the decrease of lysosomal enzyme activity, such as resulting from the mutation of 
 <italic>GBA</italic> and 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>, may lead to the aggregation of α-­synuclein and the formation of Lewy bodies, which is the pathological hallmark of PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, overexpression of lysosomal proteases cathepsin D could reduce the accumulation of α-­synuclein aggregates in mice model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Strikingly, elevated levels of lysosomal enzyme activity have been reported to occur in several autoimmune diseases, including rheumatoid arthritis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. In rheumatoid arthritis, high levels of several lysosomal cathepsins (B, D, G, K, L, and S) are present both in the serum and synovial fluid of patients, which is contradictory to the condition of PD with a lower level of lysosomal enzyme activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, rheumatoid arthritis may shed the protective effect on PD through the lysosome pathway, which is worth further exploration. In addition, all treatments available for PD are symptomatic only and could not slow down the progression up till now. Therefore, it’s urgent and important to search for new effective therapeutic approaches for PD. The present results suggested that explorations of the mechanisms of inflammation and immune response, as well as lysosomal dysfunction, have the potential to provide new targets for the treatment of PD.
</p>
