<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">The retromer complex orchestrates sequence-dependent cargo retrieval as opposed to sequence-independent bulk recycling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>
 </sup>. However, the sequence responsible for DAT-retromer interaction remains to be determined. The PDZ domain is a well characterized recycling sequence recognized by retromer and its adaptor protein for plasma membrane recycling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>
 </sup>. The same mechanism is proposed to regulate retromer-mediated recycling of DAT
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, mice harboring mutations in the putative PDZ domain of DAT exhibit reduced surface DAT expression in the striatum
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, the DAT PDZ motif was required, at least partially, for exit out of retromer-positive endosomes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>
 </sup>. However, unlike well-characterized retromer cargos such as beta 2 adrenergic receptor (β2AR) or glucose transporter1 (GLUT1)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>
 </sup> which have a type I PDZ domain, DAT has a type II PDZ domain. This is unlikely to be recognized by SNX27, the adaptor protein best characterized in retromer-mediated plasma membrane recycling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>
 </sup>. Retromer binding is sometimes facilitated by palmitoylation of cysteine residues in the cytosolic tails of cargo proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>
 </sup>, and notably, DAT undergoes C’-terminal cysteine palmitoylation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>
 </sup>. Pharmacological inhibition or mutagenesis of those cysteine residues enhances PMA-induced downregulation of DAT in heterologous cells and rat striatal synaptosomes, suggesting palmitoylation may function to resist PKC-mediated DAT degradation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>
 </sup>. The functional impact of palmitoylation on dopamine reuptake kinetics of surface DAT is well described
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>
 </sup>, but whether palmitoylation affects DAT endocytic sorting and trafficking is unknown.
</p>
