<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P17">Alternative splicing and alternative transcriptional promoter choice produces three main isoforms of 
 <italic>APOE4</italic> (
 <italic>APOE4-001, -002</italic>, and -
 <italic>005</italic>) [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>APOE-001</italic> and 
 <italic>APOE-002</italic> isoforms contain exon 1 while the 
 <italic>APOE-005</italic> isoform is generated by a promoter upstream of exon 2 [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Conflicting results have been obtained on the predominance of one 
 <italic>APOE4</italic> isoform over the others. For example, RNA-Seq experiments originally suggested that the 
 <italic>APOE4-005</italic> transcript was up regulated in AD while the 
 <italic>APOE4-001</italic> isoform was down regulated [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, Mills et al. was unable to confirm these results via the use of real time-quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) [
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The reasoning behind these discrepancies are not known but may be due to the possibility that RNA samples being taken from different areas of the temporal lobe in the two studies showed differential expression. In addition, the sample size in the Mills et al. study was 14 temporal lobe samples, whereas in the Twine et al. study the sample size was 1 temporal lobe sample. The findings from a small sample size in the Twine et al. study may be leading to an exaggerated difference between these studies. Alternatively, it is possible that the AD cases used in the two studies were not comparable in terms of pathology [
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Finally, due to the issue of heterogeneity of the disease process in AD patients, the progression of the disease most likely varies significantly between affected individuals expressing the 
 <italic>APOE4</italic> allele. Therefore, although the data support the notion that 
 <italic>APOE4</italic> is alternatively spiced additional studies are warranted to address the degree to which splice variant of 
 <italic>APOE4</italic> is up- or down regulated in normal versus AD tissues and at different stages of the disease.
</p>
