<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn fn-type="abbr">
  <p>Abbreviations: BNP = brain natriuretic peptide, CSF = cerebrospinal fluid, FDG-PET = Fluorodeoxyglucose-Positron Emission Tomography, GWAS = genome-wide association study, HPLC = high-performance liquid chromatography. SD = standard deviation, Hyp = hypoxanthine, Ino = Inosine, MDS-UPDRS = Movement Disorder Society-sponsored revision of the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale, MMSE = Mini-Mental State Exam, PCA = perchloric acid, PD = Parkinson's disease, PPS = Per Protocol Set, ROS = reactive oxygen species, SAF = Safety Analysis Set, SURE-PD = Study of URate Elevation in Parkinson's disease, T-Cho = total cholesterol, TP = total protein, UA = uric acid, Xan = xanthine, XOR = xanthine oxidoreductase.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>How to cite this article: Watanabe H, Hattori T, Kume A, Misu K, Ito T, Koike Y, Johnson TA, Kamitsuji S, Kamatani N, Sobue G. Improved Parkinson's disease motor score in a single-arm open-label trial of febuxostat and inosine. 
   <italic>Medicine</italic>. 2020;99:35(e21576).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
  <p>This work was performed under the auspices of StaGen Co., Ltd. TJ, SK, and NK are employees of StaGen Co. Ltd. NK and SK hold stock in StaGen Co. Ltd. StaGen Co., Ltd. has received a patent in Japan and the United States for use of febuxostat + Ino as an ATP enhancement therapy and has pending patent applications in other jurisdictions. GS and HW served as paid scientific advisors, and TH, AK, KM, TI, and YK served as paid principle investigators in the present study. NK received lecture fees from Teijin Pharma. GS received funding for travel and speaker honoraria from Teijin Pharma Ltd.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
