<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="mds28144-sec-0001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>
   <italic>GBA</italic> mutations are numerically the most significant genetic risk factor for Parkinson's disease (PD), yet these mutations have low penetrance, suggesting additional mechanisms.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="mds28144-sec-0002">
  <title>Objectives</title>
  <p>The objective of this study was to determine if the penetrance of 
   <italic>GBA</italic> in PD can be explained by regulatory effects on 
   <italic>GBA</italic> and modifier genes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="mds28144-sec-0003">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Genetic variants associated with the regulation of 
   <italic>GBA</italic> were identified by screening 128 common single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the 
   <italic>GBA</italic> locus for spatial 
   <italic>cis‐</italic>expression quantitative trail locus (supported by chromatin interactions).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="mds28144-sec-0004">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>We identified common noncoding SNPs within 
   <italic>GBA</italic> that (1) regulate GBA expression in peripheral tissues, some of which display α‐synuclein pathology and (2) coregulate potential modifier genes in the central nervous system and/or peripheral tissues. Haplotypes based on 3 of these SNPs delay disease onset by 5 years. In addition, SNPs on 6 separate chromosomes coregulate 
   <italic>GBA</italic> expression specifically in either the substantia nigra or cortex, and their combined effect potentially modulates motor and cognitive symptoms, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="mds28144-sec-0005">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>This work provides a new perspective on the haplotype‐specific effects of 
   <italic>GBA</italic> and the genetic etiology of PD, expanding the role of 
   <italic>GBA</italic> from the gene encoding the β‐glucocerebrosidase (GCase) to that of a central regulator and modifier of PD onset, with 
   <italic>GBA</italic> expression itself subject to distant regulation. Some idiopathic patients might possess insufficient 
   <italic>GBA</italic>‐encoded GCase activity in the substantia nigra as the result of distant regulatory variants and therefore might benefit from 
   <italic>GBA</italic>‐targeting therapeutics. The SNPs’ regulatory impacts provide a plausible explanation for the variable phenotypes also observed in 
   <italic>GBA</italic>‐centric Gaucher's disease and dementia with Lewy bodies. © 2020 The Authors. 
   <italic>Movement Disorders</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals, LLC on behalf of International Parkinson and Movement Disorder Society.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
