<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have confirmed that genetic variants in the primary sequence of the lncRNA genes (noncoding RNA transcripts) are highly correlated with human diseases [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, it is difficult to determine the contribution of intronic and intergenic SNPs to the development of disease since these are located outside of the primary RNA sequences. The expression pattern of many lncRNAs shows spatial and temporal specificity, pointing to the strong regulation of lncRNAs expression [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Abnormal expression of several lncRNAs is linked to human diseases, for example, elevated level of particular lncRNAs expression closely correlates with several types of cancer formation and/or metastatic activity [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. SNPs of noncoding genomic regions—either intronic or intergenic—are often located in or closely linked to regulatory regions [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. They may interfere with host regulatory elements [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and may affect the expression level of lncRNAs implicated in the pathogenesis of certain diseases. The results of our in silico analysis demonstrated that the 
 <italic>BCYRN1</italic> rs13388259 polymorphism lies close to the binding site of the transcription factor HNF4A. HNF4A was identified as a central regulator hub gene upregulated in peripheral blood of PD patient [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]; moreover, the relative abundance of the HNF4A mRNA correlates with the severity of the disease: upon 3-year follow-up constantly increasing HNF4A expression was observed [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The 
 <italic>BCYRN1</italic> was predicted as a target gene of HNF4A transcription factor binding site. These data together suggest that the rs13388259 polymorphism may modify the expression level of BC200 lncRNA due to the modification of HNF4A transcription factor binding affinity.
</p>
