<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract abstract-type="executive-summary">
 <title>eLife digest</title>
 <p>In our lifetime, we go through many changes – physically and also intellectually. At certain ages, we are particularly vulnerable to develop psychiatric disorders, and the majority of mental conditions start to manifest in teenagers and young adults. The symptoms for schizophrenia, for example, a mental health disorder in which patients often experience hallucinations, delusion or changes in behavior, typically start in the mid-twenties.</p>
 <p>Schizophrenia tends to run in families and it is likely that different combinations of faulty genes that affect the connections between nerve cells increase the chance of having the disease. Until now, scientists have assumed that certain situations and environmental factors trigger the condition, but it was unknown if genes could influence the age at which the disease will begin.</p>
 <p>To explore whether genes in the brain change at certain time points, Skene et al. examined how the genes are turned on and off across the lifespan of healthy mice and humans. The results showed that in both mice and humans, a ‘genetic lifespan calendar’ controlled every cell type in the brain and directed the way they worked at different ages. The timing was so precise that it was possible tell the age of a mouse or a person simply by looking at the way the genes were expressed in a tissue sample.</p>
 <p>Skene et al. then studied how the genetic lifespan calendar controlled the genes damaged in schizophrenia, and found that the calendar caused a major reorganization of the genes at the time when the symptoms started. This suggests that the genetic lifespan calendar is a crucial factor that can determine at what age the disease will start.</p>
 <p>The next step will be to study how the genetic lifespan calendar programs changes throughout the brain and to explore if it could be manipulated to change how the brain ages. This could help to develop new types of treatments for schizophrenia and other conditions of the brain.</p>
</abstract>
