<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3">
 <label>Fig. 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>
   <italic>NLRP3</italic> SNP rs7525979 impacts NLRP3 protein life cycle in vitro. Four independent polyclonal HEK293 cell lines were generated to express 
   <italic>NLRP3</italic>
   <sup>
    <italic>WT</italic>
   </sup>, 
   <italic>NLRP3</italic>
   <sup>
    <italic>979</italic>
   </sup>, or empty vector control. 
   <bold>a</bold> Polysome profiling analysis comparing cells expressing 
   <italic>NLRP3</italic>
   <sup>
    <italic>WT</italic>
   </sup> or 
   <italic>NLRP3</italic>
   <sup>
    <italic>979</italic>
   </sup> (absorbance was measured at 254 nm, tracings are offset to improve visualization). 
   <bold>b</bold> Relative 
   <italic>NLRP3</italic> mRNA transcript levels, quantified by real-time PCR, in the light and heavy polysome fractions as indicated in 
   <bold>a</bold>. Representative data shown, assayed in triplicate, two biologic repeats. (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.0011, one-way ANOVA). 
   <bold>c</bold> Representative immunoblots indicating steady-state levels of NLRP3 and HSPA5 in four independently selected polyclonal cultures as measured following gel fractionation using SDS-PAGE. NLRP3
   <sup>979</sup> expression was significantly greater than NLRP3
   <sup>WT</sup> expression across multiple independent cell lines (*
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, 
   <italic>t</italic> test). HSPA5 expression was significantly greater in cultures expressing NLRP3
   <sup>979</sup> compared to cells expressing NLRP3
   <sup>WT</sup> (**
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, one-way ANOVA). 
   <bold>d</bold> NLRP3 protein stability experiments were conducted with cycloheximide (CXH) treatment over 8 h, followed by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting. Representative immunoblotting of NLRP3 in CHX treated cells over 8 h. Linear regression analysis was performed using the GraphPad Prism software. (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.0130, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3 biologic replicates). Protein loading in all immunoblotting experiments was controlled by normalizing to beta actin. Error bars in 
   <bold>b</bold>, 
   <bold>c</bold> represent s.e.m. Blots are representative, derived from the same experiment, processed in parallel, and replicated as described
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41531_2018_61_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1252" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
