<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par72">We showed that microglia are the main cell brain population expressing Plcg2. The function of PLCγ2 in the immune system has been studied in relation to autoinflammatory and immune deficiency syndromes associated with PLCG2 mutations in humans and mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In the brain, microglia activation of Plcg2 might regulate intracellular calcium release, as shown for B cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], and contribute to the modulation of specific immune responses such as phagocytosis, migration, proliferation, and survival. One receptor acting upstream of Plcg2 and evoking such responses in innate immune cells might be Trem2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Indeed, human induced pluripotent stem cell microglia-like cells harboring mutations in TREM2 show distinct defects in phagocytosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. We found apparent co-localization of 
 <italic>Plcg2</italic> and 
 <italic>Trem2</italic> transcripts in microglia processes, which suggests a possible requirement of local translation for quick responses to environmental changes, and a mechanism to detect neural tissue damage. Mutations in TREM2 have been associated with increased risk of AD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Moreover, increased levels of Trem2 have been detected in disease-associated microglia compared to microglia in a homeostatic state (37). We found Plcg2 expression in microglia surrounding amyloid plaques in a mouse model of AD as well as in “homeostatic” microglia. This pathway, and in particular PLCγ2 activity, could be critical for microglia function in neurodegenerative conditions. Other potential signaling links of PLCγ2 variants with upstream (ITGAM or FC receptors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]) or downstream (e.g., the NRLP3 inflammasome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]) components in microglia will be also addressed by our further studies.
</p>
