<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heterozygous mutations and variants in glucocerebrosidase (
 <italic>GBA</italic>) are present in 3–5% of individuals with Parkinson’s disease (PD).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>
 </sup> The scavenger receptor class B member 2 (
 <italic>SCARB2</italic>) gene encodes a protein, lysosome membrane protein 2 (LIMP-2), that transports β-glucocerebrosidase (GCase) from the endoplasmic reticulum through the Golgi apparatus and endosomes to the lysosome.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>
 </sup> Homozygous mutations in 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> cause a rare form of progressive myoclonic epilepsy, action myoclonus-renal failure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>
 </sup> Affected patients have significantly reduced GCase activity (7 nmol/mg protein per h compared with 15 nmol/mg protein per h in controls),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>
 </sup> that is in the range observed for carriers of Gaucher disease (
 <italic>GBA</italic> heterozygotes). Two common single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), rs6812193 (refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>; 5′ of 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic>) and rs6825004
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>
 </sup> (intron in 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic>), have been shown to be associated with PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5 bib6 bib7">5–7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>
 </sup> and Dementia with Lewy Bodies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>
 </sup> in several genetic studies, including large genome-wide association studies. Furthermore, given that homozygous mutations in 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> are associated with reduced GCase activity,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>
 </sup> it is possible that these SNPs modify the risk for PD via modulation of GCase activity. In this study, we tested the hypotheses that (1) these two SNPs would be associated with PD in a New York PD cohort; and (2) that protective variants are associated with higher GCase enzymatic activity as measured in dried blood spots when compared with carriers of the non-protective variant (e.g., if indeed rs6812193 is associated with lower PD risk via 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> then carriers of the protective nucleotide, T, will have higher GCase activity than carriers of the C allele).
</p>
