<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">We have long appreciated that human aneuploidies (whole chromosome gains or losses) are a major cause of congenital disorders as well as infertility and pregnancy loss (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>). The vast majority of chromosome imbalances are not compatible with fetal development and live birth. The incidence of aneuploidy is 0.3% in newborns, 6.9% in stillbirths, and 50% in first trimester miscarriages, thus aneuploidy affects at least 10% of all clinically-recognized pregnancies 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>. The rate of preclinical losses due to aneuploidy are currently unknown, but might be much higher as 30% of human eggs are aneuploid 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. The 30% aneuploidy rate in human eggs is an average and does not reflect the maternal age effect. Recent studies of human eggs across female reproductive lifespan revealed that aneuploidy follows a U curve that can explain the natural fertility curve in humans. Aneuploidy rates are high in eggs from teenagers (&lt; 20 years), improve with age (20–32 years), and then deteriorate again as women reach their mid-30s. Even in the age group with the lowest aneuploidy rate, an extremely high baseline rate of 20% of all eggs is observed (
 <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). In young teenagers, the larger chromosomes (chr. 1–6) tend to missegregate, whereas smaller chromosomes (chr. 21, 22) are more error-prone towards the end of fertility. The segregation errors also change with age. In teenagers, whole chromosomes tend to missegregate (meiosis I nondisjunction), whereas sister chromatids, separate at meiosis I (reverse segregation) instead of homologous chromosomes or precociously segregate (premature separation of sister chromatids) in women of advanced maternal age (
 <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). These observations suggest that features of meiotic chromosomes change with increasing age defining the quality of the oocyte over the reproductive lifespan of the women, which acts as a molecular timer for fertility 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>.
</p>
