<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="S30">
 <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
 <p id="P54">Support for this research was provided by funding from the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS), United States (R25NS065723 Translational Neuroscience Training Grant, P30NS055077 NINDS Emory Neuroscience Core) and National Institute on Aging (NIA), United States (R01AG053960, R01AG057911, R01AG061800, RF1AG057470, RF1AG05747101, U01AG046161 Accelerating Medicine Partnership for Alzheimer’s disease, P50AG025688 Emory Alzheimer’s Disease Research Center).</p>
 <p id="P55">The results published here are in whole or in part based on data obtained from the AMP-AD Knowledge Portal (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://adknowledgeportal.synapse.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://adknowledgeportal.synapse.org/</ext-link>). BLSA data were generated from postmortem brain tissue collected through the National Institute on Aging’s Baltimore Longitudinal Study of Aging and provided by Dr. Levey from Emory University.
 </p>
 <p id="P56">ACT data were generated from postmortem brain tissue collected through the Adult Changes in Thought study (E. Larsen), and The University of Washington ADRC (T. Montine), with the proteomics provided by Drs. Seyfried, Lah, and Levey from Emory University (NIA U01 AG046161; NIA P50 AG025688; NIA P30 NS055077).</p>
 <p id="P57">MSBB data were provided by Dr. Levey from Emory University based on postmortem brain tissue collected through the Mount Sinai VA Medical Center Brain Bank provided by Dr. Eric Schadt from Mount Sinai School of Medicine.</p>
 <p id="P58">Banner data were provided by Dr. Levey from Emory University. A portion of these data were generated from samples collected through the Sun Health Research Institute Brain and Body Donation Program of Sun City, Arizona. The Brain and Body Donation Program is supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (U24 NS072026 National Brain and Tissue Resource for Parkinson’s Disease and Related Disorders), the National Institute on Aging (P30 AG19610 Arizona Alzheimer’s Disease Core Center), the Arizona Department of Health Services, United States (contract 211002, Arizona Alzheimer’s Research Center), the Arizona Biomedical Research Commission, United States (contracts 4001, 0011, 05-901 and 1001 to the Arizona Parkinson’s Disease Consortium) and the Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson’s Research, United States.</p>
 <p id="P59">Mayo data were provided by Dr. Levey from Emory University based on postmortem brain tissue provided by the following sources: The Mayo Clinic Alzheimers Disease Genetic Studies, led by Dr. Nilufer Taner and Dr. Steven G. Younkin, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, FL using samples from the Mayo Clinic Study of Aging, the Mayo Clinic Alzheimers Disease Research Center, and the Mayo Clinic Brain Bank. Data collection was supported through funding by NIA grants P50 AG016574, R01 AG032990, U01 AG046139, R01 AG018023, U01 AG006576, U01 AG006786, R01 AG025711, R01 AG017216, R01 AG003949, NINDS grant R01 NS080820, CurePSP Foundation, United States, and support from Mayo Foundation, United States. Study data includes samples collected through the Sun Health Research Institute Brain and Body Donation Program of Sun City, Arizona. The Brain and Body Donation Program is supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (U24 NS072026 National Brain and Tissue Resource for Parkinsons Disease and Related Disorders), the National Institute on Aging (P30 AG19610 Arizona Alzheimers Disease Core Center), the Arizona Department of Health Services, United States (contract 211002, Arizona Alzheimers Research Center), the Arizona Biomedical Research Commission, United States (contracts 4001, 0011, 05-901 and 1001 to the Arizona Parkinson’s Disease Consortium) and the Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinsons Research, United States.</p>
 <p id="P60">UPenn data were generated from postmortem brain tissue collected through the University of Pennsylvania and provided by Dr. Levey from Emory University. Emory data were generated from postmortem brain tissue collected through the Emory Alzheimers Disease Research Center Brain Bank and provided by Dr. Levey from Emory University.</p>
</ack>
