<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">At the membrane, αsynO-β might act similar to a “molecular shovel” inserting itself into the membrane with destructive, toxic, consequences.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">138</xref>
 </sup> Together with lipid/vesicle interactions at the center of αsyn function, a route to pathophysiology might be the collapse of clustered lipids/vesicles into a pathological inclusion. Similar to a massive star transitioning to a black hole, at some point pathological αsyn and lipids form a critically dense structure, and compact to form a Lewy body. Interestingly, the architecture of the Lewy pathology supports this interpretation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">144</xref>
 </sup> Neuropathological examination of patient brains shows a mixture of αsyn staining in neurons that consist of a pale diffuse, punctate irregular shape (i.e., uneven distribution), discrete body (i.e., pale body), and a massive dense structure with a pale core (i.e., Lewy body).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>
 </sup> These structures have been hypothesized to be snapshots of a pathological process with Lewy bodies being the result. Indeed, pale bodies contain a mixture of granular and vesicular structures and are often found near mature LB.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>
 </sup> Using a lipid centric view, punctate irregular “early” pathology might represent the initial vesicle clustering
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> or lipid droplet formation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup> before the characteristic pathology develops. Overexpression of αsyn in yeast models produces lipid only inclusions, lacking the filamentous αsyn that is the hallmark of synucleinopathies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">146</xref>
 </sup> Lipids have been identified as a core component of Lewy pathology
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147">147</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148">148</xref>
 </sup> but this has largely been ignored and the pathology is often considered “proteinaceous.”
</p>
