<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The fold changes observed in the proteomics data were small, and potential reasons that might contribute to this are: 1) the 3600 proteins included in the proteomics analysis were biased towards abundant proteins that could be robustly identified and variations in abundant proteins tend to be smaller, 2) while the isotopic labeling proteomics techniques, such as tandem-mass tag (TMT) and isobaric tag for relative and absolute quantification (iTRAQ), are mass spectrometry techniques with good quantitative accuracy, quantitation at the peptide level does lead to systematic underestimation of protein fold changes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], 3) prefrontal cortex is not the primary brain region affected in PD, and 4) proteins in the brain have slower turnover compared with proteins from other tissue types [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. While age at death was not significantly different between the PD and control groups in the proteomics study, the RNA-Seq PD samples showed a significantly later age at death when compared with the control samples (t-test 
 <italic>p</italic>-value = 0.0046). Additionally, while post-mortem interval values were not significantly different between PD and control samples in the proteomics and RNA-Seq studies, they were significantly increased in the control group from the microarray validation study (t-test 
 <italic>p</italic>-value = 3.9E-2). These are consequences of the fact that human brain tissue with high quality RNA is not easily accessible, especially from neurologically healthy control samples. A final limitation is the omission of non-coding RNAs, which have yielded intriguing findings in previous studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Because the purpose of this study was to integrate a differential analysis of proteomics data with RNA-sequencing data, we focused exclusively on the analysis of protein-coding genes. However, the analysis of other RNA biotypes represents a logical next step.
</p>
