<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Lipid rafts are cholesterol- and sphingolipid-enriched microdomains on the plasma membrane. DAT is proposed to distribute equally among raft and non-raft domains
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. Although it is generally acknowledged that DAT association with lipid rafts negatively regulates the kinetics of the transporter activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup> and membrane mobility
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>
 </sup>, the role of lipid rafts on DAT endocytosis is controversial. While some studies report raft-associated DAT exhibits more resistance to constitutive and PKC mediated endocytosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>, others show DAT endocytosis arises equally from raft and non-raft associated populations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. DAT forms a stable protein complex with membrane protein flotillin-1, and that interaction appears to be required for DAT targeting to lipid rafts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. siRNA mediated flotillin-1 knock down may block PMA-mediated DAT endocytosis in heterologous systems and mid-brain dopaminergic neuronal cultures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Paradoxically, in an independent study, the same treatment did not exhibit any effect in PMA-treated HA-DAT expressing cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Lipid rafts provide a scaffold for plasma membrane protein interactions with the cytoskeleton and promote DAT clustering
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. It is possible that flotillin facilitates endocytosis by promoting DAT clustering prior to carrier formation, rather than being directly involved in carrier formation, as shown for other cargos
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup>. However, the conflicting results might be due to the model system used to study raft and non-raft associated DAT trafficking. Future studies might directly examine the trafficking routes of DAT-flotillin complexes in mid-brain dopaminergic neurons expressing DAT endogenously.
</p>
