<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P36">Postmortem human brain tissues were obtained from the Baltimore Longitudinal Study of Aging (BLSA) at Johns Hopkins University, Adult Changes of Thought (ACT) at the University of Washington and Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sound, Mount Sinai Brain Bank (MSBB) at Mount Sinai University, Banner Sun Health Research Institute (Banner), Mayo Clinic Brain Bank (Mayo) at the Mayo Clinic in Jacksonville, Florida, University of Pennsylvania Brain Bank (UPenn), and Emory University (Emory). All human samples were obtained under their respective institutional review board. For details about sample-level metadata including diagnosis, gender, neuropathological criteria, etc. please see 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>. The BLSA samples consisted of 97 samples from the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (BA9 area) and precuneus (parietal cortex, BA7) representing 15 controls, 15 AsymAD and 20 AD cases (
 <xref rid="R108" ref-type="bibr">Seyfried et al., 2017</xref>). The BLSA precuneus region was not used in our analyses. The ACT samples consisted of 65 samples from 12 controls, 14 AsymAD and 39 AD cases from prefrontal cortex area. The MSBB consisted of 251 prefrontal cortex samples from 78 controls, 28 AD possible, 13 AD probable and 132 AD definite cases based on clinical dementia rating (CDR) scores (
 <xref rid="R85" ref-type="bibr">Morris, 1993</xref>). The Banner samples were from prefrontal cortex of 30 controls, 28 mild cognitive impairment, 33 AsymAD and 98 confirmed AD cases. The Mayo samples were from temporal cortex consisting of 28 controls, 84 AD, and 84 PSP cases. The UPenn samples were from prefrontal cortex consisting of 43 controls, 42 AD, 58 ALS, 29 FTD-TDP, 22 MSA, 33 PD, 58 PD-dementia, and 48 PSP-CBD. Emory samples were previously published (
 <xref rid="R97" ref-type="bibr">Ping et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R108" ref-type="bibr">Seyfried et al., 2017</xref>). This study was performed under the auspices of the UCLA Office of Human Research Protection, which determined that it was exempt because samples were anonymous pathological specimens (IRB# 15-001397).
</p>
