<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We measured the association of three potential markers of cell senescence—telomere length, p16 and p21 expression in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) with PD status and progression. We found that telomere length at baseline discriminated well between PD patients and age-matched controls, in line with some previous cross-sectional studies [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21–23, 25</xref>], but conflicting with others [
 <xref rid="ref012" ref-type="bibr">12, 13, 24, 26</xref>]. A previous meta-analysis suggested no telomere length differences overall, although there were large discrepancies on size and gender distributions of the cohorts included as well as in the types of tissues sampled [
 <xref rid="ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Nevertheless, we also showed a similar difference at 18 months follow-up, with faster rates of telomere shortening in PD participants. This is in contrast to a recent study [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] that did not find different telomere attrition rates between baseline and 36 months for controls and PD patients. While both PD cohorts were very similar in terms of HY and MDS-UDPRS-III scores at baseline, our cohort was slightly younger (about 3 years), with shorter disease duration at baseline and, importantly, larger. Importantly, we found shorter telomeres at baseline in those PD patients who went on to develop an early dementia. These patients showed no differences in p21 or p16 gene expression levels, or inflammatory score compared to those who did not develop dementia. Unfortunately, the small number of incident PDD cases in our study precluded a meaningful regression analysis of the predictive power of telomere length for PDD. However, the relationship between shorter telomeres in peripheral blood cells and incident dementia has been reported in the general population [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], in stroke [
 <xref rid="ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], AD [
 <xref rid="ref054" ref-type="bibr">54, 55</xref>], Down’s syndrome [
 <xref rid="ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] and in the transition from MCI to dementia [
 <xref rid="ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Consequently, our results suggest that short telomeres may have predictive potential for the development of PDD.
</p>
