<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Inflammation is a characteristic of both normal aging and progressive neurodegenerative disorders of the elderly.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> Pathologic examination of postmortem tissues,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> animal modeling,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> genome-wide association studies,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> and epidemiologic studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> have related neuroinflammation with Parkinson’s disease (PD).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup> Inflammasomes are multi-protein complexes that mediate inflammation in response to both pathogens and sterile inflammatory triggers. The function of inflammasomes is best characterized in myeloid lineages where inflammasome activation results in caspase 1-dependent activation and secretion of interleukin (IL)-1β.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> Inflammasome complexes are defined by the specific cytosolic nucleotide binding and oligomerization domain (NOD)-like receptor (NLR) family member that they contain. Proteins of the pattern-recognition NLR family share homology in a highly conserved NACHT domain along with an n-terminal pyrin domain and a c-terminal leucine-rich repeat domain.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> Expression of inflammasome proteins is observed in the central nervous system (CNS), typically in monocytes and microglia responding to acute infection or cell loss as occurs during neurodegeneration.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup> Although poorly understood, expression of the 
 <italic>NLRP1</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>AIM2</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>NLRP3</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup> NLRs has been detected in neurons. These findings suggest that inflammasomes may function in neuronal cells of the CNS providing a novel mechanism by which neurons may initiate or influence inflammation.
</p>
