<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The NLRP3 inflammasome is implicated in the pathogenesis of Alzheimer’s disease (AD),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> but a role for 
 <italic>NLRP3</italic> in PD has not been characterized. Our recent animal studies indicate that mice lacking 
 <italic>Nlrp3</italic> are resistant to the development of PD symptomatology resulting from exposure to the pesticide rotenone.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup> Our findings are consistent with the reports of others who have observed that mice lacking either 
 <italic>Nlrp3</italic> or the key inflammasome effector 
 <italic>Caspase 1</italic> (
 <italic>Casp1</italic>) are resistant to nigral cell loss resulting from acute exposure to the neurotoxin MPTP.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> Further, Mao et al. recently published findings supporting a pathogenic role for the NLRP3/capase-1/IL-1β axis in the 6-OHDA PD rat model.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> The potential role for 
 <italic>NLRP3</italic> in PD is also supported by in vitro studies that describe Nlrp3 inflammasome activation by mitochondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) in monocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> and by pathologic α-synuclein in cultured glia,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> two physiologically relevant inflammatory triggers associated with the progression of both the idiopathic and monogenic forms of PD.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup> Although not yet characterized in PD, it is noteworthy that dopaminergic (DA) neurons may provide a microenvironment in which inflammasomes could be activated to initiate or propagate neuroinflammation. DA neurons are subject to inflammasome-related cellular stressors, including synuclein proteinopathy,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> oxidative stress associated with dopamine metabolism,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> and mitochondrial stress associated with genetic alterations or exposure to environmental toxins.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> Understanding whether the NLRP3 inflammasome functions in DA neurons in response to PD-associated sterile inflammatory triggers would be of broad interest, as determining how DA neurons could initiate chronic neuroinflammation in PD may shed light on the cellular and molecular mechanisms underlying the earliest stages of disease progression.
</p>
