<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Germ cell hypoplasia and primordial germ cell depletion are also seen in a range of Fanconi Anemia (FA) mouse mutants 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. The Fanconi Anemia pathway recognizes DNA structures associated with stalled replication forks in response to interstrand crosslinks that impede DNA replication and transcription (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>-Fanconi Anemia). Besides its role in removal of interstrand crosslinks, the Fanconi Anemia proteins are also activated in response to R-loop formation (RNA: DNA hybrids) 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. It consists of 19 genes that include homologous recombination genes such as 
 <italic>BRCA1/FANCS</italic> and 
 <italic>BRCA2/FANCD1</italic> (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Pathogenic mutations in the core complex components 
 <italic>FANCA, FANCC</italic> and 
 <italic>FANCG</italic> account for 85% of cases and are associated with hematological defects, subfertility, malignancies and increased spontaneous chromosome breaks and sensitivity to DNA crosslinking agents such as diepoxybutane and mitomycin C 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Mouse mutants deficient in 
 <italic>Fancm</italic>, which recognizes DNA substrates on stalled replication forks, display increased DNA damage foci (γH2AX) and reduced number of primordial germ cells. The loss of primordial germ cells can be partially rescued by inhibiting the ATM-p53-p21 signaling cascade in males but not females 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Further evidence suggests that 
 <italic>Fanca</italic> together with 
 <italic>Xpf1-Ercc1</italic> and 
 <italic>Slx4/Fancp</italic>, which are required for the repair of DNA lesions and interstrand crosslinks regulate primordial germ cell proliferation, but not differentiation or migration to the genital ridges. However, transcription coupled excision repair gene 
 <italic>Csb</italic> and nuclease 
 <italic>Fan1</italic> (required for repair of ICL-induced DNA breaks for efficient homologous recombination) are dispensable for primordial germ cell proliferation (
 <xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. In primordial germ cells, endogenous DNA crosslinks that are substrates for Fanconi Anemia-mediated repair may derive from reactive aldehydes, since 
 <italic>Fanca</italic> becomes critical in 
 <italic>Aldh2</italic> and 
 <italic>Adh5</italic> mutants that accumulate endogenous reactive aldehydes 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. The level of activity of the Fanconi Anemia pathway appears to be sufficient to sustain primordial germ cell numbers, at least in inbred mice, since single mutants of 
 <italic>Aldh2</italic> and 
 <italic>Adh5</italic> have wild-type levels of primordial germ cells by embryonic day 12.5 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.
</p>
