<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Functionally, multivariate regression analyses revealed inferior temporal gyrus levels of putative 28- and 35 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers were inversely correlated with episodic memory deficits [
 <xref rid="ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Beyond these correlative observations, proteo-transduction of SEC-segregated 28 k-Da 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers isolated from TgI2.2 mice onto wild-type primary neurons resulted in a marked suppression of synapsin-I and synapsin-II levels whereas parallel experiments using SEC-segregated monomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn had no effect on synapsins. Note that because the 35 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers co-segregated with larger 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies (&gt;70 kDa), it was not possible for the authors to assess a contribution of that assembly unlike the SEC-segregated 28 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers. Remarkably, the changes induced by SEC-segregated 28 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers were also observed in 
 <italic>SNCA</italic>-null primary neurons indicating that these species do not dependent on endogenous 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn expression to mediate their effects on synapsins. Promoter activity assays and cellular signaling studies further revealed: 1) that SEC-segregated 28 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers suppress the activation of two 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-regulated signaling pathways controlled by the cAMP responsive element-binding protein (CREB) and the nuclear receptor related 1 protein (Nurr1) and 2) novel responsive elements to CREB and Nurr1 in the 5
 <sup>′</sup>UTR/promoter region of 
 <italic>SYN1</italic> and 
 <italic>SYN2</italic> genes, two transcription factors known to be suppressed by 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn [
 <xref rid="ref129" ref-type="bibr">129, 130</xref>]. Finally, independent studies from the Björklund and Perlmann groups also demonstrated that lentivirus-mediated overexpression of full-length human WT 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn (
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup>) in midbrain dopaminergic neurons resulted in the detection of 28 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers and reductions in CREB and Nurr1 signaling [
 <xref rid="ref130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Taken together, these results provide molecular insights in neuronal changes induced by isolated 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers and warrant additional work comparing the functional roles of these two distinct dimeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species.
</p>
