<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Earlier it was shown that A30P and A53T mutants can form pore-like annular protofibrils faster than 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> and were capable of permeabilizing 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> prepared phosphatidylglycerol (PG) vesicles. It was proposed that an increase in 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn protofibril structures might occur in an early stage of PD, thus suggesting a possible mechanism of toxicity in PD [
 <xref rid="ref131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. Moreover, the same study had also demonstrated that in addition to annular protofibrils, A53T mutant synuclein can form tubular protofibrils. An ordered assembly of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> oligomers into protofibrils significantly permeabilized synthetic lipid vesicles, implying their ability to disrupt cellular membranes [
 <xref rid="ref132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Using multiple techniques, including cryo-EM, another study has demonstrated the formation of two types of annular assemblies of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn, one with a typical ring shape and another with a cylindrical shape. Addition of these assemblies into rat midbrain neuronal cultures not only generated reactive oxygen species but also significantly disrupted synthetic lipid vesicles compared to monomeric or fibrillar 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn [
 <xref rid="ref133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. However, in another study, 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn pre-fibrillar oligomers (PFOs) showed comparatively stronger membrane-permeabilizing activity than the annular protofibrils of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn. Furthermore, 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn PFOs were significantly more toxic when applied exogenously to SH-SY5Y cells compared to 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn annular protofibrils [
 <xref rid="ref134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. As different types of o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn were shown to cause cellular toxicity at different degrees, such mixed observations with annular protofibrils toxicity imply the complex nature of these amyloid assemblies.
</p>
