<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An ideal epidemiologic study on PD etiology should encompass the full spectrum of PD prodromal development with the following characteristics: a sufficiently large population-based study sample free of major prodromal symptoms of neurodegeneration at enrollment, detailed assessments of risk factors, and decades of follow-up with updated exposure assessments and monitoring of nonmotor and motor symptoms as well as disease outcomes. Such a study is however infeasible and cost prohibitive. Alternative approaches have been taken, mostly focusing on at-risk populations to study phenotypical conversion. For example, the PARS Study targets individuals with a positive family history of PD, who were first screened with a sense of smell test, and then followed individuals who had olfactory impairment with repeated dopamine transporter imaging and clinical assessments [
 <xref rid="ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. On the other hand, the TREND (Tübinger evaluation of Risk factors for the Early detection of NeuroDegeneration) study follows a risk-enriched population with symptoms of hyposmia, RBD, and depression [
 <xref rid="ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. There is also the aforementioned exemplary international collaboration to investigate phenotypical conversion from clinically diagnosed RBD to neurodegenerative diseases [
 <xref rid="ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. While these studies are instrumental to understanding symptom progression and phenotypical conversion, they had limited data on risk factors and do not address how these symptoms occur in the first place. There are ongoing efforts to adapt large prospective epidemiologic studies initially designed to study cancer and cardiovascular diseases for research on prodromal PD. Examples include the Health Professionals Follow-up Study and the Nurses’ Health Study [
 <xref rid="ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], the Rotterdam Study [
 <xref rid="ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>], the Atherosclerosis Risk In Communities Study [
 <xref rid="ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], and the Health ABC Study [
 <xref rid="ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These cohorts are typically large and population-based, recruited participants in their mid-adulthood, have collected enormous risk factor data (e.g., diet, lifestyle, environment, and genetics), and have followed participants for decades. Further, these cohorts all have parallel research on clinical PD and thus allow for investigations on these symptoms in the context of PD development. We expect these large cohort studies, together with clinical and epidemiologic efforts on phenotypical conversion, will bring answers to fundamental questions about PD etiology and beyond.
</p>
