<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the time of collecting the data for this paper (January 2019), a total of 1,070 PD patients were enrolled into the QPN and analysis is presented on this cohort of 1,070 patients. However, enrolment is ongoing, with a total of &gt;1,400 patients recruited by August 2019 at the time of completing the first draft of this manuscript. All patients were diagnosed by a movement disorder specialist in the province of Quebec according to the MDS criteria or previously published criteria for patients who were recruited before the publication of the MDS criteria [
 <xref rid="ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We included here all the patients, i.e., clinically established and clinically probable based on the MDS criteria, and PD patients diagnosed using previous criteria such as the UK Brain Bank criteria. The majority of patients (76.9%) were recruited at the MNI, the Centre Hospitalier de l’Université de Montréal (CHUM), and the Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Québec (CHUQ). Data were collected by using the QPN Questionnaire (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Material</xref>), which is completed for each participant with the help of a neurologist or a trained research assistant. This questionnaire collects data on demographics, diagnosis, motor symptoms, treatment and medications, lifestyle and environmental risk factors, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) compatibility, sleeping habits, family history of PD or PD-related disorders, non-motor symptoms and comorbidities, as well as additional tests such as cognitive and psychiatric evaluations (
 <xref rid="jpd-10-jpd191775-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). More details on the type of tests used can be found in the 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Material</xref>. The QPN categorizes the collected data according to criteria commonly used for PD clinical trials. Longitudinal clinical data are being collected from consenting patients every 18 months. Since most of the patients were recruited in the last 18 months, longitudinal data are currently available for a small portion of the patients. While not analysed in the current study, these data will be available for future studies.
</p>
