<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Oxidative stress has been shown to arise from cytoplasmic dopamine rather than extracellular dopamine [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Homeostasis of cytoplasmic dopamine depends on normal functioning of both the dopamine transporter (DAT), which recycles dopamine from the extracellular medium into the cytoplasm, and the vesicular monoamine transporter 2 (VMAT2), which packages dopamine into vesicles and helps transport it to the extracellular medium [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. VMAT2 dysfunction leads to excessive dopamine aggregation in the cytoplasm, where its metabolism generates reactive oxidative species such as 
 <sup>∙</sup>OH, O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>∙−</sup>, H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, and neurotoxic quinones [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Thus VMAT2 dysfunction may contribute to PD via two pathways. One is that the reactive oxidative species inhibit mitochondrial respiration [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], proteasome activity [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and intracellular antioxidative defenses [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], directly causing the degeneration of dopaminergic neurons in substantia nigra. The second pathway is through interaction between VMAT2 and 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein. The 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein protein is thought to contribute to PD pathogenesis by disturbing ion homeostasis, mitochondrial function, and proteostasis, as well as by inducing neuroinflammation [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. VMAT2 hypomorphic mice overexpress 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein in nigral dopamine neurons and show significantly more dopaminergic neurodegeneration than wild-type mice. This suggests that VMAT2 dysfunction leads to elevated intracellular dopamine levels, which may render dopaminergic neurons more susceptible to 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein-mediated degeneration [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Thus, VMAT2 function may be essential to prevent endogenous dopamine from becoming neurotoxic [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
