<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P3">Genetic risk factors associated with early onset AD (manifestation of AD prior to age 60) typically involve mutations in the amyloid precursor protein (
 <italic>APP</italic>) gene, presenilin 1 (
 <italic>PSEN1</italic>) gene, and presenilin2 (
 <italic>PSEN2</italic>) gene [
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These genes ultimately enhance beta amyloid peptide production [
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Different genetic risk factors are associated with both sporadic and late onset AD (cases 65 and older). Candidate genes include 
 <italic>A2M</italic> (encoding alpha-2-macroglobulin), 
 <italic>ABCA1</italic> and 
 <italic>2</italic> (encoding ATP-binding cassette transporters 1 and 2, respectively), 
 <italic>CLU</italic> (encoding clusterin), 
 <italic>PICALM</italic> (encoding the phosphatidylinositol binding clathrin assembly protein), 
 <italic>SORL1</italic> (encoding sortilin-related receptor gene), and 
 <italic>TREM2</italic> (triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 2) [
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. 
 <italic>APOE, APP</italic>, and 
 <italic>tau</italic> also have alleles associated with late onset AD and are of particular interest for this review because they show disease specific alternative splicing variants. In these genes, alternatively spliced variants also show different levels of protein expression, which may in turn have important effects upon protein aggregation [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Understanding varying gene expression could ultimately answer questions about AD pathogenesis and identify possible targets for disease treatment. As proteomic and transcriptomic technologies advance, there is now the potential to identify neurodegenerative-specific changes in postmortem brain tissues. Using these approaches could be useful in understanding protein aggregation in AD and the underlying pathology of AD, which is currently unresolved.
</p>
