<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two recent studies have indicated that mutations in the 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> gene can be associated with neurological disease with features of parkinsonism. First, Marti-Masso et al. used whole exome sequencing to determine genetic variations in a Spanish family with a history of focal myoclonic tremor, parkinsonism and epilepsy. Upon screening individuals from three generations they identified a disease-segregating mutation in the 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> gene (p.Trp26Stop codon), which was predicted to be pathogenic using two well validated computational techniques [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Although ACMSD is normally expressed in the liver, kidney and brain, the disease primarily manifests as a neurological disorder in this family, suggesting an important role for ACMSD in the brain. 
 <italic>Second</italic>, a novel p.Glu298Lys mutation in 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> was detected in a single individual with late onset (74 year-old) sporadic PD [
 <xref rid="ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The individual was negative for other disease-causing mutations and had no first degree family history of PD. Using software that predicts the pathogenicity of amino acid substitutions (MutPred and SIFT, i.e., Sorting Tolerant From Intolerant) algorithm and mutation taster, the group predicted the mutation in the 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> gene to be pathogenic as it is located at a site that is expected to disrupt enzyme structure and function. Taken together, the two reports of mutations in the 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> gene that are associated with primary PD and PD-like symptoms suggest that reduced ACMSD function might confer PD risk. The fact that one disrupted allele of 
 <italic>ACMSD</italic> might be sufficient to cause idiopathic PD in a patient is particularly strong evidence, implicating a role for this enzyme in PD pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, there may be additional, unknown risk factors that might have contributed to PD pathology in this patient. Genetic studies need to be followed by functional assays to characterize the 
 <italic>in-vivo</italic> role of this enzyme in the brain in order to draw conclusions about causative mechanisms.
</p>
