<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Two-sample SMR was applied to explore the enrichment of 
 <italic>cis</italic> eQTLs within the 46 gene-sets nominated by our large-scale PRS analysis. The methodology can be interpreted as an analysis to test if the effect size of genetic variants influencing PD risk is mediated by gene expression or methylation to prioritize genes underlying these gene-sets for follow-up functional studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. QTL association summary statistics from well-curated expression datasets were compared to Nalls et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] summary statistics after extracting the gene-set-specific independent SNPs considered as the instrumental variables. Expression datasets used for these analyses include estimates for cis-expression from the Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) Consortium (v6; whole blood and 10 brain regions), the Common Mind Consortium (CMC; dorsolateral prefrontal cortex), the Religious Orders Study and Memory and Aging Project (ROSMAP), and the Brain eQTL Almanac project (Braineac; 10 brain regions). Additionally, we studied expression patterns in blood from the largest eQTL meta-analysis so far [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. LD pruning and clumping were carried out using default SMR protocols (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cnsgenomics.com/software/smr</ext-link>). Multi-SMR p-values (gene-level expression summaries for eQTLs) were adjusted by Bonferroni multiple test correction considering the number of genes tested per gene-set, and HEIDI was used to detect pleiotropic associations between the expression levels and PD risk that could be biasing the model at a p-value &lt; 0.01 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Effect estimates represent the change in PD odds ratio per one standard deviation increase in gene expression. Enrichment of 
 <italic>cis</italic> expression was assessed per gene-set and per tissue. The number of genes tested per gene-set were Bonferroni corrected, and a Chisq test was applied to assess whether the proportion of QTLs per gene-set was significantly higher than expected by chance.
</p>
