<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Integrating epigenetic information with existing PD diagnostic tools may enhance early detection, the confidence of diagnosis and therapeutic approaches. For example, neuroimaging techniques such as DaTscan, which is used to detect the density of dopaminergic transporters in the brain, helps clinicians distinguish PD from atypical parkinsonian disorders. Patients, however, are typically symptomatic before this tool is used [
 <xref rid="ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Epigenetic-based biomarkers could rapidly discern individuals at greater risk, which would prompt clinical monitoring and neuroimaging earlier; enhancing detection of prodromal PD cases. In addition, the combination of DaTscan and epigenetic biomarkers could also predict which patients will be most responsive to the main drug for PD, levodopa, given that dopaminergic treatments affect DNA methylation at the α-synuclein gene [
 <xref rid="ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Epigenetic biomarkers may also predict therapeutic utility of the newer treatments targeting α-synuclein which are currently in clinical trials [
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Finally, epigenetic biomarkers could be used in combination with genetic screens to identify individuals at risk for familial and sporadic forms of PD. Recent studies suggest that phenotypic effects of sequence variants can be influenced by accompanying epigenetic signatures, via allele-specific methylation. Studies demonstrating the abundance of allele-specific methylation in the brain [
 <xref rid="ref039" ref-type="bibr">39, 103</xref>] and its presence at PD risk genes [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] may lead to the development of novel combinatorial genetic-epigenetic biomarkers for PD. Though still at a very early stage, epigenetic research in PD may unify the aging, environmental and genetic risk factors, and thus change the strategies used in PD diagnosis and treatment.
</p>
