<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The need for more accurate data was identified as a key priority by task force members. Epidemiological data are critical to identifying population needs, forming policies, and allocating research and health care resources. This, in turn, would inform healthcare provider training, and allow for systematic improvements in care and treatment gaps, including the availability of medications. Accurate population-level epidemiologic data are also essential for the study of the region or country-specific environmental and genetic risk factors. Although some information is available [
 <xref rid="ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], most of the data on incidence and prevalence of PD and other movement disorders in the Middle East are old (
 <xref rid="jpd-10-jpd191751-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), inconclusive and often conflicting [
 <xref rid="ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Genetic forms of PD may be disproportionately prevalent in the Middle East because of higher rates of consanguineous marriages in this part of the world [
 <xref rid="ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. While 16% of the world’s PD population are estimated to reside in MENASA countries [
 <xref rid="ref065" ref-type="bibr">65, 66</xref>], this may be an underestimate due to underreporting and under-diagnosis of the illness. This, in turn, may result from the existing limitations in health care surveillance infrastructure and delivery present in many MENASA countries. Gathering data on PD epidemiology will likely be achieved via a multi-layered approach. In countries where healthcare systems are nationalized, healthcare administrative databases may be a key source of epidemiologic data. In other countries, insurance claims and/or pharmaceutical utilization/prescribing practices may provide useful data on prevalence and even incidence. In some countries, partnering with local health organizations and other non-governmental organizations may provide key opportunities for fieldwork to understand PD prevalence. Where advanced care is provided in centralized tertiary care centers, establishing patient registries may be useful in gathering key information.
</p>
