<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this part, we mainly focus on the genetics of PD. 18 PD-specific chromosomal loci are named
 <italic> PARK</italic> and numbered chronologically, nine of which have been identified and confirmed by linkage analysis or exome sequencing [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Eight of these loci were identified by linkage analysis, functional candidate gene approach or GWAS studies, and are deemed as susceptibility loci as risk factors [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. And still one of them is supposed to be erroneous locus found to be identical with
 <italic> PARK1</italic> [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Within the nine confirmed disease-causing genes,
 <italic> SNCA</italic>,
 <italic> LRRK</italic>, and
 <italic> VPS35</italic> exhibit an autosomal dominant hereditary pattern while other six genes,
 <italic> Parkin</italic>,
 <italic> PINK1</italic>,
 <italic> DJ-1</italic>,
 <italic> ATP13A2</italic>,
 <italic> PLA2G6</italic>, and
 <italic> FBX07</italic>, display an autosomal recessive hereditary pattern. Besides, some other genes, such as
 <italic> GIGYF2</italic>, were reported to be susceptible to PD with specific variants in different ethnic populations [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The mutated genes involved in PD cause brain dysfunction through various molecular mechanisms, including disturbance of presynaptic vesicle recycling and dopamine transmission, toxicity from aggregation of mutant proteins, degeneration of dopaminergic axon in substantia nigra, instability or mislocation of certain kinases, overactivation of ubiquitin kinase activities, and decreased efficiencies of ubiquitin degradation pathways [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Although only 10–15% of PD cases are familial and studies related to the pathogenic mechanisms on the confirmed disease-causing genes or susceptible loci of PD are far from being complete, the discovery of PD-related genes is a critical step for us to unravel the mysteries behind neurodegeneration in PD. Up to date, there is limited research specifically dedicated to the study of the relationship between the genetic classifications of PD and molecular mechanisms of cognitive impairment in PD. However, some negative results indicated some distinctive genetic features of cognitive decline in PD could be differentiated from other neurodegenerative disorders with cognitive disturbances [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Furthermore, the filamentous Lewy body formation could be observed in early onset of PDD carrying SNCA mutations and Dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB) [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], and the aggregation of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein could be detected in substantia nigra as well as cortex in idiopathic PD patients, which suggests that the accumulation of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein could be the presynaptic dysfunction attributed to neuronal toxicity caused by various genetic or nongenetic risk factors. It is also found that the frequency of glucocerebrosidase mutations is increased in postmortem samples from PD patients who had positive 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein inclusions [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], and the
 <italic> BDNF</italic> (Met/Met) homozygotes demonstrate dramatically worse cognitive impairment in PD patients compared to noncarriers [
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].
</p>
