<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">There is good evidence of a naturally occurring metastable soluble αsyn oligomer (i.e., tetramer) that is devoid of vesicle/lipid binding.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup> However, the existence of a soluble αsyn tetramer is based mostly on results from crosslinking experiments.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>
 </sup> The interpretation of crosslinking experiments is non-trivial. αSyn tetramers are captured when using a permissive chemical cross-linker with spacer arm length (DSG spacer arm length 7.7 Å) and perhaps not with a shorter spacer arm (formalin spacer arm length ~2 Å).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>
 </sup> A milieu of progressively larger oligomers are formed and captured even when purified recombinant αsyn is incubated with glutaraldehyde.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>
 </sup> The successful detection of an αsyn tetramer in tissues and cells is dependent on sample preparation conditions and can be detected when cells remain intact prior to crosslinking or when tissue lysates are kept highly concentrated.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>
 </sup> Indeed, purification of αsyn prevents the detection of a soluble tetramer further suggesting a cofactor is required and this factor is likely of lipid origin.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>
 </sup> Although the question remains which lipid cofactor might be responsible for the tetramer formation, the tetramer and αsyn–lipid interactions are inextricably linked. This is highlighted when recently a transgenic mouse model (called “3K”) of tetramer deficiency was generated by introducing 3E– &gt; K mutations in αsyn’s lipid-binding N-terminus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> These 3K mice exhibit aggressive αsyn aggregation, loss of an apparent tetramer, and a motor phenotype that has some semblance to Parkinson’s disease. The lipid-binding domain was mutated in the 3K mice and correspondingly lipid interactions were enhanced
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> and similar to what was observed with similar mutations in cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>
 </sup> In both mice and cells, mutated 3K αsyn clustered around vesicles and intact tissue crosslinking captured less soluble tetramer.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>
 </sup> Was this due to less tetramer or alternatively less soluble tetramer? The results could be explained either way, but if the captured αsyn species is truly an insoluble tetramer, one would expect less detection in the soluble fraction, as the authors observed. Indeed, the results appear to fit a scenario where folding on the vesicular membrane is driving αsyn pathology without the need for a soluble tetramer. (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)
</p>
