<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Soluble αsyn oligomers have been detected using several imaging techniques. Förster resonance energy transfer (FRET) is a powerful technique used to determine intermolecular distances between molecules with 1–2 nm spatial resolution.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>
 </sup> FRET has been employed to study various aspects of αsyn oligomerization mostly in vitro
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>
 </sup> but also ex vivo
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>
 </sup> and in vivo.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>
 </sup> In vitro, purified αsyn forms distinct oligomer conformers, which then can spontaneously convert to protease resistant and toxic αsynO-β.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup> Biomolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) technique uses fluorescent constructs to determine protein–protein interaction. BiFC constructs have been used to study αsyn aggregation in vivo;
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>
 </sup> however, the resolution of this technique cannot differentiate between small oligomers and complex formation (i.e., membrane bound). The method detects diffuse staining in neurons lacking pathology, suggesting either small aggregates or close association of αsyn molecules normally within the cytosol.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>
 </sup> αSyn comes into close proximity around synaptic vesicles and possibly forms multimers on the membrane.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup> Other BiFC techniques employing photoactivatable fluorescent molecules can increase the spatial resolution to several nanometers,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>
 </sup> but this type of imaging has yet to be done with αsyn.
</p>
