<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Another puzzle in DAT trafficking is the mechanism of DAT axonal targeting. Midbrain dopaminergic neurons project long and extensively arborized terminals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. In rat a single dopaminergic neuron in the 
 <italic>substantia nigra</italic> is estimated to influence ~75,000 striatal neurons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, via as many as 370,000 terminal axonal boutons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. DAT is found throughout the plasma membrane of the axons and varicosities of dopaminergic neurons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. It seems intuitive that with such a complex morphology, dopaminergic neurons might employ local DAT synthesis rather than long-range axonal trafficking. Surprisingly, the 
 <italic>in-situ</italic> hybridization signal for DAT mRNA is primarily observed in the mid-brain and almost invisible in the striatum
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>
 </sup>, although that may reflect the probes used and the sensitivity of traditional 
 <italic>in-situ</italic> methods. It remains possible that DAT mRNA may be found outside of the somatodendritic compartment. At the protein level, most DAT localizes to smooth endoplasmic reticulum in the soma and not in axonal terminals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. In mid-brain neuronal cultures from tagged HA-DAT knock-in mice, HA-DAT vesicles display rapid bi-directional movement along axons suggesting that DAT is synthesized in somal endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and subject to axonal trafficking. A recent study examined long-range DAT trafficking in medial forebrain bundle axonal tracts to reveal that most DAT is membrane localized with a more limited distribution in retromer positive vesicles
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>
 </sup>. The result raised the possibility that DAT might be trafficked by both membrane diffusion and vesicular transport
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>
 </sup>. Future studies examining DAT localization to microtubule markers and/or microtubule motor proteins such as kinesin would further clarify the mechanism of long-range DAT trafficking.
</p>
