<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lastly, two very recent studies from the Holtzman and Bu groups investigated whether 
 <italic>APOE</italic>
 <italic>ɛ</italic>4 genotype, a major risk factor for neurodegenerative diseases, affected 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn pathology in mice and subjects with PD [
 <xref rid="ref144" ref-type="bibr">144, 145</xref>]. While both studies relied on 
 <italic>APOE</italic> knock-in (E2/E3/E4) backgrounds to compare the impact of 
 <italic>APOE</italic>
 <italic>ɛ</italic>2/
 <italic>ɛ</italic>3/
 <italic>ɛ</italic>4 alleles in mouse models of synucleinopathy, Davis and colleagues used G2.3 TgA53T mice [
 <xref rid="ref145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]; Zhao and coworkers opted for an AAV-mediated overexpression of human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup>, which does not cause amyloid inclusions as defined by a lack of Thioflavin-S positivity [
 <xref rid="ref144" ref-type="bibr">144, 146</xref>]. In both experimental settings, E4 exacerbated 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn pathology, including pathological conformational changes detected by the antibody 5G4 and pS129-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn accumulation, and worsened motor deficits. However, none of these reports assessed the exact nature of the accumulating 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn. A qualitative western blot analysis using Syn1 and MJFR-13 antibodies detecting total 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and pS129-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn respectively revealed ∼23 kDa and ∼30 kDa bands, in addition to monomeric ∼14 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn, in the SDS-soluble fraction of symptomatic G2.3 TgA53T mice which the authors interpreted as o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers [
 <xref rid="ref145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Several points are problematic with this analysis: (i) there are no quantitative measurements provided; (ii) these additional bands are detected in symptomatic TgA53T/E4, TgA53T/E3 and TgA53T lacking murine APOE (TgA53T/EKO) with no apparent difference across 
 <italic>APOE</italic> genotype; (iii) the molecular weights (∼23 kDa and ∼30 kDa) are inconsistent with those previously reported for o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn by electrophoretic separation as discussed above in this section. Based on these findings, further work is needed to determine if 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomerization is altered by 
 <italic>APOE</italic>
 <italic>ɛ</italic>4 and, if it were, what o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species are differentially accumulating across 
 <italic>APOE</italic> genotypes.
</p>
