<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The structure of αS suggests that transient αS–membrane interactions could be stabilized biochemically by either amplifying the electrostatic interaction between positive lysines in αS and negative lipid head groups (e.g., via the engineered “3K” αS mutant) or by increasing the hydrophobicity in the lower, membrane-inserted half of the αS amphipathic helix (e.g., via the engineered “KLK” αS mutant) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). We have found that such membrane-enriched mutants of αS decrease multimers and lead to acute toxicity and inclusion formation when expressed in cultured cells. The resulting inclusions, however, were shown by electron microscopy (EM) not to be overtly fibrillar but rather rich in αS-decorated vesicles.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup> This experimental finding was seemingly at odds with the original isolation of filamentous aggregates from LBs that were αS-positive by immunogold electron microscopy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup> However, it may be consistent with an experimental study of random αS point mutants that assessed their fibrillization in vitro (test tubes) and in living yeast.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> Here, in vitro fibrillization rate and in vivo yeast toxicity did not correlate, suggesting that fibrillization is not necessary for αS-induced yeast toxicity. A second screen in a library of several thousand αS-mutant yeast clones identified 25 non-cytotoxic αS sequence variants.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> Most of these sequence variants contained an αS mutation to either proline (P) or glutamic acid (E), which abnormally decreased αS membrane binding relative to wild-type (wt) αS. The authors hypothesized that αS cytotoxicity in yeast is caused by the protein binding to membranes at levels sufficient to nonspecifically disrupt membrane homeostasis. Subsequent yeast studies helped further characterize this membrane-associated toxicity: wt human αS expression in yeast (which lack an αS gene) led to vesicle clustering/aggregation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup> and vesicle-trafficking defects.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>
 </sup> “Amyloid” was typically not obvious (see also review by Jarosz and Khurana
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>
 </sup>), even though at least one study also reported fibrillar aggregates upon αS expression in yeast.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup> The relevance of the vesicle-related observations beyond yeast was supported when similar trafficking defects were described in αS A53T and αS triplication iPSC-derived human neurons.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup> Nonetheless, the putative lack of amyloid-type αS aggregates in yeast was viewed critically by some investigators, because filaments of αS had long been considered the hallmark of human Lewy cytopathology, calling into question the relevance of the αS yeast model. A debate thus arose between those that only accepted amyloid-type αS fibrillar aggregation as disease relevant and others who were open to other forms of αS misfolding, including membrane-associated aggregation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Although the former group could generally rely on the support of neuropathologists, the literature on human LBs has actually provided some evidence of membrane-associated αS aggregation.
</p>
