<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Contrasting with the anecdotal reports related to possible 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn trimers, several groups have detected putative tetrameric assemblies of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in brain lysates [
 <xref rid="ref067" ref-type="bibr">67, 71, 88, 108</xref>]. The experimental observation of putative tetramers is conceptually appealing considering the prominent detection of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers and considering the potential diversity of dimeric assemblies (see dedicated chapter above). Based on the same model relying either on 14- or on 17 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn monomeric units, homomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn tetramers can thus encompass multimeric species whose molecular weights range between 56 to 68 kDa. Like 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers, two tetrameric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies may exist, i.e., ∼58–60 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species (proposed tetramer of 14.5 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn) sensitive to SDS [
 <xref rid="ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] and ∼56 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species (possible tetramer of 14 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn or compact tetramer of 17 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn) resistant to SDS [
 <xref rid="ref088" ref-type="bibr">88, 108</xref>], based on the conflicting sensitivity of putative physiological tetramers and oligomeric tetramers to this anionic detergent. Despite the apparent resistance to SDS, the 4D6-immunoreactive ∼56 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species identified by Larson and colleagues are not covalently linked as 10 to 20% hexafluoroisopropanol (HFIP) trigger its disassembly in favor of monomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn [
 <xref rid="ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. This finding thus opens the door to the hypothesis that this oligomeric assembly corresponds to a possible homomeric tetramer of 14 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn, a compact homomeric tetramer of 17 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn molecular units or a heteromeric tetramer composed of both molecular building blocks. To attempt getting at this question, it can be postulated that, if the 28 kDa or the 35 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers were the nuclei of the ∼55–56 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn assembly, then their relative abundance in vivo might be related in brain tissue. Leveraging existing data from the Religious Orders Study cohort initially reported by Larson and coworkers [
 <xref rid="ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>], we performed pair-wise regression analyses which unexpectedly revealed strong positive correlations between the 35 kDa and 55 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species in intracellular-enriched protein fractions from individuals with no cognitive impairment (NCI) and from subjects with AD (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-10-jpd201965-g002">Fig. 2</xref>A). Quantile density contours readily illustrated the parallel elevation of both species in AD tissue compared to the NCI group (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-10-jpd201965-g002">Fig. 2</xref>A). By contrast, there was no apparent relationship between the 28 kDa and 55 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species in the same biological samples (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-10-jpd201965-g002">Fig. 2</xref>B). Together, these new results thus favor the notion that the increased amounts of intracellular 55 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species in AD brain tissue might depend on the availability of 35 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers, as opposed to the smaller 28 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers. This hypothesis is further supported by SEC profiles of similar AD lysates in which the 35 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers reliably co-eluted with larger 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species including 55–56 kDa assemblies while the 28 kDa 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers displayed an elution profile consistent with a globular molecule allowing its isolation from other 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn species [
 <xref rid="ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>].
</p>
