<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">PC is the most abundant phospholipid in cellular membranes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>
 </sup> Decreased levels of PC containing the polyunsaturated fatty acyl side chains denoted 34:5, 36:5, and 38:5 were observed in the frontal cortex of PD brains.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>
 </sup> Similarly, PD visual cortex has been reported to have reductions in some PC species with polyunsaturated 34 and 36 carbon species, as well as decreases in 16:0, 18:0, 18:1, and 18:2 lyso-phosphatidylcholines (LPCs).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>
 </sup> In a study of PD patient plasma, PC 44:6 and 44:5 were increased and PC 35:6 was decreased.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>
 </sup> Such changes in PUFAs could be the consequence of αS accumulation on membranes, because trends for lower PC species were observed in yeast and rat cortical neuron models of αS excess.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup> Treating rats with the dopaminergic neurotoxin 6-hydroxydopamine
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>
 </sup> led to early (defined by the authors as preceding “full blown primary symptoms”) lipid changes in the substantia nigra (SN), with most PC species decreased. Exceptions were LPC 16:0 and LPC 18:1, which were increased. Interestingly, sex differences in lipid changes in PD patients have been observed: in one study, PC was significantly decreased in male patients only.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>
 </sup> An in vitro study, highlighting the importance of using native αS forms for studies, reported that PC affects conformation and aggregation of the 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylated form of αS, specifically that 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylation enhances binding to PC micelles and small unilamellar vesicles with high curvature.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
