<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">Mice were euthanized with CO
 <sub>2</sub> inhalation as per humane conditions and subsequently perfused using ice-cold saline containing heparin. Each spinal cord (cervical, thoracic, and lumbar segments) was divided into three sections—12 mm from the proximal section (containing cervical and thoracic segments, referred to as “thoracic” henceforth), 4 mm from the midline (containing thoracic segment), and 12 mm from the distal section containing lumbar segment (referred to as “lumbar” henceforth). The proximal and distal sections were fixed in 10% normal buffered formalin, while the midline section was flash-frozen for RNA analysis or biochemical analysis. Following paraffin processing, spinal cord fragments representing the thoracic and lumbar sections of each mouse were each serially dissected every ~2 mm into three to four coronal sections and embedded in a paraffin block. Each paraffin block representing the thoracic or lumbar spinal cord was cut at 5 µm thickness and used for immunohistochemistry. The entire brain was fixed in 10% normal buffered formalin. Each brain was then sectioned coronally distanced at 4 mm using a brain matrix and processed for paraffin embedding. Thus, each brain slide contained four coronal sections representative of various anatomical levels of the whole brain. The brain paraffin blocks were sectioned at 10 µm thickness. Paraffin-embedded tissues were immunostained using primary antibodies (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>) followed by detection with ImmPRESS Polymer Reagents (Vector Laboratories) and visualized using 3,3′-diaminobenzidine (Vector Laboratories). Briefly, slides were deparaffinized, subjected to antigen retrieval, treated with 3% hydrogen peroxide, and blocked in 2% FBS prepared in 0.1 M Tris buffer (pH 7.6) in preparation for primary antibody incubation overnight at 4 °C. Following secondary antibody incubation on the subsequent day, the sections were counterstained with Mayer’s hematoxylin (Sigma), dehydrated, and mounted in Cytoseal 60 (Fisher Scientific). Stained slides were scanned using a whole-slide imager (Aperio ScanScope CS, Leica Biosystems) and images visualized using the Aperio ImageScope software (Leica Biosystems). Quantification of immunostaining was done using the Positive Pixel count program configured to detect brown color (ImageScope, Aperio Technologies). The total number of brown pixels (positive) divided by the total number of pixels (positive+negative) was represented as a % immunoreactivity burden. For the spinal cord, the % immunoreactivity values on all serial sections on each slide were counted for any given sample and averaged for the cohort. For brain sections, the immunoreactivity value from bilateral midbrain or cortex areas were tabulated. For cleaved caspase 3, the total number of positive cells was counted as the staining pattern was sparse. The total number of cells on each slide were counted for any given sample and averaged for the cohort. For co-immunofluorescence staining, the method used was identical as described above, except that slides were not incubated in hydrogen peroxide, Alexa Fluor-conjugated secondary antibodies (1:500; Invitrogen) were used to detect signal, and slides were counterstained and mounted with 4’,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Southern Biotech). Images were captured using an Olympus BX60 Microscope fitted with an Olympus DP71 camera. Analyses were done on phenotype-matched mice. For the M83+/+ cohort, Il-10-expressing mice typically were 4–6 months old and controls were typically 8–12 months old (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), whereas for αSyn-seeded M83+/− cohort, end-stage paralyzed mice typically aged 5–7 months were used (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).
</p>
