<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Parkinson’s Disease (PD) is a complex neurological disease, affecting approximately 2% of the population over 60 years of age. Since the first reports of PD correlation with the 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> gene
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, an increasing number of genomic predispositions has been identified as direct contributors or risk factors for the disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. In the last decade, advances in cellular reprogramming and induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) technology have led to the development of patient-derived brain tissue engineering
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. The culturing of live patient-derived neurons provides a unique opportunity to study the cellular mechanisms of genetically-linked diseases in vitro
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. IPSC studies of brain disorders remain laborious and expensive, which limits the number of cell lines that can be studied in a single laboratory and may raise the issue of statistical power and reproducibility. The field is still in its infancy, and neuronal differentiation protocols are continuously improved upon, which makes technical harmonization between studies challenging
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Like any model, iPSC studies have their weaknesses, and current limitations are being addressed collectively by the research community
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, the urgent need for better treatments for brain disorders justifies the requirement for pioneering iPSC studies modeling those diseases in vitro now. Since 2011, more than 385 neuronal lines from PD patients (and control subjects) have been generated across 67 original independent studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>
 </sup>. Independent phenotypic characterization of these lines revealed known and novel impairments in a range of cellular functions associated with PD. Moving forward, it is essential to integrate and compare the results obtained from these studies to identify the most reliable disease neuronal phenotypes before expanding the work to large drug screens. The identification of robust phenotypes of neurons derived from Parkinson’s patients’ iPSCs may provide the basis for a new paradigm in preclinical drug development and accelerates the progression towards clinical trials.
</p>
