<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">To quantify the prevalence and penetrance of genes known to be associated with PD, we analyzed 50 epidemiological
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>
 </sup> and 24 genomic studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148">148</xref>
 </sup> and a genome-wide association studies (GWAS) database
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">149</xref>
 </sup>. Within this context, we then examined recent findings from human induced pluripotent stem cell (hiPSC) models that shed light on the interplay between genetic predispositions and brain cell phenotypes in people living with PD. We present an analysis of 385 human iPSC-derived neuronal lines from 67 studies, which point towards specific impairments of dopaminergic neurons from people living with PD. In comparison with the prevalence of causal PD genes in epidemiological studies, our analysis underlines the current bias of PD iPSC studies towards a subset of familial genetic predispositions. We also summarize the methodological overlap and differences between these studies, which use a broad range of reprogramming methods. Finally, our meta-analysis highlights the possibility of converging molecular and cellular pathways underlying neurodegeneration in familial and sporadic PD with diverse genetic predispositions. In particular, we discuss the convergence of various genetic predispositions on the impairment of cellular pathways underlying metabolic function, synaptic communication, inflammation, and the recycling of damaged protein and organelles. The collective insights from independent iPSC disease studies, which are pioneering this blooming field of preclinical research, may guide us towards translating fundamental discoveries into effective treatments for patients.
</p>
