<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Furthermore, small molecules have also attracted attention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Early glucocerebrosidase chaperones that underwent clinical trials for Gaucher disease included isofagomine (afegostat-tartrate, AT2101). This treatment did not lead to significant clinical improvement and further clinical development for this indication was discontinued [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Ambroxol, which is a promising small molecule chaperone widely used in Europe as a mucolytic agent, may potentially facilitate the transit of the misfolded GCase protein to the lysosome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Its stabilizing and enhancing effects on the levels of GCase were identified in a high-throughput screen in the context of Gaucher disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. It is pH dependent, binds to the active site of the GCase protein, and reduces GCase activity. Ambroxol has also been shown to improve lysosomal function and increase enzyme activity in in vitro studies utilizing dermal fibroblasts with 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations (i.e. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>] as well as in studies performed on non-human primates (i.e. cynomolgus monkeys) with 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]). The effects of Ambroxol at high doses were recently tested in a single-center, open-label, non-controlled, clinical trial (escalating oral dose to 1.26 g per day [420 mg 3 times per day] which is considerably higher compared to the 30–120 mg/day used for the treatment of respiratory disease) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. Eighteen patients with moderately severe PD (mean age 60 years) completed the study, eight with 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations and ten mutation-negative. Ambroxol penetrated CSF, but led to a 19% reduction from the mean baseline CSF GCase activity at day 186. There was an increase of CSF α-synuclein which the authors interpreted as an increase of extracellular export of the protein from the brain parenchyma. The drug was well tolerated, and no serious adverse events were reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. For other indications, Ambroxol has been studied in &gt; 15,000 patients in more than 100 trials with an excellent safety record [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. As mentioned above, GCase activity is also reduced in iPD patients’ brains (SN) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>], making the therapy potentially relevant for iPD. The effect of Ambroxol in non-
 <italic>GBA</italic> PD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>] and non-
 <italic>GBA</italic> PD dementia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>] will be better understood once results from the two ongoing studies become available. These studies include ten non-
 <italic>GBA</italic> PD and 75 PD dementia patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>] (treated at daily doses of 420 mg/day or 525–1050 mg/day, respectively).
</p>
