<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These three pathways intersect with the unique vulnerabilities of human nigral DA neurons, which produce a large amount of dopamine for controlled release in their massive axon arbors. The need for nigral DA neurons to release an oxidation-prone neurotransmitter in a continuous, autonomous pacemaking manner underlies the vulnerabilities that are revealed by mutations of PD-linked genes. Mechanism-based drug development programs can be implemented to mimic the normal functions of these genes in suppressing oxidative stress, maintaining neuronal morphology and limiting 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein expression. Patient-specific iPSC-derived neurons would provide an excellent platform for screening compounds that block the deleterious effects of these mutations. The observation that five different monogenic causes of PD converge on three common pathways suggests that it is possible to use iPSC-derived neurons with different monogenic etiologies to cross-validate hits identified from screens. Isogenic pairs of iPSC-derived neurons can be generated by introducing PD-linked mutations to normal iPSCs or by repairing mutations in patient iPSCs. Such isogenic pairs of iPSC-derived midbrain DA neurons would be an even better platform for screening compounds, as they remove the potentially confounding influence of different genetic backgrounds between normal subjects and PD patients. Furthermore, iPSC-derived midbrain DA neurons from idiopathic PD patients can be used to validate the hits and generate valuable information on how well the findings can be extrapolated to idiopathic PD. This is highly useful and unique to the human model system, where efficacy can be established in patient-specific neurons in a dish to estimate their chance of success in patients. In addition, safety studies can be done on other types of cells (e.g., liver cells or kidney cells) differentiated from the same set of iPSCs. There is an increasing trend for pharmaceutical companies to transition their drug discovery programs to the human model system as embodied in iPSCs. The stage is set for more mechanistic study and drug discovery research on PD based on patient-specific iPSC-derived cells. The future is indeed much brighter with the advent of this transformative technology.
</p>
