<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">Phosphatidylethanolamine (PE) is the next most abundant phospholipid after PC, comprising ~25% of total mammalian cellular phospholipids.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>
 </sup> In the brain ~45% of phospholipids are PE.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>
 </sup> Using magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging, decreased PE (and PC) were observed in brains of early (Hoehn and Yahr stages I and II) PD patients but not in advanced (Hoehn and Yahr stages III and IV) cases.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>
 </sup> Decreases in multiple PE species (PE 34:2, 34:1, 36:4, 36:3, 36:1, 38:7, 38:6, 38:4, 40:6, 40:5, 40:4, 38p:7, and 40p:7) and Lysophosphatidylethanolamine species (16:0, 18:0, and 20:0p), particularly in the visual cortex, of PD patients relative to controls were reported.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>
 </sup> PE 36:3 was reduced in the amygdala and species 34:1, 36:3, and 36:2 were decreased in the anterior cortex cingulate of PD patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>
 </sup> PE 34:1 was found to be decreased in PD patient plasma.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>
 </sup> A sex difference, as observed for PC above, was also noted for PE, with significantly lower PE levels in male PD patients (vs. controls) but not in females.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>
 </sup> The consequences of reduced PE for αS phenotypes have been analyzed by genetically reducing cellular PE content. Deletion of a phosphotidylserine (PS) decarboxylase (
 <italic>PSD1</italic>), which synthesizes PE from PS, increased cytoplasmic αS inclusion formation and enhanced αS toxicity in a yeast model. Importantly, dopaminergic neuron degeneration from expressing wt human αS was enhanced by PSD1 RNAi silencing in a 
 <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> model of synucleinopathy, whereas supplementation with ethanolamine, a building block for PE synthesis, led to partial rescue.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>
 </sup> By way of follow-up, low levels of PE in the mitochondria resulted in ER stress and induced αS to form cytoplasmic foci in this model. Feeding with ethanolamine rescued this phenotype.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>
 </sup> Trends for lower levels of shorter chain PE species were observed in yeast expressing wt human αS, whereas longer-chained PE increased. Alterations in PE species appeared αS dose- and time-dependent in a rat cortical neuron model of αS accumulation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
