<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">Several epidemiological studies have linked PD and IBD. Some of the first studies from Taiwanese groups identified that patients with IBD have a 35% increased risk of PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Subsequent studies in the US
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>, Korea
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, and Sweden
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup> identified that patients with either CD or ulcerative colitis (UC) had increased risk for PD relative to healthy controls; however, a study from Denmark only found an association between UC and PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Conversely, another study examining this association in Medicare beneficiaries found the opposite association whereby a diagnosis of IBD was associated with lower incidence of PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. These conflicting results could potentially be due to chronic anti-inflammatory regimens, highlighting how differences between populations and reporting and analysis methods are important determinants of how the associations are determined and interpreted. Given these seemingly disparate findings, a systematic review and meta-analysis looking at all studies to date found overall that IBD patients had a 46% increased risk of PD (risk ratio 1.41, 95% confidence interval 1.19–1.66), and this increased risk remained when examining patients with CD (28%, risk ratio 1.28, 95% confidence interval 1.08–1.52) and UC (30%, risk ratio 1.30, 95% confidence interval 1.15–1.47) separately
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, two of the studies that found a positive association between IBD and risk for PD also found that currently available anti-TNF therapy reduced the risk of developing PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, these studies have raised the interesting possibility that novel soluble TNF-selective non-immunosuppressive anti-TNF therapies may afford potential therapeutic benefit to reduce risk for PD or slow its progression.
</p>
