<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>GWAS is only the first step in identifying disease genes. Specific causal variations and their interactions at risk sites in related genes must be identified to fully understand their impact on PD development. Saeed [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] has recently identified that 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> is a significantly associated gene for PD in a GWAS. However, the relationship between 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> SNPs and PD has not been explored so far. Three selected SNPs of 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene were the protagonists of this study, including rs10503253, rs12681349, and rs1983474. The rs10503253 SNP was reported as an important genome-wide mutation in schizophrenia by Schizophrenia Psychiatric Genome-Wide Association Study (GWAS) Consortium [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The risk “A” allele of rs10502353 was associated with a neurocognitive function such as poorer performance on measures of general cognitive ability, visuospatial memory, and strategy formation, but not with emotional decision-making [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Our results show that 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene variant rs10503253 (CA versus CC: 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.002) was significantly associated with Parkinson's disease, but allele “A” reduced the risk of PD (OR = 0.776, 95% CI = 0.623–0.996, 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.023). Furthermore, the population in northern China showed visible bias in the dominant model of the late-onset cohort of rs0503253. Allele “A” may be a protective factor of PD in the female cohort of rs10503253. However, more repeated linkage studies are required to conﬁrm this result. Another variant in 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic>, rs12681349, was identified as a novel Parkinson's disease locus by stratified GWAS [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], which was analyzed in relation to Parkinson's disease in Iranian population [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], but no positive results were found. This finding supports our research result. The SNP rs1983474 of 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> has been revealed to be connected with variation in urinary C-telopeptide of type II collagen (u CTX-II) levels [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] in osteoarthritis which was a significant independent predictor of falls in patients with PD [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this paper, we found significant differences in genotype frequency (GG versus TT: 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.012), recessive model (GG versus TT + TG: 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.001), LOPD (TG versus TT: 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.047; GG versus TT: 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.042), male (TG versus TT 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.015), and female cohort (GG versus TT 
 <italic>p</italic>=0.003) for rs1983474. This seems to support the role of inflammation in the pathophysiology of Parkinson's disease. However, the power analysis for allele frequency (power &lt;0.8) of the above SNPs suggested that an investigation using a larger sample size is warranted to further analyze the associations.
</p>
