<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene is robustly expressed mainly in the developing central nervous system (CNS) and epithelial tissues [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], with some expression in the testicles, lung, breast, colon, thyroid, and pancreas [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> is an inhibitor of classical but not alternative complement activation pathways and a regulator of CNS inflammation, which is involved in the function of growth cone. Complement cascades play a crucial role in defending against pathogens in the immune system and also are relevant to synaptic plasticity and synaptic pruning [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], which seemed to be an especially important part for cognitive processes in the development of brain [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Steen et al. [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] demonstrated that genetic ablation of 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> in mice leads to behaviors associated with sluggish emotional responses, anxiety, and depression; results also indicated that 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> influenced the psychopathology of negative symptom spectrum. At the same time, genomic studies have indicated that 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> is implicated in several neurological related diseases like schizophrenia [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], cognitive impairment [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], multiple sclerosis [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], Alzheimer's Disease [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and familial Parkinson's disease [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], which provided strong support for the hypothesis that the 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> KO mice will exhibit neuropsychological deficits [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. According to the previous studies, 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene has recently been linked to a variety of pathological processes ranging from cancer and psychiatric disorders to neurodegenerative diseases, and they are related to each other. In a Danish study, melanoma patients had a 44 percent increased risk of developing PD [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
