<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130">There is compelling evidence that meiotic recombination affects human genome evolution beyond creating new arrangement of existing genes (haplotypes). Aberrant meiotic recombination is associated with maternally-derived aneuploidies 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">[99]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">[100]</xref>. Individuals with Trisomy 21 have lower genome-wide maternal recombination rates compared to their unaffected siblings 
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">[101]</xref> and carry common genetic variants in a broad selection of meiotic recombination genes 
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>. Furthermore, breakpoints of structural variants in the human population map to meiotic recombination hotspots 
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">[103]</xref>. Several chromosomal rearrangements are consistent with non-allelic homologous recombination (NAHR) 
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">[104]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">[105]</xref>, in which the template choice for double-strand break repair is a homologous/homeologous sequences in another part of the genome (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">[106]</xref>). Such recombination events would cause a range of different chromosomal rearrangements. Because chromosomal rearrangements are rare in live births, the impact of non-allelic homologous recombination in meiosis is poorly understood. However, studying both meiotic recombination and chromosome content in single sperm, egg and embryos should allow rapid advance in our understanding of their origins. Finally, meiotic recombination is mutagenic, as events are associated with 
 <italic>de novo</italic> single nucleotide variants and insertions/deletions (INDELs), sometimes at a distance 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>. It is conceivable that although homologous recombination (HR) is predominantly implemented between homologous chromosomes in meiosis that this enforcement might vary according to genomic context 
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">[107]</xref>. Several studies in budding yeast, where recombination intermediates can be followed, have shown that strand invasions are promiscous and require Bloom helicase 
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref> and the SMC5/6 complex 
 <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr">[111]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref> for their dissolution/resolution (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Taken together, the mutagenic and destabilizing effects of meiotic recombination might limit genome-wide recombination rates, despite their advantage in preventing aneuploidy in female meiosis.
</p>
