<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When investigating the pathological mechanisms contributing to PD, the availability of human post-mortem brain tissue is limited. Nonetheless, our understanding of the composition of Lewy bodies and their distribution within the brain has increased significantly through studies using post-mortem human brain tissue from PD patients. Over the past few decades, a combination of animal and cell models has also helped elucidate some of the potential causes underlying PD. However, many of these models have limitations in truly modelling PD. Mammalian and non-mammalian animal models of PD can be divided into toxin-induced and gene-related PD models. 6-OHDA (2,4,5-trihydroxyphenethylamine) injection within animal brains, tested on dogs, cats, primates and rodent models, is toxic for DA neurons and leads to PD-like behaviour. However, neurodegeneration is restricted to DA neurons and 6-OHDA does not affect other brain areas implicated in PD. MPTP (1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,5,6-tetrahydropyridine) administration has long been used as a toxin-induced PD model. An MPTP metabolite, MPP+, inhibits complex I of the mitochondrial electron transport chain and causes neuronal death through oxidative stress. MPP + induces damage to the nigrostriatal DA connections, loss of DA cells, inflammation, and generation of reactive oxygen species. However, MPTP treatment doesn’t induce Lewy bodies or synuclein pathology in the majority of studies [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16–20</xref>]. Only one group reported inclusions positive for synuclein and ubiquitin after continuous MPTP infusion [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Rotenone and paraquat, in animals, induces Lewy body formation but their effects still remain ambiguous due to numerous contradictory results in studies [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Overall, these toxin-induced PD models commonly induce oxidative stress and death of DA neurons, as observed in PD, but they do not completely model the pathological mechanisms occurring in PD patients [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16–19, 21, 22</xref>]. Murine models have also been engineered to recapitulate genetic alterations, in PARK2, PINK1, DJ-1 (parkinsonism associated deglycase), SNCA, LRRK2 and GBA genes, observed in PD patients. Duplication or triplication of SNCA and misense mutations of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein (A30P, A53T and E46K) have been identified in familial PD. Thus, transgenic mice (knock-out and overexpression), grafting models, intracerebral injections, and virally induced expression of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein have been developed to replicate 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein overexpression and mutations [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23, 24</xref>]. Mutations in LRRK2, such as G2019S and R1441C, cause late-onset autosomal dominant forms of PD [
 <xref rid="ref025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>]. Similarly to SNCA models, LRRK2 mice models present motor impairments and reduction of striatal DA neurons, but do not display disruption of the nigrostriatal DA neurons [
 <xref rid="ref028" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref>]. Only viral vector-based model has been reported to induce degeneration of nigral DA neurons in rat [
 <xref rid="ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Homozygous mutations in PARK2 and PINK1 genes are linked to autosomal recessive PD. Many knock-out mice have been generated for these genes and presented a moderate reduction in striatal DA neuron levels accompanied by low locomotor activity, without Lewy body formation [
 <xref rid="ref032" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref>]. Long-term overexpression of human wild-type and T240R mutant parkin in rat substantia nigra induces progressive DA neurodegeneration [
 <xref rid="ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Bacterial artificial chromosome transgenic mice expressing a truncated mutant parkin exhibit age-dependent motor deficits and DA neurodegeneration [
 <xref rid="ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. DJ-1 mutations are linked to autosomal recessive and early-onset PD and different mice models recapitulate nigrostriatal DA deficits and progressive DA cell loss [
 <xref rid="ref037" ref-type="bibr">37, 38</xref>]. Finally, GBA mutations are the greatest risk factor for PD discovered to date and are associated with an enhanced risk of developing synucleinopathies. Thus, different groups have investigated the link between GBA mutations and synuclein levels. They showed a correlation between 
 <italic>β</italic>-glucosidase (GCase) levels and activity and synuclein degradation [
 <xref rid="ref039" ref-type="bibr">39–42</xref>].
</p>
