<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>James Parkinson provided the first clinical definition of the “shaking palsy” that now bears his name in 1817. A little less than 100 years later, Frederick Lewy reported the inclusion bodies that are still used today in the neuropathological diagnosis of Parkinson’s disease (PD) [
 <xref rid="ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While both the clinical and neuropathological definitions of PD have been updated many times since, two aspects stand out. First, our fundamental definition of PD is over 100 years old. Second, what has been notably missing in these updates is integration of the vast amounts of molecular data that now characterize much of our understanding of many other areas of medicine, including the neurodegenerative diseases. Indeed, although both Mendelian genetic approaches and genome-wide association studies have identified 40+ genetic loci that confer varying degrees of risk for PD [
 <xref rid="ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], genetic data have yet to influence how we diagnose PD, how we prognosticate for patients, or how we make treatment choices. Similarly, despite large-scale efforts at the international scale to develop biochemical biomarkers for PD, none of this information has crossed over into the clinic. The lack of molecular integration in our approach to PD comes into focus when we consider other areas of medicine where, for example, it would be unimaginable to diagnose, prognosticate, or determine a therapeutic plan for most types of cancer at this point without molecular guidance, or where biochemical tests (e.g., troponin and lipid measurements) routinely affect decision-making about the care of cardiology patients. It should also be noted that revised clinical criteria to the other major neurodegenerative disease, Alzheimer’s disease (AD), include biomarker evidence of amyloid-
 <italic>β</italic> (A
 <italic>β</italic>) and tangle pathology, as well as neurodegeneration, (i.e., the core pathological features of the disease [
 <xref rid="ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]).
</p>
