<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">First of all, we confirm that female gender represents a crucial non-modifiable predictive factor for LID,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> independently from body weight and genetic factors.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup> Second, our results underline that cumulative exposure to levodopa is positively associated with the development of LID, in line with the results deriving from other large cohorts of PD patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> Noteworthy, it is well known that levodopa accelerates the loss of nigrostriatal dopamine nerve terminals, a key pathophysiologic element in the development of dyskinesia. Dyskinesia in Parkinson’s disease are associated with changes in long term neuroadaptation and neuronal synaptic plasticity which in turn are linked to dopamine transporters and receptors density, respectively at a presynaptic and a postsynaptic level.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> Based on this concept, both positron emission tomography (PET) and single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) were used to assess changes in neurotransmitter pathways involved in dyskinesia and, subsequently, to identify imaging biomarkers for LID development. Notably, lower dopamine transporter activity in the putamen evaluated by 
 <sup>18</sup>F-FP-CIT-PET in de-novo PD patients has been described as significant predictor of LID.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup> Our results indicate that dopamine deficits in the contralateral putamen in de-novo PD patients is an independent predictor of a shorter time to levodopa initiation. Besides, both putamen asymmetry and caudate asymmetry indices evaluated by [
 <sup>123</sup>I]FP-CIT-SPECT significantly correlated with the development of dyskinesia, with the caudate asymmetry entering in the multivariate model. These findings reflect previous evidences indicating a positive relationship between the striatal asymmetric index and the magnitude of response to levodopa.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> Thus, PD patients with higher striatal asymmetric index show an increase of both response to levodopa and susceptibility to dyskinesia.
</p>
