<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">The probability of developing dyskinesia in Parkinson’s disease is also influenced by the initial clinical phenotype. Our findings showed that tremor-dominant (TD) phenotype is at lower risk of LID compared to PIGD or Intermediate. Previous studies have already demonstrated that tremor-dominant manifestation at disease onset is associated with a reduced risk of LID compared to rigid-akinetic (RA) phenotype.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> The reason of a lower risk of dyskinesia among TD patients may lay in different patterns of nigrostriatal denervation, morphologic lesions of the basal ganglia subregions and pathophysiological mechanisms between different phenotypes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, TD patients usually show lower striatal dopamine depletion compared to RA patients on [
 <sup>
  <bold>123</bold>
 </sup>I]FP-CIT-SPECT,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> suggesting a less pronounced predisposition to LID. Nigrostriatal dopamine depletion is one of the main prerequisite for developing dyskinesia and dopaminergic denervation is increased by disease severity. Therefore, it is not surprising that disease severity at baseline represents an important predictive factor for LID. Our findings indicate that UPDRS Part III score in de-novo patients is a significant clinical biomarker to predict dyskinesia. However, it is not fully consistent with data from STRIDE-PD trial which showed UPDRS Part II score as risk factor for dyskinesia, whereas UPDRS Part III did not correlate with dyskinesia development.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> Such contrasting results may be due to the fact that UPDRS motor score does not always reflect precisely the status of presynaptic dopamine denervation evaluated by PET or SPECT.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> The relationship between the severity of disease and the susceptibility to dyskinesia is also supported by the significant inverse correlation we found between ADL Scale score and risk of LID. Thus, patients with higher disease severity testified by greater impairment on daily living activities are more prone to develop dyskinesia. Genetic susceptibility to dyskinesia is of great interest, with conflicting results deriving from several studies focusing on single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of different genes. PPMI polygenic risk score was developed to explain the risk of idiopathic PD onset so far and it does not include several genes that are known to increase the risk of developing LID.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> However, to the best of our knowledge, for the first time in this study we highlighted a correlation between cumulative effect of known genetic risk variants of PD and LID development. Such results, if corroborated by extensive genome-wide association studies (GWAS), might represent a focus for future research. Interestingly, we also found that anxiety was associated to an increased risk of dyskinesia. This could be linked to the relationship between dopaminergic dysfunction and neuropsychiatric symptoms in early PD.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
