<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Changes in gut microbiota composition have also been linked to increased risk for PD. The relative abundance of certain families of bacteria are notably different between PD patients and healthy controls. While several studies have noted different patterns of changes, fecal levels of 
 <italic>Bifidobacteriaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, 
 <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Christensenellaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Tissierellaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Lactobacillaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Pasteurellaceae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Verrucomicrobiaceae</italic>, among others, have all been shown to be significantly altered in PD patients relative to healthy controls
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Some of these changes were associated with motor and non-motor symptoms. The fecal abundance of 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> was positively associated with gait difficulty and postural instability, while decreased levels of 
 <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic> correlated with motor impairment and disease severity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. Patients with tremors exhibited relatively higher abundances of fecal 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> relative to patients without tremors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Classifying PD patients based on GI non-motor symptoms, the abundance of 
 <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic> was found to be reduced in constipated patients relative to non-constipated patients, while diversity of 
 <italic>Firmicutes</italic> was increased in constipated patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Levels of the anti-inflammatory bacteria from the genera 
 <italic>Blautia</italic>, 
 <italic>Coprococcus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Roseburia</italic> were reduced in the colons of PD patients relative to healthy controls, while levels of the pro-inflammatory bacteria of the genus 
 <italic>Ralstonia</italic> were elevated in PD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. In accordance with these bacterial changes promoting an inflammatory environment in the GI system of PD patients, levels of immune factors, such as Flt1, IL-1α, and CXCL8 have been shown to be elevated in PD patient stool
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>, while levels of 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> and 
 <italic>Verrucomicrobia</italic> have been positively correlated with plasma levels of TNF and interferon gamma (IFNγ), respectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, changes in microbiome could potentially be used as biomarkers for disease state or risk. For more detailed analyses reviewing GI dysbiosis in PD, we refer the readers to ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
