<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">The evidence for overabundance of opportunistic pathogens in PD gut microbiome was potentially the most exciting finding of this study. Braak et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> originally hypothesized that non-inherited forms of PD are caused by a pathogen that can pass through the mucosal barrier of the gastrointestinal tract and spread to the brain through the enteric nervous system. Although many aspects of Braak’s hypothesis have gained support in recent years, there is no direct evidence that a pathogen is involved. Presence of α-synuclein in the gastrointestinal tract has been documented in persons with established Lewy body disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>, as well as those with rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder, which is considered prodromal PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. Epidemiological studies suggest that truncal vagotomy if conducted decades before onset of PD reduces risk of developing PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. In a mouse model, α-synuclein fibrils injected into the gut induced α-synuclein pathology which spread to the brain resulting in Parkinsonian neurodegeneration and behavioral phenotype; whereas truncal vagotomy and α-synuclein deficiency prevented the gut-to-brain spread and the associated neurodegeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. Human studies unrelated to PD have shown that infection in the gut or the olfactory system induce α-synuclein expression, and the increased abundance of α-synuclein mobilizes the immune system to fight the pathogen
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>. It was also shown in a genetic model of PD (
 <italic>pink1</italic> knockout mice) that intestinal infection by pathogens elicits activation of cytotoxic T cells in the periphery and the brain, and leads to deterioration of dopaminergic cells and motor impairment, suggesting that intestinal infection acts as a triggering event in PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>. Despite the increasing evidence linking the gut, α-synuclein, and inflammation to PD, there was no direct evidence that a pathogen is responsible for the pathology. Here, we present evidence from human samples indicating an overabundance of opportunistic pathogens in the gut microbiome of persons with PD. The three genera that rose to significance (
 <italic>Porphyromonas</italic>, 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic>, or 
 <italic>Corynebacterium_1)</italic> represented a larger polymicrobial cluster of opportunistic pathogens that co-occur in controls as well as in patients (although at much lower abundances in healthy gut). Per literature, these opportunist pathogens are often harmless, but can grow and cause infections if the immune system is compromised or if they penetrate sterile sites through, e.g., compromised membranes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. The exciting question is whether these are Braak’s pathogens capable of triggering PD, or they are irrelevant to PD but are able to penetrate the gut and grow, because the gut lining is compromised in PD. We re-emphasize that no claims can be made on function based solely on association. The knowledge on the function of microorganisms in the gut is currently limited. Although there may be a large body of literature, each organism has been studied with a narrow lens. Organisms that are known to be opportunistic pathogens are being looked for in clinical specimen, whether they have other critical functions is not known. The identity of these microorganisms will enable experimental studies to determine if and how they play a role in PD.
</p>
