<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">We also found elevated levels of 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> in PD, which are generally considered as probiotics. Increased 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> have been noted in some of the prior PD studies, albeit not consistently
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Both are ubiquitous inhabitants of human gut and metabolize carbohydrates derived from plants and dairy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. We found a significant correlation between increasing levodopa dose and increasing 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> levels. 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> produce a bacterial enzyme that metabolizes levodopa into dopamine before it can reach the brain, reducing efficacy of the drug and requiring higher doses, which in feedback causes further growth of the bacteria
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>
 </sup>. Ironically, 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> are sold in stores as probiotics, and a clinical trial has reported fermented milk, which contained 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, and fiber, among other active ingredients, improved constipation in PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>
 </sup>. Although generally believed to be safe, and possibly beneficial for the healthy population, they can act as opportunistic pathogens and cause infection and excessive immune stimulation in immune-compromised individuals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. It is important to understand why 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> are elevated in PD and if they are beneficial (a compensatory mechanism to overcome the dysbiosis) or detrimental (feedback of levodopa).
</p>
