<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">DAT contains twelve transmembrane helices that harbor the primary substrate binding site and have large N- and C- terminals extended into the cytoplasm. DAT undergoes N-linked glycosylation on extracellular loop 2, which is important for surface targeting of the transporter. Pathogenic amino acid substitutions have been described near the Na
 <sup>+</sup> binding site that interfere with conformational changes during transport, resulting in dystonia-parkinsonism, and which highlight the functional significance of this transmembrane domain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Additional rare substitutions have been implicated in attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and autism spectrum disorder (ASD)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. DAT N- and C- terminals have the most diverse structures among SLC6 family members, and these domains account for differential interaction profiles. Notably, the N-terminus of DAT harbors several secondary modification sites, including residues subject to phosphorylation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> and ubiquitination
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>, that are important for the activity and trafficking of the transporter. The C-terminus contains domains for interactions with other proteins including α-synuclein
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>, parkin
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>, flotillin
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> and protein kinase C (PKC)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. Recently, RAS-like GTPase, Rit2 was shown to complex with DAT and regulate PKC-stimulated DAT trafficking
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Genetic variability in the Rit2 locus has been robustly associated with PD and several other dopaminergic disorders
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
