<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">The high-resolution crystal structure of human DAT (hDAT) has not been solved as it is lipid associated and the protein aggregates during purification. Nevertheless, recent studies have resolved a partial structure of Drosophila melanogaster DAT (dDAT) in multiple conformational states. Hence, the functional dynamics of DAT and its interactions with ligands are being elucidated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. At resting state, dDAT exists in an open and outward facing conformation. Upon substrate binding, an outward facing occluded conformation forms that is stabilized by salt bridges between key residues (the extracellular gate). Then the occluded complex transitions to become inward facing. Subsequent disruption of a separate set of salt bridges (the intracellular gate) allows substrate release into the intracellular space. Mutations that disrupt the conformational structure often lead to anomalous efflux or inefficient uptake activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. However, it should be noted that dDAT intracellular N- and C- termini were removed to facilitate crystallization. In addition, dDAT was crystallized as a monomer
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>, whereas biochemical and microscopy data frequently detect dimers, oligomers and clusters of DAT molecules in DAT expressing model systems
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Oligomerization could influence DAT trafficking and surface expression. Small molecules, notably AIM100, may directly induce DAT oligomerization and subsequent endocytosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Readers are referred to the recent review for more detailed discussion on DAT oligomerization
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
