<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent report from the United Nations projects that the number of people aged 65 or older, estimated at about 703 million in 2019, will reach almost 1.5 billion in 2050 [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. As age is the biggest risk factor for neurodegeneration, this maturing of the world population will inevitably lead to a significant increase in the number of patients with neurodegenerative disorders. Parkinson's disease (PD) is a chronic progressive disease and is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder in the world [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It affects about 2% of the population over 60 years old, which corresponds today to over 7 million patients. Although symptoms can be relieved by dopamine replacement, there are a lack of treatments that actually alter the course of neurodegeneration [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Symptoms were first described in 1817 by James Parkinson in ‘An essay on shaking palsy’ [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and are characterised by rigidity, bradykinesia, tremor, and postural instability. These symptoms are thought to be due to a loss of striatal dopaminergic (DA) neurons originating in the substantia nigra pars compacta (SNpc), and the accumulation of aggregates of α-synuclein, which are a major constituent of Lewy bodies [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, the physiological and molecular mechanisms leading to these phenotypes are still largely unknown. PD is a multifactorial and complex disease that can be subclassified in familial and apparently sporadic PD. While over 90% of cases are sporadic, 22 genes have been identified from familial cases [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Many of these PD loci are either directly or indirectly associated with mitochondrial dysfunction [
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-49-551C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
