<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Disease-associated SNPs are, for the most part, in linkage disequilibrium with many other SNPs. This means that SNPs identified in GWAS are often not the true disease risk factor, but rather one of the co-inherited SNPs is likely responsible for disease risk. As a result it may be impossible to identify true causal variants using GWAS alone. Epigenetic profiling of regions surrounding co-inherited SNPs could be a useful approach to revealing true risk variants. This was shown in an elegant recent study by Soldner et al. [
 <xref rid="ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], who identified a SNP allele that can up-regulate the α-synuclein gene by 10–20%. This SNP was identified by intersecting PD- associated SNPs in the α-synuclein locus (463 SNPs) with publicly available epigenetic data generated by the NIH Roadmap. This effort revealed two SNPs in α-synuclein intron 4 that overlapped histone marks characteristic of enhancers. Enhancers are distal regulatory elements that increase the expression of genes, and enhancer activity is determined by epigenetic status. The authors then tested the effects of the SNP alleles using the CRISPR-Cas9 gene editing technique in human pluripotent stem cell-derived neurons. The G-allele of SNP rs356168 was found to significantly increase α-synuclein mRNA expression and was associated with greater PD disease risk. This is one example of a DNA variant that modifies disease risk via epigenetically-controlled regulatory elements. However, there are certainly many more, because studies of the adult brain have found that PD-associated SNPs are enriched in distal enhancers [
 <xref rid="ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Analysis of active enhancers overlapping PD risk loci have also implicated tissues outside of the central nervous system [
 <xref rid="ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Such research indicates that epigenetic analysis at PD-associated SNPs can generate molecular biomarkers for detection of disease vulnerability. In addition, combined epigenetic–genetic analysis can pave the way for the development of genetically-modified cell lines useful for drug candiadate screening and therapeutic discovery.
</p>
