<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">We report detection of 
 <italic>NLRP3</italic> expression in DA neurons in PD patients, a finding related to a recent report by Zhang et al., who found expression of the canonical inflammasome targets IL-1β and IL-18 in cerebrospinal fluid obtained from PD patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup> These findings of neuronal inflammasome expression in human tissues extend previous reports that identified neuronal 
 <italic>NLRP1</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>AIM2</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>NLRP3</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup> expression and function in rodents.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup> Collectively, these studies suggest that, in neurons, inflammasome proteins may be an important component of the cellular stress response. In the context of PD-associated cellular stressors, both mitochondrial dysfunction and misfolded protein accumulation, two pathological hallmarks of PD, have been reported to activate inflammasome proteins.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup> Specifically, many of the causal mutations in familial PD result in deregulation of mitochondrial function. Misfolded α-synuclein, one of the main components of Lewy bodies in PD, has been observed to activate the NLRP3 inflammasome in cultured microglia. Our identification of enhanced 
 <italic>NLRP3</italic> expression in neurons is of interest because prior studies of the NLRP3 inflammasome in the CNS have primarily focused on microglia. Neuron–glia interactions are of particular importance in the progression of PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> and cytosolic stress sensors like the NLRP3 inflammasome are compelling candidates for mediating such interactions based on the potential for release of diffusible factors during the process of inflammasome activation and pyroptotic cell death.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> It is intriguing to consider the possibility that DA neurons may utilize the inflammasome platform to sense intracellular sterile triggers such as ROS and misfolded proteins and then employ inflammasome-dependent cytokine intermediates to activate local glial cells. Such a process is likely to unfold at the earliest stages of PD and may help to explain how CNS stressors including environmental toxicants could increase the risk of developing PD.
</p>
