<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent investigations suggest that epigenetic marks may be a new source of biomarkers for PD (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-7-jpd160914-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Epigenetics refers to heritable and acquired alterations in gene activity and expression, without changes in DNA sequence. The epigenome is partially dynamic, such that stable epigenetic changes can occur in fully differentiated, post-mitotic cells in response to environmental signals [
 <xref rid="ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Epigenetic marks, such as biochemical modifications of DNA and of histone proteins, regulate gene expression by controlling DNA accessibility and signaling to the transcriptional machinery [
 <xref rid="ref008" ref-type="bibr">8, 9</xref>]. To date, DNA modifications, which includes DNA methylation and other covalent cytosine modifications, have been the most commonly investigated epigenetic marks for biomarker discovery studies. Historically, DNA modifications were thought to occur exclusively within CpG (cytosine-phosphate-guanine) sites, but it is now established that DNA modification occurs at non-CpG sites as well, particularly in brain neurons [
 <xref rid="ref010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref>]. Other epigenetic marks, such as post-translational modification of histones and noncoding RNAs, frequently act in concert with DNA modifications, affecting chromatin accessibility and structure as well as the recruitment of various transcription factors and protein complexes [
 <xref rid="ref013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref>]. By modifying genomic activities, epigenetic mechanisms impact downstream protein amounts, cellular function, and phenotypic outcome. The epigenome also exhibits considerable heterogeneity between tissues, tissue subregions, and cell types within an organism, which enables the divergent biological roles of tissues and cell types [
 <xref rid="ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In the brain, epigenetic mechanisms are central to neurodevelopment, synaptic transmission, and plasticity [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref>]. Epigenetic abnormalities have been implicated in the mechanism of numerous brain illnesses, including PD [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
