<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epigenetic investigations of PD may yield biomarkers involved in disease pathogenesis. PD has numerous complex, non-Mendelian features that are consistent with the dynamic nature of the epigenome. Such features includes the prevalence of sporadic, non- familial PD cases (∼90%); the low concordance rates (only 11%) between monozygotic twins for sporadic PD [
 <xref rid="ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]; the 1.5-2 times higher risk of PD in males relative to females [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]; diurnal fluctuations in symptom severity (sundowning syndrome) [
 <xref rid="ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]; and the various agricultural and industrial chemicals associated with increased PD risk [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23–25</xref>]. The epigenome is well known to vary between monozygotic twins [
 <xref rid="ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], respond to sex hormones [
 <xref rid="ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], exhibit circadian fluctuations [
 <xref rid="ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and affect neuronal functions following exposure to PD-associated environmental toxins [
 <xref rid="ref029" ref-type="bibr">29–31</xref>]. Moreover, epigenetic mechanisms may contribute to the greatest risk factor for PD: aging. Epigenetic variation accumulates in aging cells, even between genetically-identical individuals, a phenomenon often referred to as “epigenetic drift”. In most tissues, including the brain, there are rapid changes in DNA modifications in the early life period, but these changes gradually slow over the life span [
 <xref rid="ref012" ref-type="bibr">12, 32–34</xref>]. Epigenetic aging affects genomic locations differentially: promoter-associated CpG islands tend to increase in DNA methylation with age, while areas with high DNA methylation (i.e. repetitive elements in intergenic regions) tend to lose methylation with age [
 <xref rid="ref033" ref-type="bibr">33, 35–37</xref>] Epigenomic alterations during aging are mediated not only by external/environmental factors but by genetic factors as well. There are numerous sites in the genome that exhibit allele-specific epigenetic differences, which have been shown to be haplotype-dependent, highly tissue-specific, and prevalent in the brain [
 <xref rid="ref038" ref-type="bibr">38–40</xref>]. Different DNA haplotypes can demonstrate markedly different epigenetic changes with age, which affects phenotypic outcome [
 <xref rid="ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Thus, the epigenome can serve as a convergence point for genetic and environmental risk factors of disease, making it an attractive means of detecting heritable and nonheritable disease risk, disease progression, and treatment efficacy in biomarker applications.
</p>
