<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We propose the following areas of development to enhance the care of patients with PD. These are general future directions and would need to be tailored for implementation in different countries to adapt to country-specific health-care system structures and resources.
 <list list-type="simple" id="list0010">
  <list-item id="listitem0020">
   <label>1)</label>
   <p>Training providers to deliver high-quality PD care. This may be achieved by on-the-ground engagement with medical schools, residency programs, and ancillary health care provider education programs. This can be facilitated by international, regional, national and local neurological and movement disorders societies.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="listitem0025">
   <label>2)</label>
   <p>Improving access to care to healthcare providers trained in PD and other movement disorders. Telemedicine [
    <xref rid="ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] may be used to reach patients that reside in areas that are far from specialist care. Encouraging the use of electronic medical record systems to monitor the delivery of health care would facilitate the delivery of care remotely.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="listitem0030">
   <label>3)</label>
   <p>Creating a network of movement disorders specialists in some MENASA countries and organizing an infrastructure to allow for systematic data collection. This could translate into further collaborations to help gather data on epidemiology, genetic contributors, and environmental risk factors [
    <xref rid="ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="listitem0035">
   <label>4)</label>
   <p>In the long-term, establishing centers of excellence, modeled on those in North America, Europe, and other regions will maximize the delivery of optimal care to PD patients. These centers would lead the way to provide multidisciplinary care, such as medical, surgical, psychiatric/psychological care, rehabilitation services, and home care, as well as establishing social support groups to patients and families caring for patients with parkinsonism.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="listitem0040">
   <label>5)</label>
   <p>Creating networks for patients and caregivers in the region: to educate them more about the disease, provide further support, encourage more socialization, foster learning how to live with the disease, and strengthen the bond between them and their communities.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
