<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Parkinson's disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disease after Alzheimer's disease and is clinically defined as a motor syndrome consisting of levodopa responsive parkinsonism (bradykinesia, tremor, rigidity, and postural instability) and the absence of markers suggestive of other diseases [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is characterized pathologically by loss of dopaminergic (DA) neurons in the 
 <italic>substantia nigra pars compacta</italic> (
 <italic>SNpc</italic>), loss of DA innervation in the striatum, and the presence of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein positive aggregates (Lewy bodies). PD has an age-related prevalence, affecting around 1% of the population over the age of 65, rising to up to 3% among individuals 80 years of age and older [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. While most cases are thought to be sporadic, in about 10% of the patients, a genetic cause can be detected, ascribable to mutations in more than a dozen genes [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The rare monogenic forms clinically mimic the sporadic form and can thus serve as a disease model for this much more common form of PD. Mutations in several PD causing genes, encoding PINK1 (PTEN-induced serine/threonine kinase 1), Parkin, 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein, LRRK2 (leucine-rich repeat kinase 2), DJ1, CHCHD2 (coiled-coil-helix-coiled-coil-helix domain-containing 2), and POLG (mitochondrial DNA polymerase gamma), have been shown to induce mitochondrial dysfunction demonstrating that mitochondrial homeostasis and quality control have a central role in the disease process [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Several aspects of mitochondrial biology have been described as impaired in different PD models, leading to a defect in electron transport chain enzyme activities, ATP depletion, and generation of reactive oxygen species [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Systemic administration of the pesticides rotenone and paraquat as well as the neurotoxicant MPTP (1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine), which are inhibitors of the mitochondrial respiratory chain NADH dehydrogenase (complex I), induces neuropathologic and behavioral changes in rodents similar to human PD [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These data from basic science have been replicated in clinical studies showing a 20–30% decrease of mitochondrial complex I activity in the 
 <italic>SNpc</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], in platelets [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and in lymphocytes of patients with sporadic PD [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], suggesting a systemic inhibition of complex I activity at least in a subset of the common form of PD. Aging is the biggest risk factor for PD, and during aging mitochondrial function declines, with an accumulation of deletions in the mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In line with these data, mtDNA depletion has been observed in nigral neurons from PD patients [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], but the mechanisms by which these mutations affect biochemical pathways leading to mitochondrial dysfunction are not answered yet. However, mtDNA levels or age-dependent increases in mtDNA mutations may be factors that influence penetrance of nuclear mutations known to act via mitochondrial mechanisms. While the phenomenon of reduced penetrance was initially described in the context of family studies, the advent of next-generation sequencing has revealed an unexpectedly large number of putatively pathogenic mutations in overtly healthy individuals, raising the need for a better understanding of factors influencing penetrance. Indeed, for several mutations in autosomal dominant PD genes penetrance is markedly reduced, whereas heterozygous carriers of mutations in recessive PD genes may also manifest disease or subclinical phenotypes of disease. In the following sections, we will review the evidence supporting the hypothesis that gene-environment, nuclear gene-mtDNA, and protein-protein interactions are able to modify the penetrance of genetic forms of PD.
</p>
