<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p>To discover genetic determinants of Parkinson disease (PD) motor subtypes, including tremor dominant (TD) and postural instability/gait difficulty (PIGD) forms.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>In 3,212 PD cases of European ancestry, we performed a genome-wide association study (GWAS) examining 2 complementary outcome traits derived from the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale, including dichotomous motor subtype (TD vs PIGD) or a continuous tremor/PIGD score ratio. Logistic or linear regression models were adjusted for sex, age at onset, disease duration, and 5 ancestry principal components, followed by meta-analysis.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Among 71 established PD risk variants, we detected multiple suggestive associations with PD motor subtype, including 
   <italic>GPNMB</italic> (
   <italic>rs199351</italic>, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>subtype</sub> = 0.01, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>ratio</sub> = 0.03), 
   <italic>SH3GL2</italic> (
   <italic>rs10756907</italic>, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>subtype</sub> = 0.02, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>ratio</sub> = 0.01), 
   <italic>HIP1R</italic> (
   <italic>rs10847864</italic>, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>subtype</sub> = 0.02), 
   <italic>RIT2</italic> (
   <italic>rs12456492</italic>, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>subtype</sub> = 0.02), and 
   <italic>FBRSL1</italic> (
   <italic>rs11610045</italic>, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>subtype</sub> = 0.02). A PD genetic risk score integrating all 71 PD risk variants was also associated with subtype ratio (
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.026, ß = −0.04, 95% confidence interval = −0.07–0). Based on top results of our GWAS, we identify a novel suggestive association at the 
   <italic>STK32B</italic> locus (rs2301857, 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>ratio</sub> = 6.6 × 10
   <sup>−7</sup>), which harbors an independent risk allele for essential tremor.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Multiple PD risk alleles may also modify clinical manifestations to influence PD motor subtype. The discovery of a novel variant at 
   <italic>STK32B</italic> suggests a possible overlap between genetic risk for essential tremor and tremor-dominant PD.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
