<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Why some brain disorders with a strong genetic component have a late developmental onset is unknown. The prevailing hypothesis for schizophrenia proposes that an early (fetal) insult or mutation renders the brain vulnerable to a secondary environmental insult that occurs in young adults, which then triggers the onset of psychosis (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bayer et al., 1999</xref>). However, the finding that the age of onset for schizophrenia has a heritability estimated at 33% (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Hare et al., 2010</xref>), suggests that the timing may have a genetic basis. In recent years, there has been major progress in understanding the genetic basis of schizophrenia with the identification of many mutations and variants contributing to disease susceptibility. It is widely accepted that many mutations directly impact on synapse proteins, particularly those involved with postsynaptic signalling mechanisms in excitatory synapses (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Kirov et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Pocklington et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Fromer et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Fernández et al., 2009a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2017</xref>). The postsynaptic proteome of excitatory synapses is physically organised into multiprotein complexes of which the supercomplexes assembled by PSD95 (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Husi et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Frank et al., 2016a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Frank and Grant, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Frank et al., 2017</xref>) play a major role in regulating cognitive functions (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Migaud et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Nithianantharajah et al., 2013</xref>) and are disrupted by schizophrenia mutations (
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Pocklington et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Fromer et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Fernández et al., 2009a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Kirov et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Purcell et al., 2014</xref>). Together these observations suggest there may be genetic mechanisms that account for the convergence between the many schizophrenia susceptibility genes, the postsynaptic proteome and the young adult brain.
</p>
