<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">The emerging evidence that αS accumulation in LBs may not solely be fibrillar as traditionally assumed has several important implications. First, the popular “PFF” model of αS fibrillization and proteotoxicity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>
 </sup> may have to be rethought and complemented with models of intracellular membrane-mediated αS aggregation such as the αS “3K” model that was developed in cultured cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup> and then shown in transgenic mice to cause PD-like phenotypes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>
 </sup> Second, positron emission topography tracers for synucleinopathies may have to be designed differently than attempted thus far, taking into account the protein’s excess on cellular membranes in a yet undefined conformation. Third, drugs that alter lipid and FA homeostasis in addition to SCD inhibitors may become promising targets.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> Fourth, the common assumption that proteinopathy means amyloid aggregation may have to be modified in the case of αS in PD and DLB. From these and other considerations, a new model is emerging in which αS “misfolding” in the cell can occur on several levels. Just an excess amount of the wt αS monomer that normally interacts with vesicles, i.e., which forms physiological amphipathic helices, may already have to be considered a type of “misfolding”. Thus, excess membrane-associated αS may be cytotoxic and disease relevant in the absence of actual β-sheet-rich fibrillar aggregation. A progression to β-sheet-rich fibrillar aggregates may confer further detriment, but it might also be temporarily beneficial by sequestering αS monomers away from membrane vesicles, thereby mitigating negative effects on vesicle trafficking. The recently published αS “3K” mouse model that exhibits a pronounced neurodegenerative and movement disorder phenotype indeed developed vesicle-rich αS + aggregation in young animals, whereas older animals seemed to display occasional “classical” filament-rich amyloid aggregates.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>
 </sup> This finding could indicate that vesicle clustering is potentially an early event in LB formation, whereas fibrillar aggregates are characteristic of more mature inclusions. Related to these considerations may be the question of the nature of the so-called “pale bodies” of αS aggregation that can be observed in PD patient brains and that have been discussed to potentially be a stage in the formation of LBs (e.g., see ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>
 </sup>).
</p>
