<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Total RNA from ClonTech was converted to cDNA using 1 μg of RNA and High Capacity RNA-to-cDNA kit (Cat N. #4387406, Applied Biosystems, Europe). PCR was performed using Herculase II Fusion DNA Polymerase (Cat N. #600675, Agilent, Europe) on a Veriti Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems) in the presence of 3% DMSO with the following optimized protocol: 95 °C for 2 min, followed by 35 cycles of amplification (95 °C for 20 s, 52 °C for 20 s and 72 °C for 30 s) and extension at 72 °C for 3 min. 
 <italic>SORL1-38B</italic> was amplified using primers in exon 35 and 38b. Primer sequences were SORL1-Ex35-fw: 5′-GGCACACAACACCAATGACT, and SORL1-Ex38B-rev; 5′-TGCTCTTCCAACATCCCTTCT. Water was used as negative control. RT-PCR for the analysis of splicing events downstream of E38b was performed using Titanium One-Step RT-PCR Kit (Cat N. 639504, ClonTech) on total RNA from human cerebellum (Cat N. 636535, ClonTech) with primers located in exons 38b and 40. Primer were SORL1-Ex38b-fw: 5′-TGACCACACATACCAAGAAGGG and SORL1-Ex40-rev: 5′-TGCTTCCTCGGAAGTTCAAAGT. The refined analysis of transcript levels across tissue was performed using qPCR on the same samples and protocol for cDNA synthesis. Each cDNA was tested with a custom Taqman probe for detection of 
 <italic>SORL1-38b</italic> (SORLA_EX_37-38B, AssayID AJBJXYH, Cat N. 4441114) (Applied Biosystems), and pre-designed probes for 
 <italic>SORL1 exon 3–4</italic> (Hs00268342_m1). Three household genes were analysed: 
 <italic>HPRT1</italic> (Hs02800695_m1), 
 <italic>TFRC</italic> (Hs00951083_m1), and 
 <italic>TXNL1</italic> (Hs00355488_m1). Singleplex PCR was performed in 96-well plates LightCycler 480 System (Roche) with the following conditions: 95 °C for 10 s, 45 cycles of amplification (95 °C for 10 s, 60 °C for 30 s, 72 °C for 1 s), and 72 °C for 1 s. The efficiency and dynamic range for each qPCR assay was established using a serial dilution, and confirmed to be above 92% for all assays.
</p>
