<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Identification and characterization of PD subtypes has received increased attention in recent years, with the goal of predicting progression, stratifying patients based on risk of nonmotor complications (e.g., dementia), and elucidating mechanisms of disease heterogeneity.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">–</xref>
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
  <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>
 </sup> Recent studies strongly suggest that genetic factors can influence the presence and severity of many varied PD manifestations and therefore likely influence disease subtypes.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 </sup> We have performed a GWAS for PD motor subtype. Our results highlight some evidence for 5 established PD risk alleles as potential modifiers of motor subtype, and we further found that a PD GRS including 71 risk variants was associated with subtype ratio. One strength of our analysis was consideration of 2 complementary PD motor subtype outcomes. The TD/PIGD score ratio trait offers a continuous outcome and has the advantage of a larger sample size because subjects with indeterminate subtype can be considered. On the other hand, by including subjects with a mixed phenotype, it is also possible that the subtype ratio may dilute power to detect the effects of certain variants. In such cases, the dichotomous subtype outcome permits greater contrast between groups of subjects manifesting the TD or PIGD phenotype. In a prior, candidate-based analysis of 10 PD risk alleles in 810 PD cases, a variant at the 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> locus (
 <italic>rs356182</italic>) was discovered to be associated (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.004, β = 0.7) with a similar TD/PIGD score ratio outcome.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> Although we did not replicate that association in our larger sample (n = 3,212, 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.18, β = 0.03), this may relate to modest differences in the derivation of the subtype score ratio, and additional replication analyses should be undertaken in the future.
</p>
