<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the TD and PIGD categories are the earliest and mostly widely used subtype classification,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> there are also several notable limitations. The cutoffs used for differentiating the TD or PIGD subtypes are somewhat arbitrary and without underlying biological or clinical rationale.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
 </sup> In addition, treatment with dopaminergic medication is known to alter the motor UPDRS examination—especially gait scores—which may in turn influence subtype classification.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
  <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>
 </sup> Information on medication status and other factors (e.g., dementia, lifestyle, and environmental exposures) was not universally available for consideration as potential confounders or genetic modifiers in this analysis. Lastly, several recent studies have suggested that PD motor subtypes may shift from TD to PIGD subtype along with disease progression,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">–</xref>
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> raising questions about the stability of these phenotypes over time. This relation between disease duration and subtype proportions was recapitulated among the cohorts included in this study (table e-1, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/NXG/A373" specific-use="external-ds" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">links.lww.com/NXG/A373</ext-link>). Such observations suggest that motor subtypes may represent a transient state rather than a static trait.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>
 </sup> To control for potential shifts in subtype phenotypes, our analyses were adjusted for both onset age and estimated disease duration. In addition, we speculate that even if PD motor subtypes are dynamic, either completely or in part, they may nevertheless serve as a useful proxy for disease progression, which is likely itself under genetic influence.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
  <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
  <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
  <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup> In sum, regardless of evolving interpretations for PD subtypes, we argue that analyses of such phenotypes may identify genetic variants that meaningfully modify the PD clinical course, whether motor manifestations, rate of progression, medication response, or some combination. Future genetic analyses of PD subtypes will also benefit from alternative outcome traits that are independent of medication status and disease duration.
</p>
