<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The QPN has three main research axes: 1) Clinical and Treatment Research, 2) Non-Motor Symptoms, and 3) Molecular and Cellular Biology. Since its creation in June 2013, the QPN has supported more than 60 research projects involving participants from the registry, leading to more than 30 peer-reviewed publications to date. QPN-facilitated research projects are initiated when an investigator requests to use the registry, to access existing data or to enroll QPN patients for their study and collect additional data or samples for their study. The QPN selects patients from the registry for participation in the study based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria provided by the investigator. If the investigator approves inclusion of the participant in their study, they may contact the participant. An initial contact form, indicating whether or not the participant will be included in the study, is submitted by the investigator to the QPN and this information is documented by the QPN for each participant. Participants who are not included in the study remain eligible to be selected for other studies. Participants may be involved in several studies simultaneously; however, the QPN ensures that participants already taking part in a study are not selected for another study deemed incompatible with the first. In this way, the registry provides access to patients for investigators conducting research in PD. As the QPN Participant Registry continues to grow, the QPN is consolidating data collected through the questionnaire, patient medical records, and QPN-facilitated research studies, such as NeurO C-BIGR, in a centralized, open-access database (LORIS [Longitudinal Online Research and Imaging System]) [
 <xref rid="ref026" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref>]. All epidemiological, clinical, neuroimaging, neuropsychological, and biological data will then be made publicly accessible to promote data sharing throughout the PD research community, ultimately leading to new research projects and analyses. Applications for data and for new studies can be made through the QPN website (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rpq-qpn.ca/en/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rpq-qpn.ca/en/</ext-link>).
</p>
