<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All patients (
 <italic>n</italic> = 184, 60.9% male, mean age at onset 68.1 years ± 9.2 SD) and normal controls (
 <italic>n</italic> = 178, 51.4% male, mean age at inclusion 66.7 years ± 9.6 SD) participate in the ongoing Norwegian ParkWest study [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. ParkWest is a large population-based multicenter study of newly diagnosed drug-naïve PD patients designed to determine the incidence, neurobiology, and prognosis of PD. Multiple recruitment strategies were employed to identify all patients with incident PD in four counties in Southwestern Norway during a 22-month period between the 1st of November 2004 and the 31st of August 2006 [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Patients underwent comprehensive and standardized clinical examinations before drug treatment was initiated, including rating of disease severity by Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS, baseline score 23.6 ± 11.2 SD) and Hoehn and Yahr staging (baseline score 1.9 ± 0.6 SD). Diagnosis of dementia was made according to the established criteria [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and by two study neurologists, as previously described [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. PD patients are currently under continued follow-up, and only those whose diagnosis remained unchanged until their latest clinical visit, on average 4.6 (1.1 SD) years after first presentation, were considered eligible for this study to maximize diagnostic accuracy [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. During the same time period, we also recruited normal control subjects in the same geographical area. Controls being first- or second-degree relatives of patients were disregarded for single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) genotype analysis (
 <italic>n</italic> = 10). All participants signed written-informed consent. The Regional Committee for Research Ethics of the University of Bergen, Norway, approved the study.
</p>
