<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent advances in biomaterials, 3D tissue engineering and microscale technologies have led to the emergence of “organs-on-a-chip” (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-9-jpd181515-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> microphysiological system, different types of organoids are co-cultured in a continuous liquid flow system to mimic the physiology of the body. This technology potentially represents a more physiological platform for drug discovery and toxicity testing, because it mimics cell-cell and cell-matrix interactions, and provides appropriate chemical and mechanical forces, such as shear stress, and electrical cues through microelectrodes arrays [
 <xref rid="ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Moreover, the development of incorporated biosensors can allow monitoring of biomarkers, chemokines and analytes, to better understand disease mechanisms. A number of companies and laboratories have developed connected organs with multiple fluid flow circuits operated by pumps, thus incorporating blood and excretory flow circuit with organoids, to carry out brain neurosphere analyses such as neurotoxicity screening, high content imaging, kinetic and electrophysiological assays [
 <xref rid="ref140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>] (cf also Mimetas
 <sup>®</sup>, DRAPER
 <sup>®</sup>, StemoniX
 <sup>®</sup> websites). Brain-on-a-chip models have been developed to model neurodegenerative disorders. So far, only neurospheres, but not complex brain organoids, have been incorporated on chips to model AD [
 <xref rid="ref140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>] or PD [
 <xref rid="ref141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. Interestingly, for the AD model, fluid flow mimicked the cerebrospinal fluid flow, which has a major role in cell communication and metabolism. This flow promoted differentiation of neurons, decreased cell death, and promoted the response of neurons to amyloid-beta protein addition [
 <xref rid="ref140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>].
</p>
