<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the major advantages to combining iPSC-derived tissue and microfluidic chips is the possibility of deriving multiple organs from the same donor or patient. As mentioned above, connection of gut and brain organoids from a PD patient would be an interesting chip to develop, to investigate the impact of microbiota on the development of pathological markers, such as 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein, which is suspected to spread from the enteric nervous system to the brain via the vagus nerve [
 <xref rid="ref142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. “Gut-on-a chip” systems have already been developed to test the inflammatory impact of microbial infection on intestinal epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="ref143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Future technologies may connect, on a single chip, gut-organoids and brain-organoids derived from iPSCs [
 <xref rid="ref120" ref-type="bibr">120, 144–147</xref>]. Such microphysiological systems, that mimic biologically relevant human conditions, could help model diseases and provide a better understanding of the pathological mechanisms at play. Moreover, adding a blood brain barrier to envelop the neural network system is a major potential breakthrough for the 3D neural network model [
 <xref rid="ref148" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. Recently, one group generated human vascularized brain organoids from a patient, by co-culturing his iPSC-derived endothelial cells with the brain organoids [
 <xref rid="ref149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. This promising study demonstrated the feasibility of organoid vascularization. So far, neuronal organoids lack vascularization, leading to poor diffusion of oxygen and nutrients to the center of the tissue, which can often become necrotic with age [
 <xref rid="ref138" ref-type="bibr">138, 150, 151</xref>]. This is one of the major limitations of organoid growth and one explanation for the heterogeneity observed within the tissue. Concurrently, another group showed vascularization of a human brain organoid transplanted in an adult mouse brain [
 <xref rid="ref152" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>], suggesting a connectivity between the grafted organoid and the host. Recently, Berger and others developed millifluidic cultures to improve human midbrain organoid vitality and differentiation in bioreactors. They observed a decrease in the necrotic core size with continuous medium flow during culture, rather than shaking culture [
 <xref rid="ref153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. These pioneering studies present immense promise for truly generating more relevant models of PD through organoids.
</p>
