<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>P-glycoprotein (P-gp) is an efflux transporter encoded by the
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> (also known as
 <italic> MDR1</italic>) gene that protects the brain against neurotoxicants [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Certain
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> genetic variants, known to alter the function of this transporter, have been suggested to influence the risk to develop PD in conjunction with exposure to toxicants [
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>–
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. A case-control study, in 599 European PD patients and controls, detected no relevant association between three
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> variants and PD, while it found that the distribution of c.3435C&gt;T differed significantly between PD patients exposed to pesticides compared to those nonexposed (OR = 4.74, 95% CI [1.01–22.31]) [
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Another case-control study, among 207 PD cases and 482 matched controls, addressed the association between PD and 2 polymorphisms in
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> (c.2677G&gt;[A/T], c.3435C&gt;T), as well as the interaction between
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> and pesticides. Participants were classified as never users, user for gardening, and professional users of pesticides. This study found that
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> polymorphisms were not associated with PD. Among PD cases only, an association between carrying 2 variant c.2677G&gt;[A,T] alleles and organochlorine exposure was found (OR = 5.4, 95% CI [1.1–27.5]) [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. More recently, another study lent support to previous findings. In a population-based case-control study, including 350 cases and 724 controls, homozygote carriers of
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> c.2677G&gt;[A/T] or/and c.3435C&gt;T risk alleles, exposed specifically to organophosphorus pesticides, had from 2 to 3.7 times higher risk to develop PD versus noncarriers (OR = 2.1, 95% CI [1.3–3.2] for homozygotes of 1 risk allele; OR = 3.7, 95% CI [2.0−7.0] for homozygotes of both risk alleles) [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. In contrast to all these reports mainly relating to participants of European ancestry, a Japanese hospital-based case-control study found no interaction between pesticide exposure and
 <italic> ABCB1</italic> rs1045642 [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Reason for this inconsistency could be that, unlike previous cited studies, authors examined interactions for rs1045642 using a dominant genetic model or might be explained by ethnic differences.
</p>
