<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Like all neurodegenerative diseases, PD remains a challenge for drug discovery. There are limited treatments and no cures available, despite huge investments. PD patients exhibit clinical, pathological and genetic heterogeneity that, combined with lack of efficacy or toxic side effects of drugs, may explain the failures of drug trials [
 <xref rid="ref156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. New tools are needed to better predict and target future therapies, especially at presymptomatic stages. The technologies described in this review represent promising platforms for human research. Worldwide, institutions and universities are creating biobanks, including open access biobanks [
 <xref rid="ref157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>], that could allow researchers to more readily generate such tools, to be used for finding personalized drug candidates or therapies to test in clinical trials [
 <xref rid="ref158" ref-type="bibr">158, 159</xref>]. However, since the goal of models is to reproduce the complexity of the human body, they need to be highly elaborate. As a consequence, there are many challenges to face. First, the production of iPSCs, via fibroblast or blood cell reprogramming, induces a loss of epigenetic memory [
 <xref rid="ref160" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. 2D or 3D cultures derived from iPSCs recapitulate fetal gene expression profiles and thus represent a hurdle for modeling late-onset disorders. Inducing or accelerating the aging process in iPSC-derived cultures, to improve late-onset age-related disease features, is a critical point to consider and improve in existing iPSC models for AD and PD. So far, one group has reported induction of aging in an iPSCs model using progerin [
 <xref rid="ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. However, even in such aged cells, the original potential epigenetics disease markers carried by the donor cannot be recovered, representing a limitation of this model. Secondly, it is important to keep in mind that genetic factors contribute to approximately 10% of PD cases, meaning that environmental factors have a major impact on the development of pathology. Recently, a group investigated the interaction between genome and environment and demonstrated an impact of local environment on the transcriptome and clinical endophenotypes, stronger than genetic ancestry. They demonstrated that local air pollution directly affected gene expression, and pathways affecting cardio-metabolic and respiratory traits, when controlling for genetic ancestry [
 <xref rid="ref161" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Thus, it is crucial to consider and include environmental contributors and complex polygenic inheritance in existing genetic iPSC models.
</p>
