<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>GBA</italic>-PD has long been associated with a younger onset of PD and a more malignant disease course, with increased dementia risk and mortality,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
  <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">–</xref>
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 </sup> but studies evaluating the progression of motor impairment using the UPDRS, particularly in early PD, have been surprisingly few and inconsistent. Only 2 other studies have previously shown an association of 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants and motor impairment measured by the UPDRS, and both of these did so only in patients with more advanced disease. The first followed 13 patients with PD (average disease duration 7.5 years) and the 2 most common pathogenic 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations (N370S or L444P) and 26 matched noncarriers, and showed more rapid motor progression in patients with 
 <italic>GBA</italic>-PD.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 </sup> Subsequently, a large multicenter study of 733 patients (average disease duration 8.6 years) showed that carriers of a 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variant experienced a larger increase in UPDRS motor score compared to noncarriers.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Another study looked at the association of 2 individual 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants (N370S or K26R/rs75548401) selected from the PDgene database and progression of UPDRS motor score. No significant association was shown between either variant and the change in UPDRS motor score measured in participants from the Washington University cohort and Parkinson's Progression Markers Initiative (PPMI) cohorts using UPDRS scores in the “on” or “off” state.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> Of note, the low observed minor allele frequency of each variant (N370S 0.007 and K26R 0.012) combined with moderate sample size and length of follow-up of the cohorts may account for the lack of significant associations. The analysis of individual 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants may require larger collaborations; indeed the largest genome-wide association study of PD clinical phenotypes to date included 12 cohorts (including PPMI) and whereas no significant associations were identified with UPDRS motor scores, 
 <italic>GBA</italic> T369M was shown to be associated with the faster development of H&amp;Y stage 3.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> Alternatively, a more comprehensive assessment of 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants using exome sequencing, as done in the present study, could determine whether 
 <italic>GBA</italic> carrier status affects motor impairment in these cohorts.
</p>
