<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A major challenge for drug development in neurodegenerative diseases is that adequately powered trials typically require several hundred participants and long durations. The expected progression of the trial's primary outcome in genetic subgroups can be used to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of clinical trials. The utility of this model in 
 <italic>GBA</italic>-PD was assessed by comparing simulated randomized placebo-controlled trial designs to recruit all newly diagnosed patients with PD (all-comers) or only those predicted to be at risk of a faster motor decline, by limiting trial selection to carriers of a 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variant. We show that a trial limited to 
 <italic>GBA</italic> carriers could recruit up to 65% fewer participants than a traditional all-comer design, which could feasibly translate into considerable savings in costs. Our data are in line with and extend on previous estimations targeting only patients with a 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutation (such as L444P) for a hypothetical trial with MMSE as the primary outcome.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 </sup> Notably, this hypothetical trial was found to reduce trial size by as much as 25-fold compared to a trial of patients with PD without a 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 </sup> However, neuropathic 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations are rare in the general PD population (1.4% in our study), whereas we considered all types of 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variant and thus substantially increased the number of eligible trial participants. In light of this, the threefold reduction in trial size shown here is more realistic in a population-based setting. The first example of a trial studying ambroxol in genetically defined patients with PD was recently published,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 </sup> and although this trial was not powered to assess the clinical efficacy of the drug, it demonstrates the potential of using genetic information to balance or build a trial.
</p>
