<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Parkinson’s disease (PD) is a devastating neurodegenerative disorder, affecting more than 1% of the population over 65 years of age. It is characterized by debilitating motor symptoms, including bradykinesia, tremors and muscle rigidity, as well as non-motor symptoms that include intestinal dysfunction, depression, cognitive decline and sleep disturbances [
 <xref rid="ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While the majority of PD cases are idiopathic, about 10% have been linked to genetic mutations with Mendelian inheritance within families. Specifically, such mutations have been found to occur in genes including 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein (SNCA), Leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2), glucocerebrosidase (GBA), Parkin (PARK2 gene) and PTEN-induced putative kinase (PINK1). Independent of familial history, Gene wide association studies (GWAS) have also unravelled several gene variants associated with an increased risk of PD development [
 <xref rid="ref002" ref-type="bibr">2–4</xref>]. These genetic data have helped scientists create models explaining the pathogenic causes of this disorder. Classical hallmarks of PD are the selective loss of dopaminergic (DA) neurons in the substantia nigra pars compacta, accompanied by the presence of inclusions within neurons called “Lewy bodies”. These inclusions are primarily comprised of the 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein protein [
 <xref rid="ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], which forms cellular fibrillar aggregates within the cells that may be able to spread from cell to cell in a prion-like manner [
 <xref rid="ref006" ref-type="bibr">6–8</xref>]. After two decades of research on PD genes, several cellular pathways have been implicated in PD pathogenesis, including mitochondrial dysfunction [
 <xref rid="ref009" ref-type="bibr">9–11</xref>], perturbed electrical activity of neurons [
 <xref rid="ref012" ref-type="bibr">12, 13</xref>], and dysregulated protein homeostasis due to autophagy, lysosomal and proteasomal defects [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14, 15</xref>]. However, to date, there are no therapies to effectively halt the progression of the disease, and treatment of PD is limited to symptom management. It is therefore of utmost importance to refine the models we use in fundamental research, to better understand the pathophysiology of PD for developing effective therapeutic strategies. Here we present existing PD models, and discuss the future of PD modelling by outlining the next generation of more relevant models of PD pathophysiology, made possible through the advent of human induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) technology and genome editing. We will also discuss the potential of using iPSCs in drug discovery assays.
</p>
