<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Parkinson’s disease (PD) is a neurodegenerative disorder characterized by motor and non-motor symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup> So far, levodopa still stands as the most effective symptomatic treatment for PD.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> However, long-term dopamine repletion treatment may lead to motor fluctuations, such as wearing-off and dyskinesias.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> Several factors participate in the development of motor fluctuations, including loss of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra, changes in pre and post-synaptic striatal activity with chronic pulsatile stimulation of dopamine receptors,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> and the daily dosage of levodopa.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> Motor fluctuations highly impact on the quality of life of people with PD, representing a major criteria for eligibility to advanced treatments.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> Observational studies have shown that more than 50% of PD patients treated with levodopa for more than 5 years develop levodopa-induced dyskinesia (LID).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup> Several risk factors for LID have been proposed, including levodopa dosage,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup> treatment duration,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup> female gender
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> and low body weight.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> Other factors have been investigated as predisposing to LID, including neuroimaging findings, with conflicting results.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup> It is worth noticing that the available studies are poorly comparable, given the different methodological approaches and follow-up duration, with patients being rarely followed up ever since de novo stage. The Parkinson’s Progression Markers Initiative (PPMI) is a large-scale international prospective observational study, started in 2010, designed to identify markers of disease progression in de novo PD patients. Clinical, neuroimaging and CSF/blood biomarkers are collected yearly. We wanted to define factors predictive of LID development already in de novo stage of PD.
</p>
