<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>About 10% of all PD patients suffer from a monogenic form where autosomal dominant or recessive mutations in single genes are causative. Autosomal dominant PD is mostly represented by mutations in 
 <italic>SNCA</italic>, coding for 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein, and 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> and recessive PD by mutations in 
 <italic>PINK1</italic> and 
 <italic>Parkin</italic>. Many of these mutations, particularly in the autosomal dominant forms, are only imperfectly penetrant or show a delay in the age at onset. Notably, heterozygous mutations in 
 <italic>Parkin</italic> and 
 <italic>PINK1</italic> are relatively frequent (about 8% of all PD patients screened for 
 <italic>Parkin</italic> mutations [
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]) and may predispose to PD or subclinical phenotypes with highly reduced penetrance [
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>], although this remains controversial [
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. This reminds however mutations in the 
 <italic>GBA</italic> gene (encoding the lysosomal enzyme glucocerebrosidase), which in a homozygous fashion, are responsible for the lysosomal storage disorder Gaucher's disease, while heterozygous mutations in this gene have been established as well-validated risk factors for PD [
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. The vast majority of PD patients are thought to be sporadic with a genetically complex form. In fact, more than 40 loci have been identified that are able to increase PD risk with however only modest to moderate effect size estimates (ORs ranging from 1.1 to 1) [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Given the high rate of reduced penetrance in PD, finding factors responsible for an incomplete or delayed disease onset and understanding the underlying mechanisms is important as they might be able to protect from developing the disease or delay the disease onset. We are highlighting environmental and genetic modifiers as well as mtDNA alterations and protein-protein interactions as possible factors underlying nonpenetrant or highly reduced penetrant forms of PD (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). These modifiers are all involved in the maintenance of mitochondrial function and may result in neuroprotection despite the presence of mutations causing PD in many instances. Validation of such modifiers would have high translational potential for the identification of early diagnosis and novel therapeutic options to halt the disease progression.
</p>
