<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most likely barrier to embracing a molecular view of PD follows directly from the points made previously: we may end up concluding that PD is not one disease, but many, and this will be difficult to accept. To some extent, fragmentation of the relatively monolithic view of what constitutes PD is already happening. As mentioned previously, trials of 
 <italic>GBA</italic> substrate reduction are not enrolling PD patients who lack 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations for the simple reason that PD patients who have 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations are most likely to benefit from targeting this pathway. Other glimpses of this fragmentation are also apparent to the careful observer: the division between tremor-predominant PD and non-tremor-predominant PD can be found as early as Gowers’ statement in the 1880 s that “In the majority of cases (two-thirds) the tremor precedes the weakness; occasionally this relation is reversed,” which is remarkably similar to the ratio found by Jankovic in 800 patients (441:233) from the DATATOP cohort in 1990 [
 <xref rid="ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. What was lacking was a molecular “tag” for these subtypes, leading to debate in the literature of the significance of the tremor-predominant subtype if individuals might change their clinical presentation over time [
 <xref rid="ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Indeed, this debate motivated our 2016 report that a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) near 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> defines a subtype of PD characterized by clinical tremor-predominance, decreased cerebellar 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> RNA expression, and slower motor progression [
 <xref rid="ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Importantly, while the “tremor-predominant” clinical state may be demonstrably transient, a SNP genotype is not. Thus, while our report that the rs356182 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> SNP characterizes a clinically important subtype of PD may be disproved over time, the SNP status of an individual patient, unlike his or her tremor-predominant state, is not similarly debatable.
</p>
