<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another key barrier is the lack of well-validated biomarkers for the PD-related pathologies that constitute our current “definitions” of disease. CSF total tau, phospho-tau and A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>42</sub> (preferably in a ratio with the less aggregation-prone A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>40</sub> that may be used to normalize for inter-individual differences in A
 <italic>β</italic> production and clearance) may be used to exclude individuals with AD-related pathologies, although this is certainly complicated by the co-occurrence of AD-related pathologies in the vast majority of PD patients at autopsy [
 <xref rid="ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. CSF or serum/plasma neurofilament light concentrations may be used to differentiate PD from atypical parkinsonian disorders, as neurofilament light levels are less elevated in PD [
 <xref rid="ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, when it comes to positive identification of Lewy body pathology, CSF 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein concentration is not specific; currently available tests do not differentiate normal from pathological (inclusion-specific or -enriched) forms of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein and show only minor changes in PD [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Novel tests for oligomeric or phosphorylated forms of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein show promising results but are far from validated [
 <xref rid="ref015" ref-type="bibr">15, 16</xref>]. The most promising fluid-based biomarker assay for Lewy body pathology at present detects the amplified biochemical signal of 
 <italic>α</italic>-synuclein seeds that may be Lewy body-derived in the CSF from PD patients but not in healthy controls [
 <xref rid="ref017" ref-type="bibr">17, 18</xref>]. In regards to positron emission tomography, intense research is ongoing to identify Lewy body-specific ligands but there is no available method yet. Our hope, however, is that the genetic and biochemical characterization of patient-derived materials, using both targeted and unbiased approaches [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], will make it possible to subgroup clinical PD patients regarding prognosis, risk of various co-morbidities, and extent and intensity of pathological processes. We note, additionally, that while genetic markers such as 
 <italic>GBA</italic> and 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation status are most mature at this point, biochemical biomarkers are important to develop as well, since they may reflect both genetic and environmental influences. Patient-derived molecular signatures—reflecting both genetic and environmental influences— should be useful when developing and evaluating novel drug candidates.
</p>
