<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Using human brain cytosol from unspecified source and characterization, early studies reported that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn directly interacts with the microtubule binding region of tau thereby modulating the phosphorylation state of tau proteins at least at two serine residues (S262 and S356), suggesting a possibility of direct physical interaction between 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and tau [
 <xref rid="ref198" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. 
 <italic>In situ</italic>, LBs found in PD and DLB cases also contain hyperphosphorylated tau [
 <xref rid="ref199" ref-type="bibr">199, 200</xref>]. A few years later, transgenic TgA53T mice overexpressing mutant human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>A53T</sup> (M83 line) were shown to display abundant tau pathology as threads, grains, spheroids and pre-tangles in several brain regions [
 <xref rid="ref201" ref-type="bibr">201, 202</xref>], whereas transgenic mice overexpressing human wildtype 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> (unspecified line from PDGF-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn mice [
 <xref rid="ref203" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>]) develop spontaneous pathological tau changes including tau hyperphosphorylation and tau misfolding [
 <xref rid="ref189" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>]. Profound neuronal tau inclusions resembling NFTs were also found in transgenic mice overexpressing another human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn mutation, E46K [
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Despite the demonstration that mutant 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>E46K</sup> is less efficient than 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> at promoting tau inclusions in cultured QBI293 cells, it is worth noting that TgE46K mice displayed a greater number of tau inclusions compared to TgA53T mice [
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], suggesting the marked effects of the environment, species and cell type differences on potential molecular interactions between 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and tau. To date, the reason for the accumulation of hyperphosphorylated tau inclusions in TgE46K mice remains unclear and may warrant additional work, specifically with respect to 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and tau oligomers. Beyond the detection of co-occurring aggregates of tau and 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in neurons from M83 TgA53T mice, this co-aggregation was also exacerbated in oligodendrocytes from a bigenic CNP-TauP301L/
 <italic>α</italic>SynWT mouse model overexpressing mutant P301L tau and human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> driven by an oligodendrocyte-specific promoter (2
 <sup>′</sup>,3
 <sup>′</sup>-cyclic nucleotide 3
 <sup>′</sup>-phosphodiesterase or CNP) [
 <xref rid="ref201" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>]. In these cells, inclusions were positive to Thioflavin S [
 <xref rid="ref201" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>], denoting advanced fibrillization.
</p>
