<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, these seminal studies focused on fibril formation as opposed to oligomerization per se. Consequently, the functional role of oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn/tau cross-talks 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> was investigated by several groups. In recent studies, the co-occurrence of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and tau in their toxic oligomeric forms was observed in postmortem brain tissues of PD and DLB patients [
 <xref rid="ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. In this study, Sengupta and colleagues demonstrated a co-immunoprecipitation of o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn with tau oligomers (o-Tau) coupled with a cytoplasmic colocalization of these species in brain tissue from individuals with PD [
 <xref rid="ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Recognizing that mixed protein pathologies of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and tau are observed in PD whereas tau pathology alone is found without any documented 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn pathology in progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP), Castillo-Carranza and coworkers investigated the toxicity of hybrid o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn/o-Tau assemblies by injecting either complexes of oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and tau hybrid species derived from PD brain tissues or PSP-derived o-Tau alone in human tau transgenic Htau animals overexpressing human tau isoforms in a murine tau background [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Hybrid o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn/o-Tau complexes accelerated endogenous tau aggregation along with memory deficits in Htau animals compared to o-Tau [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Importantly, the functional interaction of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn/tau cross-talks 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> was further investigated by Gerson and coworkers using passive immunotherapy with the tau oligomer-specific monoclonal antibody (TOMA) in M83 TgA53T mice [
 <xref rid="ref204" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>]. Compared to mice injected with control immunoglobulins, TgA53T mice treated with TOMA displayed reduced synaptic loss, premature deaths and cognitive and motor deficits [
 <xref rid="ref204" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>]. Importantly, TOMA-mediated lowering of tau oligomers in TgA53T mice was accompanied by a marked reduction in LB-like pathology and by an increase in o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn detected by F8H7 and Syn33 antibodies. Based on the properties of TOMA antibodies, which preferentially detect off-pathway o-Tau [
 <xref rid="ref205" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>], and based on those for F8H7 and Syn33, which preferentially bind off-pathway o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn [
 <xref rid="ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>], these findings highlight complex molecular interactions between o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and o-Tau, which are not fully clear at this time.
</p>
