<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neurotherapeutics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neurotherapeutics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neurotherapeutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1933-7213</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-7479</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7483040</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32914362</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">920</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13311-020-00920-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emerging Targeted Therapeutics for Genetic Subtypes of Parkinsonism</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>Susanne A.</given-names></name><address><email>susanne.schneider@med.uni-muenchen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hizli</surname><given-names>Baccara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Alcalay</surname><given-names>Roy N.</given-names></name><address><email>rna2104@cumc.columbia.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5252.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 973X</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurology, </institution><institution>Ludwig-Maximilians-University of M&#x000fc;nchen, </institution></institution-wrap>Marchioninistr. 15, 81377 Munich, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.21729.3f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000419368729</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurology, </institution><institution>Columbia University Irving Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, NY USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1378</fpage><lpage>1392</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">In recent years, a precision medicine approach, which customizes medical treatments based on patients&#x02019; individual profiles and incorporates variability in genes, the environment, and lifestyle, has transformed medical care in numerous medical fields, most notably oncology. Applying a similar approach to Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD) may promote the development of disease-modifying agents that could help slow progression or possibly even avert disease development in a subset of at-risk individuals. The urgent need for such trials partially stems from the negative results of clinical trials where interventions treat all PD patients as a single homogenous group. Here, we review the current obstacles towards the development of precision interventions in PD. We also review and discuss the clinical trials that target genetic forms of PD, i.e., <italic>GBA</italic>-associated and <italic>LRRK2</italic>-associated PD.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s13311-020-00920-8) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Key Words</title><kwd>Genetic Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</kwd><kwd>SNCA</kwd><kwd>GBA</kwd><kwd>LRRK2</kwd><kwd>kinase inhibitor</kwd><kwd>small molecule compounds</kwd><kwd>Venglustat</kwd><kwd>ambroxol</kwd><kwd>clinical trial</kwd><kwd>TORC1 inhibitor</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100009401</institution-id><institution>Medizinischen Fakult&#x000e4;t, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000864</institution-id><institution>Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson's Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Alcalay</surname><given-names>Roy N.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100001790</institution-id><institution>Ara Parseghian Medical Research Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100007453</institution-id><institution>Stiftung VERUM</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The American Society for Experimental NeuroTherapeutics, Inc. 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder, affecting more than 6 million people worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Numerous drugs for the treatment of motor and non-motor symptoms of PD are available on the market. While these drugs improve motor symptoms and quality of life of people with PD, there is no evidence that any of these interventions modify the progression of PD pathology. There are no FDA-approved interventions to slow down PD progression even though there have been multiple clinical trials for treatments that would modify the PD pathophysiological process. One potential explanation of this challenge is that PD is not a single patho-biological process. Consequentially, a tailored approach, where interventions are selected by the patients&#x02019; genotype or other biomarkers (as a measure of a biological process associated with a disease state), is required. In parallel, our knowledge of genetic risks has expanded significantly in the past decade and makes a precision medicine approach in PD very timely. Here, we review the obstacles towards the completion of clinical trials in PD along with the efforts to overcome these challenges. We outline the currently available data on precision medicine clinical trials, focusing primarily on <italic>alpha synuclein</italic> (<italic>SNCA</italic>), <italic>glucocerebrosidase</italic> (<italic>GBA</italic>), and <italic>Leucine-Rich Repeat Kinase 2</italic> (<italic>LRRK2</italic>).</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>Precision Medicine</title><p id="Par3">Precision medicine aims to tailor treatment in a personalized manner, for the right person at the right time. To achieve this, it uses diagnostic tools to identify specific biomarkers, often genetic, to help assess which medical treatments will be best for each patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Thus, in addition to the mission of providing personalized medicine, the term precision medicine also conveys the concept that genomics and other emerging biodata sciences will improve medicine&#x02019;s clinically defined nosology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">The hypothesis underlying precision medicine is that diseases previously treated as a single condition are actually biologically different, and that treatment should be tailored based on the biological signature of the individual (stratified medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]). A successful example is oncology, where precision medicine led to the identification of effective therapies based on tumor profiling and a better understanding of how tumors become resistant to cancer therapy&#x000a0;(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.gov/research/areas/treatment/pmi-oncology">https://www.cancer.gov/research/areas/treatment/pmi-oncology</ext-link>). In PD, precision trials are ongoing for genetic forms of PD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Genetic Underpinnings of Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease</title><p id="Par5">In recent years, our understanding of the genetics of PD has expanded significantly. In addition to over a dozen Mendelian loci (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), multiple PD genetic risk factors have been identified. These risk factors are mostly associated with a small increase in risk of PD (e.g. up to ~1.5-fold) but occur as commonly as 40% in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. It is thought that the overall heritable component of disease is about 30% (5&#x02013;10% due to monogenic causes and around 22% driven by common variants identified by genome-wide association studies) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. A prevailing hypothesis is that many of the identified genes and risk factors map into two closely related and overlapping cellular pathways: mitochondrial metabolism and autophagy. In addition, other pathways such as endosomal trafficking, synaptic transmission and immune response pathways have been identified to play a role in the pathogenesis of PD. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] While these biological pathways have been linked to PD via genetic studies, it is very likely that dysfunction in these same pathways due to environmental exposures could also lead to PD. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> describes the genetic architecture of PD.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Genetic architecture of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease, modified from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], showing the continuum of variants of different effect strengths and allele frequencies. The size of the bubbles roughly corresponds to population allele frequencies. Colors symbolize modes of inheritance: dominant (red), recessive (yellow), risk loci (green). The genetic risks for PD can be roughly divided into three groups (dotted areas; see main text for more details). The group of common low-risk genes (lower right corner) includes more than 90 putative independent genome-wide significant signals identified in a GWAS meta-analysis based on more than 13,000 patients and 95,000 controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Similar to <italic>LRRK2</italic> and <italic>SNCA</italic>, some mutations in <italic>VPS13C</italic> and <italic>GCH1</italic> are likely causal or confer high risk for PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13311_2020_920_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">The genetic risks for PD can be roughly divided into three groups, based on their frequency in the general population and the PD risk they convey. Accordingly, clinical trial designs for each one of these groups may also differ.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par7"><bold>Group A</bold> includes most of the Mendelian genes linked to PD (shown in the left upper part of Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). These mutations convey a major risk factor for PD, but are extremely rare. In most cases, mutations are present in too few patients for a standard clinical trial design (e.g., <italic>PINK1</italic> or <italic>PARK7</italic>). Intervention on such mutations would require a different study design such as patient-customized therapy. A recent report of patient-customized intervention in a child with neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis 7 (CLN7, a form of Batten&#x02019;s disease) demonstrates the potential of this type of study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Among all of these rare PD mutations, mutations in <italic>SNCA</italic> and <italic>Parkin</italic> may be more common. Indeed, if a sufficient amount of <italic>SNCA</italic> mutation carriers are identified, there may be promising interventions in this patient population group including silencers of the <italic>SNCA</italic> gene (e.g., antisense oligonucleotides (ASOs), viral-mediated delivery of siRNA, and miRNA. Of these, ASOs have recently shown favorable results in patients with spinal muscular atrophy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and Huntington&#x02019;s disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. As described below, these treatments may also be useful for a broader range of PD patients.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par8"><bold>Group C</bold> includes variants which convey a very low increased risk for PD (shown in green on the right in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), but may be present in a large percentage of people with PD. These variants may be common enough that intervention on the biological pathway of one of these variants may not require pre-screening clinical trial candidates, but instead result in stratifying the participants based on the presence of the variant. For example, a major pathway highlighted by GWAS analysis in large PD cohorts is the adaptive immune system. This was first identified through a human leukocyte antigen association but is now increasingly recognized as a major determinant of risk across the genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. We are not aware of any current clinical trials that focus on a Group C gene for PD. However, ASOs (developed by Ionis) targeting tau (<italic>MAPT</italic>) are being studied in a phase I clinical trial for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. In addition, retroactive analyses of published clinical trials may identify responders versus non-responders based on variant status. It is possible that unsuccessful clinical trials for disease-modifying agents would have been successful in a select group of people with PD.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par9"><bold>Group B</bold> includes variants that are shown in the middle of Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. They are deleterious enough (associated with a high enough risk for PD) to warrant an intervention, but also common enough to make clinical trials targeting mutation carriers with a reasonably high number of participants feasible. Currently, this group includes variants in <italic>GBA</italic> and <italic>LRRK2.</italic> Given tremendous efforts to identify research cohorts, (e.g., by the Michael J. Fox Foundation-funded PPMI studies) our knowledge of the PD phenotype and the risk for PD among these mutation carriers has improved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par10">The differences among the groups (A/B/C) are derived from the frequency of the variant in the population (<italic>x</italic>-axis), and the risk for PD associated with the variant (<italic>y</italic>-axis). The relationship between frequency and PD risk can guide the study design and who will benefit from particular interventions. Specifically, mutations in group A are rare, and interventions on these targets may not benefit all PD cases. One example of this is homozygous carriers of <italic>PRKN</italic> mutations. We are not aware of such studies in group A in PD but an example from the dementia field would be for intra-cisternal PR006 administration of the progranulin protein (<italic>PGRN</italic>) in carriers of the progranulin gene mutation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.ucsf.edu/trial/NCT04408625">https://clinicaltrials.ucsf.edu/trial/NCT04408625</ext-link>). This type of intervention would not be for all patients with dementia but would only include mutation carriers. The study design would have to include genotype as an inclusion criterion and a large number of PD cases would have to be genotyped to identify a small number of participants. Variants in group C are common and intervention on them may be beneficial for all PD cases. An example would be interventions on alpha-synuclein (&#x003b1;-syn) in PD. These studies do not require prescreening for genetic variants prior to study participation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Current Research and Clinical Trials for Genetic Forms of PD</title><sec id="Sec4"><title><italic>SNCA-</italic>Associated Parkinsonism: Active and Passive Immunization</title><p id="Par11">Discovered in 1997, <italic>SNCA</italic>, which encodes the protein product &#x003b1;-syn, was the first cloned gene for PD. Soon after, it was discovered that &#x003b1;-syn is a key component of Lewy bodies which are considered to be a pathological hallmark of PD. Therefore, the link between &#x003b1;-syn and PD seems clear and extends beyond the genetic cases caused by <italic>SNCA</italic> mutations. The physiological state of &#x003b1;-syn is an intrinsically disordered monomer or helically folded tetramere that has toxic effects in its oligomeric form. The protein is degraded mainly by the autophagic system. Pathogenic missense mutations (A53T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], A30P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], E46K [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and H50Q [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and G51D [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] [PARK1] which leads to misfolding and promotes apoptosis) and changes in gene dosage (duplications, triplications [PARK4] which leads to an excess and aggregation of &#x003b1;-syn) are associated with PD (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The prevailing hypothesis is that excess &#x003b1;-syn is pathogenic and that mutations in the <italic>SNCA</italic> gene lead to&#x000a0;gain-of-function. Indeed, the clinical phenotype of mutation carriers has been associated with early-onset rapid motor progression and frequent dementia; the phenotype may also overlap with multiple system atrophy (MSA) or dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB). Following the dosage effect, the disease may be more rapidly progressive in triplication carriers versus duplication carriers.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>World map of <italic>SNCA</italic>-associated Parkinsonism. A total of 140 cases have been reported in the literature. Circles reflect frequency per region. Data and image were retrieved from the MDSGene Website [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13311_2020_920_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Multiple clinical trials are targeting alpha-synuclein. While <italic>SNCA</italic> mutation carriers would naturally benefit from such interventions, given the difficulty recruiting large enough cohorts of these carriers, none of the trials focuses solely on this population. Since &#x003b1;-syn deposits are universally present in PD and MSA, the trials include both PD and MSA patients. While a very attractive drug target, one of the challenges of the field is that there are no &#x003b1;-syn tracers available. Developing &#x003b1;-syn tracers would help advance the field as they may serve as biomarkers, specifically for target engagement.</p><p id="Par13">Multiple mechanisms of actions are currently being studied for &#x003b1;-syn, including immunotherapies, gene therapies, and small molecules (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Compounds under development targeting alpha-synuclein</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Mechanism of action</th><th align="left">Compound</th><th align="left">Sponsor</th><th align="left">Phase/status</th><th align="left"><italic>N</italic> of patients</th><th align="left">Recruited participants</th><th align="left">RCT no.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Active immunization</td><td align="left">PD01A, PD03A</td><td align="left">AFFITOPE</td><td align="left">Phase 1, completed</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td align="left">PD</td><td align="left">NCT02267434</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Passive immunization</td><td align="left">BIIB054 (SPARK Study)</td><td align="left">Biogen</td><td align="left">Phase 2, active, not recruiting, estimated completion 06-2021</td><td char="." align="char">311</td><td align="left">PD</td><td align="left">NCT03318523</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Passive immunization</td><td align="left">Prasinezumab, PRX002/RO7046015 (PASADENA Study)</td><td align="left">Prothena/Roche</td><td align="left">Phase 2, active, not recruiting, estimated completion 02-2021</td><td char="." align="char">316</td><td align="left">PD</td><td align="left">NCT03100149</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Passive immunization</td><td align="left">MEDI1341</td><td align="left">AstraZeneca and Takeda</td><td align="left">Phase 1, recruiting, estimated completion 01-2021</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td align="left">healthy</td><td align="left">NCT03272165</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Passive immunization</td><td align="left">Rec47</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibition</td><td align="left">NPT200-11, NPT100-18A</td><td align="left">Neuropore</td><td align="left">Phase 1, completed</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td align="left">Healthy</td><td align="left">NCT02606682</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibition</td><td align="left">NPT-088</td><td align="left">Proclara (formerly Neurophage)</td><td align="left">&#x02020;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibition</td><td align="left">Anle138b&#x000a0;[*]</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical, a clinical trial in PD is expected to begin end of 2020</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibition</td><td align="left">CLR01 [*]</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibition</td><td align="left">PBT434 [*]</td><td align="left">Alterity Therapeutics Limited</td><td align="left">Phase 1</td><td char="." align="char">70</td><td align="left">MSA</td><td align="left">n.k.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibition</td><td align="left">VX-765[*]</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn degradation enhancers</td><td align="left">Rapamycin (Sirolimus)[*]</td><td align="left">NYU Langone Health, NINDS</td><td align="left">Phase 2, recruiting, estimated completion 08-2021</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td align="left">MSA</td><td align="left">NCT03589976</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn degradation enhancers</td><td align="left">Micro-RNA-101 [*]</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-syn degradation enhancers</td><td align="left">TLR4-agonist MPLA [*]</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nanobodies</td><td align="left">VH14*PEST</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Preclinical</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Epigenome editing</td><td align="left">n/a</td><td align="left">Duke University/Seelos Therapeutics</td><td align="left">Phase 1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">n/a</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>n/a = not applicable; n.k. = not known</p><p>*Compounds primarily being tested in MSA</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Trial completed in individuals with probable Alzheimer&#x02019;s, may be applicable to synucleinopathies</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Immunotherapies</title><p id="Par14">Immunotherapies include active immunization (i.e., a vaccination which triggers the immune system to generate an immune reaction, including antibodies, against &#x003b1;-syn), and passive immunization (i.e., administration of antibodies directed against different domains of &#x003b1;-syn). Since it is estimated that antibodies would be most effective against extracellular proteins, these immunotherapies are designed to reduce the load of extracellular &#x003b1;-syn, stop the spread of &#x003b1;-syn pathology in the brain, and/or neutralize its toxic effects. While active vaccinations are generally associated with a higher potential risk of side effects, so far no relevant safety and tolerability issues have occurred in the current &#x003b1;-syn studies. However, active vaccination strategies (such as AFFITOPE) have only been tested in phase 1 human trials.</p><p id="Par15">Of the passive vaccinations, two compounds have reached the clinical phase 2 study level and are currently tested in patients with early PD: PRX002 (PASADENA study, sponsored by Prothena) and BIIB054 (SPARK study, sponsored by Biogen). The first antibody, prasinezumab (PRX002/ RO7046015), binds to the C-terminus of &#x003b1;-syn. A study in healthy volunteers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and in mild-to-moderate PD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] demonstrated a favorable safety and tolerability profile which led to the international PASADENA study. A total of 68 centers in the USA and Europe (i.e., Austria France, Germany, and Spain) participate in this 52-week trial. Completion is estimated for early 2021.</p><p id="Par16">The second &#x003b1;-syn antibody, BIIB054, binds to the N-terminus of &#x003b1;-syn, to residues 1&#x02013;10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. BIIB054 is highly selective for aggregated forms of &#x003b1;-syn with at least an 800-fold higher apparent affinity for fibrillar versus monomeric recombinant &#x003b1;-syn and it has a strong preference for human PD brain tissue. Efficacy studies in three different mouse models with intracerebrally inoculated preformed &#x003b1;-syn fibrils showed that BIIB054 treatment attenuated the spreading of &#x003b1;-syn pathology, rescued motor impairment, and reduced the loss of dopamine transporter density in dopaminergic terminals in the striatum. This led Biogen to initiate the international SPARK study which consists of monthly IV infusions (at 250&#x000a0;mg, 1250&#x000a0;mg, or 3500&#x000a0;mg) over 52&#x000a0;weeks. Another compound in the pipeline for passive immunization is MEDI1341 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] (phase 1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Small Molecules</title><p id="Par17">Another approach that takes a different route of action is small molecules which penetrate the blood&#x02013;brain barrier and modify &#x003b1;-syn biology. These include inhibition of &#x003b1;-syn misfolding and aggregation and reduction of cortical pathology (NPT200-11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], currently in phase 1). Another small molecule mechanism utilized is targeting misfolded or aggregated proteins (NPT088, a second-generation immunoglobulin-general amyloid interaction motif (Ig-GAIM) molecule, which is being developed by the company Neurophage). In the case of an &#x003b1;-syn overexpression-based PD rat model, VH14*PEST (a nanobody which targets the non-amyloid component region) showed maintenance of striatal dopaminergic tone and modest behavioral improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Nanobodies are genetically engineered fragments of antibodies which can modulate monomeric concentrations of target proteins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Gene Therapy</title><p id="Par18">Another potential strategy is gene therapy, namely the CRISPR-dCas9 epigenome-editing approach which manipulates endogenous <italic>SNCA</italic> levels. Researchers at Duke University (now further developed by Seelos Therapeutics) designed an all-in-one lentiviral which harbors gRNA, dCas9 nuclease, and the catalytic domain DNMT3A to target specific hypomethylated CpG islands in the <italic>SNCA</italic> intron 1 region. This led to the downregulation of <italic>SNCA</italic> mRNA and protein levels and phenotypic perturbations in pluripotent stem cells of a <italic>SNCA</italic> triplication carrier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">Given PD&#x02019;s shared pathophysiological basis with MSA (i.e., both are synucleinopathies), it will be interesting to follow current developments in MSA as treatments may also be effective in PD. &#x003b1;-syn aggregation inhibitors (e.g., Anle138b, CLR01, PBT-434, and VX-765), passive immunization (rec7), and &#x003b1;-syn degradation enhancers (e.g., rapamycin/sirolimus) have been investigated for MSA; for a review, see Heras-Garvin and Stefanova [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><italic>LRRK2</italic>-Associated Parkinsonism: Kinase Inhibitors Are a Promising Target</title><p id="Par20">More than 700 <italic>LRRK2</italic> cases have been reported in the literature. The International <italic>LRRK2</italic> Consortium study estimated that the most common mutation in <italic>LRRK2</italic>, G2019S, accounts for 1% of sporadic and 4% of familial PD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Mutations in <italic>LRRK2</italic> are more common in certain ethnicities. North African Arabs (36% in familial, 39% in sporadic) and Ashkenazi Jews (28% in familial, 10% in sporadic) have the highest frequencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The G2019S mutation is common in Whites, while G2385R and R1628P are the most frequent variants in Asian patients (detected in around 5&#x02013;10% of Asian PD patients) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Penetrance of <italic>LRRK2</italic> is age dependent and estimations in the general population are variable, ranging between 30% and 74% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. There are multiple reasons for this wide range of penetrance estimates, including differences in study design, the investigation of different populations, and the heterogeneity of <italic>LRRK2</italic> presentation. Regardless, the wide range of penetrance estimation makes trial design for preventative interventions extremely difficult.</p><p id="Par21">While the mechanisms by which <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutations cause PD have not been completely disentangled, there is increasing evidence of increased LRRK2 kinase function in mutation carriers with PD. The G2019S mutation, for example, results in a direct two-to-threefold increase in kinase activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].The potential gain-of-function effect is an attractive target for treatment because inhibition is easier to achieve than improvement of reduced protein activity (as in <italic>GBA</italic>). Furthermore, kinase inhibitors are widely used in oncology and the PD field can benefit from advancements in other fields. Since the first generation of LRRK2 inhibitors, newer compounds have progressively improved in potency, selectivity, and brain penetrance. However, efficacy and safety remain a concern. This is mainly due to the fact that other tissues, particularly the kidney, lung, and a subtype of peripheral immune cells, robustly express LRRK2. For example, the kidney has a ~6.2-fold higher expression of LRRK2 compared to the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The expression of <italic>LRRK2</italic> in other tissues is a potential source of peripheral side effects, which can include the development of lamelar bodies and impaired autophagy-lysosomal function induced by LRRK2 inhibitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. More recent data, however, suggest compounds that only partially downregulate LRRK2 levels or kinase activity, i.e., by 50% or less, are unlikely to produce major side effects related to on-target safety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] and lipid droplets in lamelar bodies are absorbed after the drug is stopped.</p><p id="Par22">One alternative to avoid systemic toxicity is to find a way to specifically modify LRRK2 activity in the brain without modifying activity peripherally. New drug modalities that keep peripheral side effects to a minimum include PROTACs (PROeolysis TArgeting Chimera) which selectively induce intracellular proteolysis via the ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome system of the mutant without affecting WT-LRRK2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. However, due to their molecular size, PROTACs show poor permeability across cell membranes which might affect brain penetration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Another alternative to avoid systemic side effects is currently tested by Biogen, who launched a phase 1 antisense oligonucleotide (ASO) trial. Participants will receive a single intrathecal injection of the compound BIIB094, an ASO, on multiple days. Recently, ASOs have been approved by the FDA for spinal muscular atrophy and are being tested for Huntington&#x02019;s disease and non-neurological disorders such as cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. ASOs reduce the expression of a mutated gene by binding to target mRNAs and either block the translation of the abnormal protein or induce its degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. ASOs can also promote splicing around mutations. For disorders caused by toxic gain-of-function mutations such as <italic>LRRK2</italic>, further investigation regarding ASOs is warranted. In a preclinical study, administration of <italic>LRRK2</italic> ASOs to the brains of mice reduced LRRK2 protein levels and fibril-induced &#x003b1;-syn inclusions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]; data from humans are not yet available.</p><p id="Par23">Several structurally different LRRK2 inhibitors from Genentech, GSK, Merck, and Pfizer are in the pipeline (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The compounds developed by Denali are already in clinical trials and a phase 1b trial in healthy individuals has been completed which included pulmonary and renal safety parameters. The company is advancing DNL201 (GNE-7915) to a phase 1b safety and biomarker study in <italic>LRRK2</italic>-linked PD and iPD (idiopathic PD). Twenty-nine mild to moderately affected PD patients with or without <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation were randomized to either low dose DNL201, high dose DNL201, or placebo in this 28-day randomized placebo-controlled trial. In January 2020, Denali announced that both doses achieved more than 50% inhibition of pS935 LRRK2 and pRab10 phosphorylation in blood, and improved the lysosomal biomarker BMP in urine (by 20% or 60% at the low and high dose) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf">(https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf</ext-link> [online]). The same company also is testing another compound, DNL151. In a trial in 150 healthy volunteers, safety and biomarker goals were met <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf">(https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf</ext-link> [online]). The compound is now being tested in PD patients with recruitment in Belgium, the Netherlands, and the UK; however, the trial is delayed because of the COVID-19 pandemic. According to the press release, Denali intends to select either DNL201 or DNL151 in mid-2020 to advance into phase 2/3 clinical trials in patients with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf">(https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf</ext-link> [online]). To facilitate recruitment, a &#x0201c;direct-to-consumer&#x0201d; approach for testing and counseling will be available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]&#x02014;a strategy that proved successful in genetic testing with the PPMI initiative. Most recently, Denali has announced a strategic collaboration with Centogene, a gene diagnostic lab, to enhance recruitment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Pharmaceutical companies and academic centers are also conducting observational studies to identify best endpoints related to the <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation, e.g. typical neurocognitive abnormalities <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01424475?term=lrrk2&#x00026;draw=2&#x00026;rank=8">(https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01424475?term=lrrk2&#x00026;draw=2&#x00026;rank=8)</ext-link>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><italic>LRRK2</italic>-targeted treatments including LRRK2 inhibitors and antisense oligomeres under development for PD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="7">LRRK2</th></tr><tr><th>Compound</th><th>DNL201</th><th>DNL151</th><th>No public data</th><th>No public data</th><th>No public data</th><th>BIIB094</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Sponsor</td><td>Denali</td><td>Denali</td><td>GSK</td><td>Pfizer</td><td>Genetech</td><td>Biogen</td></tr><tr><td>RCT no.</td><td>NCT03710707</td><td>NCT04056689</td><td/><td/><td/><td>NCT03976349</td></tr><tr><td>Mechanism</td><td>LRRK2 inhibition</td><td>LRRK2 inhibition</td><td>LRRK2 inhibition</td><td>LRRK2 inhibition</td><td>LRRK2 inhibition</td><td>Antisense oligonucleotide (ASO)</td></tr><tr><td>Status</td><td>Completed</td><td>Delayed because of COVID19</td><td>Planned</td><td>Under development</td><td>Under development</td><td>Ongoing, estimated completion end of 2022</td></tr><tr><td>Phase</td><td>Phase 1b</td><td>Phase 1b</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>Phase 1</td></tr><tr><td>Design</td><td>Multicenter, randomized, placebo-controlled</td><td>Multicenter</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>International, multicenter, placebo-controlled</td></tr><tr><td>Total <italic>N</italic> of patients</td><td>29</td><td>34</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>62</td></tr><tr><td><italic>LRRK2</italic>-PD</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td>Idiopathic PD</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td>Age</td><td>30&#x02013;75</td><td/><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>35&#x02013;80</td></tr><tr><td>Duration</td><td>28&#x000a0;days</td><td>28&#x000a0;days</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n.d.</td></tr><tr><td>Doses tested</td><td>Low/high</td><td>Three doses</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td><td>Single- and multiple-ascending-dose</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Deep Brain Stimulation for <italic>LRRK2</italic>-Associated PD</title><p id="Par24">Interestingly, a different level of benefit was noted after deep brain stimulation surgery in <italic>LRRK2</italic>-associated PD. The outcome was better in patients with the most common <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation, p.G2019S, compared to the poor response seen in patients with the rarer p.R1441G mutation. However, overall numbers remain small. The overall benefit was compromised by the rapid progression of cognitive and neuropsychiatric symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Parkinsonism Associated with <italic>GBA</italic> Mutations</title><p id="Par25">Clinical trials that target the glucocerebrosidase (<italic>GBA</italic>) pathway are probably in the most advanced stages towards precision medicine in PD. This is a result of the relatively high frequency of <italic>GBA</italic> mutations in PD and the availability of basic science data collected about <italic>GBA</italic> mutations from Gaucher disease research. <italic>GBA</italic> mutations are a common risk factor for PD and are present in 7&#x02013;10% of PD patients worldwide. Among Ashkenazi Jews, around 20% of PD patients carry a <italic>GBA</italic> mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. A high prevalence has also been reported in the Netherlands, where 15.5% of PD patients carry a <italic>GBA</italic> mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Homozygous <italic>GBA</italic> mutations cause Gaucher disease (GD), the most common autosomal recessive lysosomal storage disease, with an estimated annual incidence of 1/60,000 and an estimated carrier frequency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] of 0.7 to 0.8% in the general population. The clinical presentation of GD can be divided into systemic and neurological manifestations. The former, present in all forms of GD, includes hepatosplenomegaly, painful skeletal disorders, and pancytopenia. The latter is present in the more severe types of GD, GD- type 2, and GD-type 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. More than 300 mutations in <italic>GBA</italic> have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], and they are traditionally divided based on the GD phenotype they are associated with. Mild mutations (e.g., the N370S mutation) are associated with type 1 GD, while severe mutations (e.g., the L444P mutation) are associated with type 2 or type 3 GD. Some ethnicities show higher mutation rates; specifically, in the Ashkenazi Jewish (AJ) population, the annual incidence is 1/1000 and carrier frequencies are as high as 6% in all AJ. Both GD patients and healthy heterozygous carriers are at increased risk for PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>].&#x000a0;About 10% of <italic>GBA</italic> mutation carriers will develop PD and studies suggest that penetrance is age dependent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].&#x000a0;As in LRRK2, there is incomplete penetrance of PD among carriers and a wide range of penetrance estimates.</p><p id="Par28">Parkinsonism in <italic>GBA</italic> heterozygotes may be indistinguishable from iPD. However, they may have an earlier age at onset, more prevalent cognitive impairment, and may not respond to levodopa as well as iPD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. <italic>GBA</italic> mutations are also associated with other alpha-synucleinopathies, including dementia with Lewy bodies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] (pathologically confirmed) and, in some studies, with MSA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. In contrast, there is no association with essential tremor or Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease.</p><p id="Par29">Pathologically, the brains of patients with heterozygous <italic>GBA</italic> mutations strongly resemble those from patients with iPD. However, there is also widespread cortical Lewy body involvement in <italic>GBA</italic> mutation carriers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. A few studies showed a reciprocal relationship between levels of glucocerebrosidase (GCase; the enzyme encoded by <italic>GBA</italic>) and levels of the aggregate-prone protein &#x003b1;-syn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Notably, iPD patients also have reduced GCase activity (about 33% decrease) in the substantia nigra and cerebellum, making treatments that target <italic>GBA</italic> relevant for iPD and patients with PD dementia as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. </p><p id="Par30">The GBA-encoded protein, glucocerebrosidase, is a lysosomal enzyme which plays a role in the breakdown of glucocerebroside and glucosylsphingosine into glucose and ceramide or sphingosine respectively. In GD, there is a lysosomal buildup of the substrate glucocerebroside in the reticulo-endothelial system with reduced clearance. Gaucher disease manifestations are a result of this diminished glucocerebrosidase (GCase) activity. FDA-approved interventions for GD include enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) and substrate reduction therapy (SRT), which are inhibitors of the glucosylceramide synthase enzyme. None of the currently approved drugs penetrate the blood&#x02013;brain barrier, but theoretically similar interventions that penetrate the blood&#x02013;brain barrier may modify the PD phenotype.</p><p id="Par31">While the PD field can benefit from decades of GD research, the underlying mechanisms of how <italic>GBA</italic> leads to the development of PD are not fully understood. One hypothesis is that there is a self-propagating bidirectional feedback loop between GCase and &#x003b1;-syn. Loss of GCase activity causes &#x003b1;-syn accumulation and oligomerization, resulting in neurotoxicity through aggregate-dependent mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Furthermore, elevated &#x003b1;-syn inhibits lysosomal maturation and normal GCase activity while hindering GCase transport from the endoplasmic reticulum to the lysosome. All of these mechanisms continue over time until the threshold for neurodegeneration is reached [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Based on this, targeted treatments can take a variety of approaches including modulation of glycosphingolipid turnover and restoration of enzyme function (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Treatment approaches for <italic>GBA</italic>-associated PD include the modulation of glycosphingolipid turnover and restoration of enzyme function</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13311_2020_920_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><italic>GBA</italic>-targeting treatments for PD in the clinical phase that aim to modulate glycosphingolipid turnover and restore enzyme function</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>GBA</th><th>MOVES-PD study part 1</th><th>MOVES-PD study part 2</th><th>AiM-PD</th><th colspan="3"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Compound</td><td colspan="2">Venglustat (GZ/SAR402671)</td><td>Ambroxol</td><td>RTB101</td><td>LTI-291</td><td>PR001</td></tr><tr><td>Administration</td><td colspan="2">Oral</td><td>Oral</td><td>Oral</td><td/><td>Injections</td></tr><tr><td>Sponsor</td><td colspan="2">Sanofi</td><td>UCL and Cure PD Trust</td><td>Restorbio</td><td>LTI/Allergan</td><td>Prevail</td></tr><tr><td>RCT no.</td><td colspan="2">NCT02906020</td><td>NCT02941822</td><td/><td>(NL7061; NTR7299) <sup>a</sup></td><td/></tr><tr><td>Mechanism</td><td colspan="2">Glucosylceramide synthase inhibition; reduction of GBA-related GSLs</td><td>GCase activation</td><td>TORC1 inhibition</td><td>GCase activation</td><td>Gene therapy, AAV-based</td></tr><tr><td>Status</td><td>Completed</td><td>Recruiting, estimated primary completion 2021</td><td>Completed</td><td>Ongoing; data expected 2020</td><td>Recruiting in Leiden (NL)</td><td>Clinical centers initiated</td></tr><tr><td>Phase</td><td>2</td><td/><td>2a</td><td>1b/2a</td><td>1b</td><td>1b</td></tr><tr><td>Design</td><td>Multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo&#x02013;controlled, sequential cohort</td><td>Prospective, single-center, open-label</td><td>Single-center open-label noncontrolled clinical</td><td>Multicenter, 2:1 randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled</td><td>Randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, parallel study</td><td>Randomized, double-blind, sham procedure-controlled, ascending dose study</td></tr><tr><td>Total N of part.</td><td>17</td><td/><td>8&#x02009;+&#x02009;10</td><td>45</td><td>Approximately 40</td><td>30/16</td></tr><tr><td><italic>GBA</italic>-PD</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td/><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td>Idiopathic PD</td><td>No</td><td/><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>&#x0221a;</td><td>No</td><td>&#x0221a;</td></tr><tr><td>Age</td><td>18&#x02013;80&#x000a0;yrs. (mean 58&#x000a0;years)</td><td/><td>40&#x02013;80, mean 60&#x000a0;years</td><td/><td>18&#x000a0;years or older</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Duration</td><td>36&#x000a0;weeks</td><td>52&#x000a0;weeks + 104&#x000a0;weeks extension</td><td>6&#x000a0;months</td><td>4&#x000a0;weeks</td><td>28&#x000a0;days</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Doses tested</td><td>3 escalating doses</td><td>1 dose</td><td>Escalating oral dose to 1.26&#x000a0;g per day [420&#x000a0;mg 3 times per day]</td><td>300&#x000a0;mg; &#x000b1;&#x02009;sirolimus</td><td>10 or 60&#x000a0;mg once daily</td><td>Two escalating dose cohorts</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.trialregister.nl/trial/7061">https://www.trialregister.nl/trial/7061</ext-link> for more information</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Treatment Directed at Modulation of Glycosphingolipid Turnover</title><p id="Par32">Substrate reduction therapy inhibits the biosynthesis of lipid substrates and thereby prevents their accumulation. While this approach does not target the mutant gene or dysfunctional enzyme itself, it is an effective FDA-approved treatment of the systemic symptoms of Gaucher disease. However, the approved inhibitors show no effective CNS concentration and do not affect the neurological symptoms of Gaucher disease (i.e., Gaucher type&#x000a0;2 and&#x000a0;3). New glucosylceramide synthase inhibitors show good brain penetration, improved &#x003b1;-syn processing, and behavioral outcomes in mouse models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Based on these findings, Sanofi launched the MOVES-PD study, a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, in order to assess the efficacy and safety of the glucosylceramide synthase inhibitor Venglustat (GZ/SAR402671). Initial results from a phase I study were recently published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Briefly, 17 <italic>GBA</italic>-PD were enrolled (13 on Venglustat, 4 on placebo; mean age 58&#x000a0;years, mean disease duration 7&#x000a0;years) into this 36-week randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, sequential cohort study of once-daily Venglustat at three escalating doses. No serious adverse events occurred. Side effects included psychological, neurological, and gastrointestinal-related symptoms. Plasma and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) glucosylceramide levels decreased in a dose-dependent manner (up to 75%), confirming target engagement. This favorable safety and tolerability profile of Venglustat at all doses led the company to advance to a phase II study (a 52-week trial which is currently ongoing) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Treatment Directed at Restoration of Enzyme Function</title><p id="Par33">Other therapies focus on the restoration of enzyme function, thus increasing glucocerebrosidase activity, especially in the brain. This can be achieved by [3)] ERT (enzyme replacement therapy), [9)] gene therapy, or [7)] small molecules. ERT is currently available for patients with Gaucher disease. However, ERT is based on large molecules and we are not familiar with any clinical trials of ERT that may penetrate the blood&#x02013;brain barrier. Furthermore, there are no data on the use of ERT in PD.</p><p id="Par34">Gene therapy uses adeno-associated virus vectors to deliver engineered DNA to human cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. For <italic>GBA</italic>, preclinical studies in mice demonstrated that adeno-associated virus-mediated expression of glucocerebrosidase corrected the aberrant accumulation of the toxic lipid glucosylsphingosine and reduced the levels of ubiquitin, tau, and &#x003b1;-syn aggregates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Prevail Therapeutics, a new company launched in 2017, started a gene therapy clinical trial of PR001 in 16 <italic>GBA-</italic>PD patients in late 2019 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ir.prevailtherapeutics.com/news-releases/news-release-details/prevail-therapeutics-provides-program-update-pr001-parkinsons-0">https://ir.prevailtherapeutics.com/news-releases/news-release-details/prevail-therapeutics-provides-program-update-pr001-parkinsons-0)</ext-link>. The company will also test the compound in children with neuropathic Gaucher disease starting in the first half of 2020.</p><p id="Par35">Furthermore, small molecules have also attracted attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Early glucocerebrosidase chaperones that underwent clinical trials for Gaucher disease included isofagomine (afegostat-tartrate, AT2101). This treatment did not lead to significant clinical improvement and further clinical development for this indication was discontinued [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Ambroxol, which is a promising small molecule chaperone widely used in Europe as a mucolytic agent, may potentially facilitate the transit of the misfolded GCase protein to the lysosome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Its stabilizing and enhancing effects on the levels of GCase were identified in a high-throughput screen in the context of Gaucher disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. It is pH dependent, binds to the active site of the GCase protein, and reduces GCase activity. Ambroxol has also been shown to improve lysosomal function and increase enzyme activity in in vitro studies utilizing dermal fibroblasts with <italic>GBA</italic> mutations (i.e. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>] as well as in studies performed on non-human primates (i.e. cynomolgus monkeys) with <italic>GBA</italic> mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]). The effects of Ambroxol at high doses were recently tested in a single-center, open-label, non-controlled, clinical trial (escalating oral dose to 1.26&#x000a0;g per day [420&#x000a0;mg 3 times per day] which is considerably higher compared to the 30&#x02013;120&#x000a0;mg/day used for the treatment of respiratory disease) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. Eighteen patients with moderately severe PD (mean age 60&#x000a0;years) completed the study, eight with <italic>GBA</italic> mutations and ten mutation-negative. Ambroxol penetrated CSF, but led to a 19% reduction from the mean baseline CSF GCase activity at day 186. There was an increase of CSF &#x003b1;-synuclein which the authors interpreted as an increase of extracellular export of the protein from the brain parenchyma. The drug was well tolerated, and no serious adverse events were reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. For other indications, Ambroxol has been studied in &#x0003e;&#x02009;15,000 patients in more than 100 trials with an excellent safety record [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. As mentioned above, GCase activity is also reduced in iPD patients&#x02019; brains (SN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>], making the therapy potentially relevant for iPD. The effect of Ambroxol in non-<italic>GBA</italic> PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>] and non-<italic>GBA</italic> PD dementia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>] will be better understood once results from the two ongoing studies become available. These studies include ten non-<italic>GBA</italic> PD and 75 PD dementia patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>] (treated at daily doses of 420&#x000a0;mg/day or 525&#x02013;1050&#x000a0;mg/day, respectively).</p><p id="Par36">The effects of LTI-291, an activator of the GCase enzyme and another small molecule therapy, were studied in a 1-month phase 1b trial conducted in the Netherlands, where the frequency of <italic>GBA</italic> mutations was reported to be around 15% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Around 40 <italic>GBA</italic>-PD patients participated. There were no safety events and data showed a good dose-dependent brain penetration (personal communication). The company, Lysosomal Therapeutics, Inc. (LTI), is a Massachusetts-based biotech venture which plans to develop therapies for Gaucher disease and other lysosome-based neurodegenerative diseases.</p><p id="Par37">Small molecules can also modify <italic>GBA</italic>-PD&#x000a0;by modifying <italic>GBA</italic>-independent pathways. One such example is RTB101, which is an inhibitor of the target of rapamycin complex 1 (TORC1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Rapamycin reached public attention when Bloomberg magazine publicized it as a potential &#x0201c;forever pill&#x0201d; in 2015. Known for its immunosuppressant properties, rapamycin prolongs lifespan by 15&#x02013;25% in various non-mammalian organisms even when given late in life; it has also been found to increase healthspan. A 5-year study in dogs is planning on testing the geroprotective effects of RTB101 in mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. <italic>TORC1</italic> plays a role in cell growth and aging and is the switch between fasting and feeding states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Mutations in <italic>TORC1</italic> cause focal cortical dysplasia, an established cause of epilepsy. The role of mTORC1 in regulating autophagy may also have implications for neurodegenerative diseases. In preclinical models, TORC1 inhibition induces autophagy and prevents neuronal loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. It improves motor function in multiple PD models including &#x003b1;-syn transgenic mice and MPTP models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. In oncology cell cultures, treatment with RTB101 reduced the levels of glucosylceramide, the main substrate of GCase. There is a current phase 1b/2a trial of RTB101 in combination with sirolimus that involves 45 PD patients with or without a <italic>GBA</italic> mutation. The study was initiated in early 2019; data is expected in 2020.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Deep Brain Stimulation for <italic>GBA</italic>-PD</title><p id="Par38">Outcome data after DBS are available for around 30 <italic>GBA</italic>-PD patients, 60% of whom showed a favorable response, whereas 30% showed a poor response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. However, sample sizes remain small and genetic testing does not yet provide added prognostic value over what can already be obtained through careful clinical assessment when the patient is evaluated for DBS&#x000a0;surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Targeting the Mitochondrial Pathways&#x02014;Treatment for <italic>PRKN</italic>/<italic>PINK1</italic></title><p id="Par39">The second major pathway implicated in PD pathogenesis is mitochondrial metabolism, which is susceptible to damage by oxidative stress. A prevailing hypothesis is that mutations in <italic>PRKN</italic> and <italic>PINK1</italic> cause PD due to mitochondrial dysfunction. Clinically, people with PRKN PD and PINK1 PD display an earlier-onset, are sensitive to levodopa, and are prone to motor fluctuations. And, &#x000a0;these patients have minimal cognitive decline, even after many years of disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par40">Hence, antioxidative strategies targeting Parkin (encoded by <italic>PRKN</italic>) and <italic>PINK1</italic>-mediated mitophagy are another emerging therapeutic approach for new treatments of PD. Several small molecule drugs that enhance mitophagy are in preclinical development and exploratory biomarkers for mitochondrial dysfunction and mitophagy activation are being tested. However, there are many aspects that need to be considered such as selecting the most effective and feasible targets in the mitophagy pathway, potential side effects, and stratification of the ideal population (for recent review, see Miller and Muquit 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]).</p><p id="Par41">It is important to note that several compounds targeting mitochondria have been systematically studied in PD, including coenzyme Q10 and creatine. However, these trials failed to demonstrate a disease-modifying benefit in patients with PD. Of these, coenzyme Q10 is currently revisited in a &#x0201c;smaller, smarter trial&#x0201d; where patients are recruited based on their genetic risk profile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Hence, patients will be stratified according to their risk for mitochondrial dysfunction (i.e., biallelic or monoallelic mutation in <italic>PRKN</italic> or <italic>PINK1</italic> vs. patients in whom omics suggest little or minimal mitochondrial dysfunction).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Challenges for Precision Clinical Trials</title><p id="Par42">Surprisingly, the major challenge towards precision medicine clinical trials for PD is not in the basic understanding of the genes and their function, but rather in identifying mutation carriers for clinical trials (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). There are many ways studies are trying to overcome this difficulty. In the case of interventions targeting &#x003b1;-syn, the challenge in identifying carriers of point mutations or copy number variants has led to clinical trials targeting patients with sporadic PD. In the case of <italic>GBA</italic> and <italic>LRRK2</italic>, it is less clear whether interventions on these pathways would help patients with sporadic PD. Given the relative rarity of mutation carriers, <italic>GBA</italic> and <italic>LRRK2</italic> trials may include patients in different stages of PD, as opposed to other clinical trials of disease modification which recruit patients in early PD who are often medication na&#x000ef;ve. The inclusion of patients at different stages of PD requires the development of more sophisticated outcome measures that are less sensitive to symptomatic, dopaminergic therapy than the standard motor examination, the Unified Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Top four challenges and barriers to effective clinical trials as perceived by health professionals, patients, and their caregivers&#x02014;for the full list, see Mathur et al. (2015) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Scientists and other health professionals</th><th>Patients and caregivers</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Lack of funding</td><td>Risk of potential adverse consequences and potential side effects</td></tr><tr><td>Lack of administrative support and time available to manage the trial</td><td>Disruption to normal medication regimen</td></tr><tr><td>Slow and difficult recruitment of people</td><td>Prospect of receiving a placebo instead of the active drug</td></tr><tr><td>Lack of practical support</td><td>Upheaval and inconvenience to life that trial participation would cause</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par43">The feasibility of genetically-targeted clinical trials would require a significant change in the way genotyping is currently practiced in PD. Only a small fraction of PD patients are clinically genotyped in CLIA-approved laboratories and know their genetic status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. A few pharmaceutical companies launched major genotyping efforts, e.g., Denali Therapeutics in collaboration with Centogene <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.centogene.com/company/article/centogene-and-denali-therapeutics-announce-strategic-collaboration-to-recruit-lrrk2-patients-for-cli.html">(https://www.centogene.com/company/article/centogene-and-denali-therapeutics-announce-strategic-collaboration-to-recruit-lrrk2-patients-for-cli.html</ext-link> [online]). In this context, the Parkinson&#x02019;s Foundation launched the PD GENEration initiative (currently conducted at 6 sites in the USA), which offers free genetic testing for clinically relevant PD-related genes and free genetic counseling to help participants better understand their results. More about current efforts in &#x0201c;Overcoming barriers to PD trial participation&#x0201d; are discussed in chapter 15 of this special issue.</p><p id="Par44">Another major challenge is the identification of reliable and validated disease markers and outcome measurements that are suitable for targeted intervention. Past trials largely relied on clinical motor impressions (e.g. UPDRS in the &#x0201c;off&#x0201d; state during clinic visits) which may not robustly detect disease-modifying effects. Better biomarkers are needed to evaluate the effectiveness of treatments by reflecting drug target engagement, disease severity, and progression of disease. Having a reliable marker would enhance drug development. For example, in the case of Huntington&#x02019;s disease, trials now include femtomolar-sensitive quantification (single molecule counting immunoassay) of the mutant protein in CSF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. For PD, Real-Time Quaking-Induced Conversion (RT-QuIC) techniques are being tested to determine their sensitivity and specificity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. There is also still a lack of reliable &#x003b1;-syn imaging methods which is a barrier to testing promising compounds; however, targeting a-syn is a major pursuit on the research front [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. Using artificial intelligence may advance the field further by identifying new biomarkers or facilitating biomarker validation and application.</p><p id="Par45">Furthermore, better understanding of disease mechanisms linking these genes to PD is necessary. In <italic>LRRK2</italic> and <italic>SNCA</italic>, while detailed mechanisms are not fully understood, treatments are focused on reducing activity or expression. In the case of <italic>GBA</italic>, as outlined above, enhancing or restoring enzyme function are currently favored approaches. Drug development for other genetic forms lags behind (e.g., <italic>PRKN</italic>), because suitable druggable targets have not been identified. Concerted efforts are being made to identify a variety of disease progression markers including biospecimen-based (i.e., blood, urine, CSF or biopsy; molecular, genomic, cellular), clinical, imaging, or others (e.g., electrophyiological, behavioral, and environmental). Among these, the PPMI initiative is a valuable source that brings together longitudinal data and specimen collection from more than 1200 volunteers with PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Summary and Final Remarks</title><p id="Par46">Recent failures in large Phase III clinical trials for PD suggest that disease modification will not succeed as long as PD is treated as a single disease with one pathophysiology. Therefore, we believe that precision medicine in PD may be a promising alternative and a timely approach.</p><p id="Par47">As summarized in this review, several gene-based therapies are being tested in clinical trials and numerous more are in the pipeline. These are exciting times. However, the process of bringing a drug into the clinic is cumbersome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]. Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America (PhRMA) estimate that for every 5000 to 10,000 compounds screened, only five enter human clinical trials, only one is approved by the Food and Drug Administration, and only two in ten drugs generate enough revenue to recoup their research and development costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. Thus, setbacks are expected.</p><p id="Par48">One unanswered question is who will benefit from new &#x0201c;precision&#x0201d; drugs. Will these be useful only for mutation carriers (and therefore require an orphan drug assignment) or will they be beneficial for the larger group of idiopathic PD or atypical parkinsonian disorders? It seems unlikely that these broad groups will all respond to the same drug unless there are shared downstream disease mechanisms. One may even have to differentiate among mutations within <italic>GBA</italic> due to the effect a specific mutation has on the protein. For example, the affinity of chaperones to a mutated enzyme may be different depending on the mutation. Furthermore, a new drug that facilitates protein function may fail in patients with null mutations who do not express any protein. The term &#x0201c;super precision medicine&#x0201d; has been used to capture this phenomenon. To be able to make the most out of clinical trial data, future clinical trials will benefit from pretrial genetic adjustment or, at the minimum, post-trial adjustment, and analysis for failed trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>].</p><p id="Par49">However, in addition to addressing the purely scientific aspects, success in drug development also depends on funding opportunities for late preclinical development phases which are significantly more expensive than early-stage discovery. Experience shows that promising ideas have often failed in this &#x0201c;Valley of Death&#x0201d; (a term coined by former NIH director, Elias Zerhouni) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. Feasible regulatory frameworks and efficient data-sharing ecosystems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>] that also ensure ethical leadership and governance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>] as well as new funding instruments (for example, similar to the recently initated public-private partnership set up to boost research and drug development in infectious diseases and thereby to address market failures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]) will facilitate drug development.</p><p id="Par50">Raising awareness and educating the community, including physicians, patients, and caregivers, will be an important step towards successful future studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]<bold>.</bold> Advancing precision medicine will not only shift current reactive approaches to proactive detection and prevention, but will also help the next generation of scientists develop creative new approaches for detecting, measuring, and treating Parkinson&#x02019;s disease.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic Supplementary Material</title><sec id="Sec17"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13311_2020_920_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><label>ESM 1</label><caption><p>(PDF 458&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>Open Access funding provided by Projekt DEAL. We thank Ms. Amanda K. Chan for her careful work editing the manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Required Author Forms</title><p id="Par51"><xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Disclosure forms</xref> provided by the authors are available with the online version of this artic</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>S. Schneider was supported by LMU Clinician Scientist Programme, the Ara Parseghian Medical Research Fund, and the Verum Stiftung. R. Alcalay research is funded by the NIH, DoD, Parkinson&#x02019;s Foundation, and the Micheal J. Fox Foundation. He received consultation fees from Sanofi, Roche, Janssen, and Restorbio.</p></notes><notes><title>Compliance with Ethical Standards</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p id="Par52">Dr. Alcalay reports receiving consultation fees from Genzyme/Sanofi, Roche, Janssen, and ResTORbio.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global, regional, and national burden of Parkinson's disease</collab></person-group><article-title>1990-2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016</article-title><source>The Lancet Neurology</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30287051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abrahams E, President | Personalized Medicine Coalition Personalized Medicine: The Changing Landscape of Health Care; Key Note lecture, The 2nd Biomarker Meeting in Personalized Reproductive Medicine Valencia, Spain [www.comtecmed.com/biomarker/2014/Uploads/Editor/PDF/ppt/Edward%20Abrahams_Key%20Note%20Lecture.pdf]2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juengst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Settersten</surname><given-names>RA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>From "Personalized" to "Precision" Medicine: The Ethical and Social Implications of Rhetorical Reform in Genomic Medicine</article-title><source>Hastings Cent Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27649826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27649826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manolio</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Finding the missing heritability of complex diseases</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>461</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19812666?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Usefulness of Genetic Testing in PD and PD Trials: A Balanced Review</article-title><source>J Park Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>215</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nalls</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blauwendraat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallerga</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel risk loci, causal insights, and heritable risk for Parkinson's disease: a meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies</article-title><source>The Lancet Neurology</source><year>2019</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31701892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31701892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandres-Ciga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Diez-Fairen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of Parkinson's disease: An introspection of its journey towards precision medicine</article-title><source>Neurobiology of disease</source><year>2020</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>104782</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31991247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31991247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalls</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallgrimsdottir</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies identifies 17 new Parkinson's disease risk loci</article-title><source>Nature genetics</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28892059?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28892059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostaszewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrating pathways of Parkinson's disease in a molecular interaction map</article-title><source>Mol Neurobiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23832570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23832570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moufawad El Achkar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient-Customized Oligonucleotide Therapy for a Rare Genetic Disease</article-title><source>The New England journal of medicine</source><year>2019</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>1644</fpage><lpage>1652</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31597037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31597037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nusinersen as a therapeutic agent for spinal muscular atrophy</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J</source><year>2020</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32233169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leavitt</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Landwehrmeyer</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Targeting Huntingtin Expression in Patients with Huntington's Disease</article-title><source>The New England journal of medicine</source><year>2019</year><volume>380</volume><fpage>2307</fpage><lpage>2316</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31059641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31059641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress in the genetic analysis of Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Human molecular genetics</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>R215</fpage><lpage>R218</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31518392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31518392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrado</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular Neuroimaging of the Dopamine Transporter as a Patient Enrichment Biomarker for Clinical Trials for Early Parkinson's Disease</article-title><source>Clin Transl Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30706986?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30706986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Siderowf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Parkinson's progression markers initiative (PPMI) - establishing a PD biomarker cohort</article-title><source>Ann Clin Transl Neurol</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1460</fpage><lpage>1477</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30564614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30564614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polymeropoulos</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavedan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutation in the alpha-synuclein gene identified in families with Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>2045</fpage><lpage>2047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9197268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ala30Pro mutation in the gene encoding alpha-synuclein in Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9462735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarranz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alegre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Esteban</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The new mutation, E46K, of alpha-synuclein causes Parkinson and Lewy body dementia</article-title><source>Ann Neurol</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14755719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14755719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appel-Cresswell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilarino-Guell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Encarnacion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alpha-synuclein p.H50Q, a novel pathogenic mutation for Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23457019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23457019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesage</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anheim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Letournel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>G51D alpha-synuclein mutation causes a novel parkinsonian-pyramidal syndrome</article-title><source>Annals of neurology</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23526723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23526723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">MDSGene Websitte wmo. Accessed Aug 8, 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First-in-human assessment of PRX002, an anti-alpha-synuclein monoclonal antibody, in healthy volunteers</article-title><source>Movement disorders : official journal of the Movement Disorder Society</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27886407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jankovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Safirstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety and Tolerability of Multiple Ascending Doses of PRX002/RG7935, an Anti-alpha-Synuclein Monoclonal Antibody, in Patients With Parkinson Disease: A Randomized Clinical Trial</article-title><source>JAMA Neurol</source><year>2018</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1206</fpage><lpage>1214</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29913017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29913017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weihofen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of an aggregate-selective, human-derived alpha-synuclein antibody BIIB054 that ameliorates disease phenotypes in Parkinson's disease models</article-title><source>Neurobiology of disease</source><year>2019</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30381260?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30381260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preclinical development of a high affinity alpha-synuclein antibody, MEDI1341, that can enter the brain, sequester extracellular alpha-synuclein and attenuate alpha-synuclein spreading in vivo</article-title><source>Neurobiology of disease</source><year>2019</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>104582</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31445162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31445162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The small molecule alpha-synuclein misfolding inhibitor, NPT200-11, produces multiple benefits in an animal model of Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>16165</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30385782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30385782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteasome-targeted nanobodies alleviate pathology and functional decline in an alpha-synuclein-based Parkinson's disease model</article-title><source>NPJ Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>25</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30155513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30155513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kantor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagliafierro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Downregulation of SNCA Expression by Targeted Editing of DNA Methylation: A Potential Strategy for Precision Therapy in PD</article-title><source>Mol Ther</source><year>2018</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2638</fpage><lpage>2649</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30266652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heras-Garvin A, Stefanova N. MSA: From basic mechanisms to experimental therapeutics. Parkinsonism &#x00026; related disorders 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Falchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phenotype, genotype, and worldwide genetic penetrance of LRRK2-associated Parkinson's disease: a case-control study</article-title><source>Lancet neurol</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18539534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lim SY, Tan AH, Ahmad-Annuar A, et al. Parkinson's disease in the Western Pacific Region. The Lancet Neurology 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozelius</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthil</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders-Pullman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LRRK2 G2019S as a cause of Parkinson's disease in Ashkenazi Jews</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>354</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16436782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16436782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaleel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LRRK2 phosphorylates moesin at threonine-558: characterization of how Parkinson's disease mutants affect kinase activity</article-title><source>The Biochemical journal</source><year>2007</year><volume>405</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17447891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17447891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atashrazm</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzamko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LRRK2 inhibitors and their potential in the treatment of Parkinson's disease: current perspectives</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27799832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27799832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blauwendraat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kia</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Frequency of Loss of Function Variants in LRRK2 in Parkinson Disease</article-title><source>JAMA Neurol</source><year>2018</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1416</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30039155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30039155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuji</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Flagella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of selective LRRK2 kinase inhibition on nonhuman primate lung</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>273ra215</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baptista MAS, Kalpana M; Barrett, T.; Bryce, D.K.; Ellis, M.; Estrada, A.A.; Fell, M.J.; Fiske, B.K.; Fuji, R.N.; et al.. LRRK2 kinase inhibitors induce a reversible effect in the lungs of non-human primates with no measurable pulmonary deficits. bioRxiv, 390815 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Whiffin NA, Irina M; Kleinman, A.; Marshall, J.L.; Minikel, E.V.; Goodrich, J.K.; Quaife, N.; Cole, J.B.; et al. Human loss-of-function variants suggest that partial LRRK2 inhibition is a safe therapeutic strategy for Parkinson&#x02019;s disease. bioRxiv 2019; 10.1101/561472.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domingos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2) for the treatment of Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Future Med Chem</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1953</fpage><lpage>1977</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31517532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31517532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA Therapeutics: How Far Have We Gone?</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>1157</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31342441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31342441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>d'Azzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tifft</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lysosomal storage diseases</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>27</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30275469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30275469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Delic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LRRK2 Antisense Oligonucleotides Ameliorate alpha-Synuclein Inclusion Formation in a Parkinson's Disease Mouse Model</article-title><source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28918051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28918051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sardi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedarbaum</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brundin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted Therapies for Parkinson's Disease: From Genetics to the Clinic</article-title><source>Movement disorders : official journal of the Movement Disorder Society</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>684</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29704272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foroud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel recruitment strategy to enrich for LRRK2 mutation carriers</article-title><source>Mol Genet Genomic Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26436106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26436106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.centogene.com/company/article/centogene-and-denali-therapeutics-announce-strategic-collaboration-to-recruit-lrrk2-patients-for-cli.html">https://www.centogene.com/company/article/centogene-and-denali-therapeutics-announce-strategic-collaboration-to-recruit-lrrk2-patients-for-cli.html</ext-link>, accessed: 24th July, 2019 [online].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kuusimaki T, Korpela J, Pekkonen E, Martikainen MH, Antonini A, Kaasinen V. Deep brain stimulation for monogenic Parkinson's disease: a systematic review. Journal of Neurology 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan-Or</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Giladi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozovski</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genotype-phenotype correlations between GBA mutations and Parkinson disease risk and onset</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2008</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>2277</fpage><lpage>2283</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18434642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18434642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">den Heijer JM, Cullen VC, Quadri M, et al. A Large-Scale Full GBA1 Gene Screening in Parkinson's Disease in the Netherlands. Mov Disord 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shmueli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Carrier screening for Gaucher disease: lessons for low-penetrance, treatable diseases</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2007</year><volume>298</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1290</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17878420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hruska</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>LaMarca</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gaucher disease: mutation and polymorphism spectrum in the glucocerebrosidase gene (GBA)</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18338393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18338393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalls</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aasly</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multicenter analysis of glucocerebrosidase mutations in Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>1651</fpage><lpage>1661</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19846850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19846850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roshan Lal T, Sidransky E. The Spectrum of Neurological Manifestations Associated with Gaucher Disease. Diseases 2017;5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balwani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcalay</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-specific Parkinson disease risk in GBA mutation carriers: information for genetic counseling</article-title><source>Genetics in medicine : official journal of the American College of Medical Genetics</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22935721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the glucocerebrosidase gene are associated with early-onset Parkinson disease</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2007</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1270</fpage><lpage>1277</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17875915?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17875915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartsaklis</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf Gilbert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of glucocerebrosidase mutations with dementia with lewy bodies</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2009</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19433657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19433657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Next-generation sequencing reveals substantial genetic contribution to dementia with Lewy bodies</article-title><source>Neurobiol dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27312774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27312774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variants associated with Gaucher disease in multiple system atrophy</article-title><source>Ann clin transl neurol</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25909086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25909086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sklerov MK,Un J; Liong, C.; Marder, K.; Pauciulo, M.; Nichols, W.C.; Chung, W.K.; Honig, L.S.; Cortes, E.; Vonsattel, J.P.. Frequency of GBA Variants in Autopsy-proven Multiple System Atrophy. Mov Disord Clin Pract 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segarane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucocerebrosidase mutations in 108 neuropathologically confirmed cases of multiple system atrophy</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19332698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilarino-Guell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucocerebrosidase mutations in diffuse Lewy body disease</article-title><source>Parkinsonism Relat Disord</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20971030?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20971030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goker-Alpan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Giasson</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Eblan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucocerebrosidase mutations are an important risk factor for Lewy body disorders</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2006</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>908</fpage><lpage>910</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16790605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16790605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzulli</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gaucher disease glucocerebrosidase and alpha-synuclein form a bidirectional pathogenic loop in synucleinopathies</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21700325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barkhuizen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Grobler</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in GBA-associated Parkinson's disease--Pathology, presentation and therapies</article-title><source>Neurochem Int</source><year>2016</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26743617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26743617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sardi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Viel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucosylceramide synthase inhibition alleviates aberrations in synucleinopathy models</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>2699</fpage><lpage>2704</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28223512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28223512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterschmitt</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulisevsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Simuni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics of oral venglustat in Parkinson disease patients with a GBA mutation</article-title><source>Mol genet metabol rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>S117</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hitti FL, Yang AI, Gonzalez-Alegre P, Baltuch GH. Human gene therapy approaches for the treatment of Parkinson's disease: An overview of current and completed clinical trials. Parkinsonism &#x00026; Related Disorders 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sardi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Viel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Augmenting CNS glucocerebrosidase activity as a therapeutic strategy for parkinsonism and other Gaucher-related synucleinopathies</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>3537</fpage><lpage>3542</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23297226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23297226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aflaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chaperoning glucocerebrosidase: a therapeutic strategy for both Gaucher disease and Parkinsonism</article-title><source>Neural Regen Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1760</fpage><lpage>1761</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28123414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28123414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maegawa</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tropak</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of ambroxol as an enzyme enhancement agent for Gaucher disease</article-title><source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>23502</fpage><lpage>23516</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19578116?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19578116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalhaes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ambroxol improves lysosomal biochemistry in glucocerebrosidase mutation-linked Parkinson disease cells</article-title><source>Brain : a journal of neurology</source><year>2014</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1481</fpage><lpage>1495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24574503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Migdalska-Richards A, Ko WKD, Li Q, Bezard E, Schapira AHV. Oral ambroxol increases brain glucocerebrosidase activity in a nonhuman primate. Synapse 2017;71.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mullin S, Smith L, Lee K, et al. Ambroxol for the Treatment of Patients With Parkinson Disease With and Without Glucocerebrosidase Gene Mutations: A Nonrandomized, Noncontrolled Trial. JAMA Neurol 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>CRA</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKinley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ambroxol as a novel disease-modifying treatment for Parkinson's disease dementia: protocol for a single-centre, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>BMC Neurol</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>20</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30738426?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30738426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gegg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heales</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucocerebrosidase deficiency in substantia nigra of parkinson disease brains</article-title><source>Annals of neurology</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23034917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23034917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trust hcginNsbSUaCPs.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Institute hcginNsbSLHR.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mTOR Signaling in Growth, Metabolism, and Disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28388417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28388417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New tricks from old dogs join the fight against ageing</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>552</volume><fpage>S57</fpage><lpage>S59</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29239380?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29239380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spilman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Podlutskaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of mTOR by rapamycin abolishes cognitive deficits and reduces amyloid-beta levels in a mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e9979</fpage><?supplied-pmid 20376313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20376313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decressac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mTOR inhibition alleviates L-DOPA-induced dyskinesia in parkinsonian rats</article-title><source>J Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23938307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23938307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ligaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sannaes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pihlstrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep brain stimulation and genetic variability in Parkinson's disease: a review of the literature</article-title><source>NPJ Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>18</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31508488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31508488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Muqit</surname><given-names>MMK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic approaches to enhance PINK1/Parkin mediated mitophagy for the treatment of Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2019</year><volume>705</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30995519?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30995519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">e:Med. Mitochondrial endophenotypes of PD, MitoPD, clinical trial <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sys-med.de/en/demonstrators/mitopd/sp-6/">https://www.sys-med.de/en/demonstrators/mitopd/sp-6/</ext-link> [online]. Accessed 20 Feb.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWitte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Robledo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaacs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rising to the Challenges of Clinical Trial Improvement in Parkinson's Disease</article-title><source>J Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25720445?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25720445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alcalay</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kehoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shorr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correction: Genetic testing for Parkinson disease: current practice, knowledge, and attitudes among US and Canadian movement disorders specialists</article-title><source>Genetics in Medicine: official journal of the American College of Medical Genetics</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>448</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31772350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scahill</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluid and imaging biomarkers for Huntington's disease</article-title><source>Mol Cell Neurosci</source><year>2019</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30807825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30807825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Rumund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AJE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairfoul</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Esselink</surname><given-names>RAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloem</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeek</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>alpha-Synuclein real-time quaking-induced conversion in the cerebrospinal fluid of uncertain cases of parkinsonism</article-title><source>Ann Neurol</source><year>2019</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30801759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30801759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Teil M, Arotcarena ML, Faggiani E, Laferriere F, Bezard E, Dehay B. Targeting alpha-synuclein for PD Therapeutics: A Pursuit on All Fronts. Biomolecules 2020;10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedarbaum</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brundin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Proposed Roadmap for Parkinson's Disease Proof of Concept Clinical Trials Investigating Compounds Targeting Alpha-Synuclein</article-title><source>J Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30400107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30400107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Long G. The Biopharmaceutical Pipeline: Innovative Therapies in Clinical Development. Analysis Group <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.analysisgroupcom/uploadedfiles/content/insights/publishing/the_biopharmaceutical_pipeline_report_2017pdf">https://www.analysisgroupcom/uploadedfiles/content/insights/publishing/the_biopharmaceutical_pipeline_report_2017pdf</ext-link> 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">(PhRMA) PRaMoA. PhRMA SPECIAL 301 SUBMISSION 2009 OVERVIEW. 2009;Special 301 Submission.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leonard H, Blauwendraat C, Krohn L, et al. Genetic variability and potential effects on clinical trial outcomes: perspectives in Parkinson's disease. Journal of Medical Genetics 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ghoda LY, Rosen ST, Kwak LW. The changing investment in translational science by academic medical centers: HOPE in the Valley of Death. J Clin Invest 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blasimme</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vayena</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Data Sharing For Precision Medicine: Policy Lessons And Future Directions</article-title><source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source><year>2018</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29733719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ho CWLA, Ali J, Caals K. Ensuring Trustworthy Use of Artificial Intelligence and Big Data Analytics in Health Insurance. Bull World Health Organ 2020;98:263-269.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>