<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because the data within IPDGC is both broad and deep an important role we play is to assess emerging mutations or variants associated with disease. Clearly, given the investment in time and resources for functional investigation of individual loci or variants, it is critical that these are investigated rigorously. The IPDGC supports this effort in three ways, through the provision of publicly available data, through the assessment of genes/variants upon request (&gt;10 such requests have been addressed by IPDGC), or by assessing variants after they are published. Rare variants in 
 <italic>ADORA1</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> (p.H50Q) [
 <xref rid="ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], 
 <italic>TMEM230</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], 
 <italic>EIF4G1</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> (loss of function variants) [
 <xref rid="ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], 
 <italic>MC1R</italic> (p.R160W) [
 <xref rid="ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], 
 <italic>CHCHD2</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], 
 <italic>ADH1C</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], 
 <italic>ARSA</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and 
 <italic>LRP10</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] were all previously identified to be associated with “monogenic” forms of PD or high risk variants, however none of these results could be replicated in IPDGC data. Additionally common variants in PARK10 [
 <xref rid="ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and multiple other associations with age of onset of PD [
 <xref rid="ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] were not replicated in IPDGC efforts. Similarly we have not been able to replicate the associations between vitamin D and PD [
 <xref rid="ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and the causal relationship between urate levels and PD [
 <xref rid="ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. While false negative replication can be a result of testing extremely rare variants (private mutations or single family) or may reflect population specific alterations, the relatively large sample series available through IPDGC does provide a frame of reference for such associations and suggest that these associations may represent false positives or very rare family-based or population specific effects.
</p>
