<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">The emerging information about the importance of the gut microbiome in human health and disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>, together with the well-established connection between PD and the gut including common and early occurrence of constipation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>, inflammation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, and increased gut membrane permeability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>, have raised the possibility that microorganisms in the gut may play a role in PD pathogenesis and prompted a fast growing literature on studies conducted in humans and animal models
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Every study that has compared the global composition of the gut microbiome in PD vs. controls found it to be significantly altered; in contrast, attempts to identify PD-associated microorganisms have produced inconsistent results
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Low reproducibility has been attributed to small sample sizes (missing true associations due to low power), relaxed statistical thresholds (inflating false-positive results), and publishing without a replication dataset (required for genomic studies). Differences in methods of sample collection, transportation and storage, DNA extraction, sequencing, bioinformatics, and statistics can all contribute to inter-study variations. The choice of taxonomic resolution for analysis (PD has been tested at all levels from phylum to species) and the inconsistent taxonomic assignments and nomenclature used in various reference databases add to the confusion when comparing results. Last but not least is confounding by heterogeneity in the populations that were studied: PD is heterogenous and so is the microbiome. PD subtypes cannot be readily identified; thus, patient populations are inevitably varied. A myriad of factors can affect the microbiome ranging from diet, health, and medication to cultural habits, lifestyles, race, and geography
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
