<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While many studies have suggested that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and Aβ are capable of direct and indirect molecular cross-talks in the brain along with hybrid oligomer formation [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21, 174–179</xref>], few studies have demonstrated that endogenous Aβ and 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn directly interact in cultured cells or 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Specifically, Tsigelny and colleagues reported that 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn and Aβ directly interact in the brains of small (
 <italic>n</italic> = 4) groups of patients with AD, DLB and in APP/
 <italic>α</italic>-syn tg mice (Thy1-APPmut tg [line 41] x PDGFβ-
 <italic>α</italic>-syn tg mice [line D]) using co-immunoprecipitation analyses of membrane fractions. Although immunoreactive bands at ∼28, ∼40 and ∼70 kDa labeled as 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn dimers, trimers and pentamers by the authors were readily detected by western blotting using unspecified 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn antibodies in the membrane fractions of AD, DLB and APP/
 <italic>α</italic>-syn tg brain tissue, only monomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn (or Aβ) and no oligomeric species were identified by coimmunoprecipitation. By contrast, two independent studies from the Lesné group failed to observe putative 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn/Aβ hybrid species in AD brain lysates and in double transgenic APP/
 <italic>α</italic>Syn mice (PDGFβ-APPmut tg [line J20] ×PrP-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn tg mice [line TgI2.2]) using non-denaturing dot blotting following size exclusion chromatography with several monoclonal 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn antibodies (LB509, 4B12 and 4D6) or using coimmunoprecipitation with the LB509 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn antibody [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19, 108</xref>]. All three studies used the monoclonal antibody 6E10 to detect human Aβ. Overall, these findings are not consistent and additional work is needed to confirm the presence of endogenous 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn/Aβ hybrid assemblies and to assess whether differences in the approaches and/or in the biological specimens might be responsible for these diverging observations.
</p>
