<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To assess whether Aβ and 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn aggregation co-occurs or whether a potential cross-talk between these two amyloid precursors, Bassil and coworkers (2020) injected mouse 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn preformed fibrils (
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mPFFs) into young adult 5XFAD mice harboring amyloid plaques. The presence of Aβ deposits enhanced 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn pathology and spreading throughout the brain [
 <xref rid="ref180" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. Mechanistically, the injection of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mPFFs altered APP processing favoring Aβ production resulting from a decrease in ADAM-10 protein abundance coupled to an increase in presenilin-2 and nicastrin, two members of the 
 <italic>γ</italic>-secretase complex. These findings have led the authors to suggest a “feed-forward” mechanism whereby Aβ plaques potentiate 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn seeding and spreading over time [
 <xref rid="ref180" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. It is however worth noting that soluble APP-
 <italic>α</italic> (sAPP
 <italic>α</italic>) levels were remarkably unchanged despite a  50% reduction in ADAM-10, a proponent candidate of 
 <italic>α</italic>-secretase activity, arguing against an overall decrease in 
 <italic>α</italic>-secretase activity. In addition, these putative alterations of APP processing induced by 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn were not observed in two other recent studies examining the interaction between Aβ and 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19, 20</xref>]. Furthermore, these latter two studies actually reported effects of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn on Aβ deposition opposite to that described by Bassil and colleagues, whereby overexpression of either mutant human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>A30P</sup> or 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn
 <sup>WT</sup> in two distinct APP transgenic mice led to a reduction in Aβ burden [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19, 20</xref>]. Both independent groups validated these 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> findings with 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> approaches relying on thioflavin-T analyses with recombinant proteins [
 <xref rid="ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and relying on measurement of on-pathway amyloid oligomers using conformation-specific OC antibodies [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Of particular interest, the forebrain abundance of o-
 <italic>α</italic>Syn detected with oligomeric 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-specific antibody Syn33 was highest in bigenic APP/
 <italic>α</italic>Syn mice when Aβ deposits were the lowest [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Furthermore, ablation of the 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> gene encoding for 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn in the same APP transgenic model led Khan and colleagues to witness a bidirectional effect of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn on Aβ deposition, by which the genetic removal of 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn elevated Aβ deposition [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] reminiscent of prior work by the Zheng group [
 <xref rid="ref181" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. While differences in APP transgenic mouse models could in principle account for these differences, it is more likely that the nature of the 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn molecules introduced in these various models is contributing to the diverging observations. Indeed, while 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn-mPFFs are created by sonicating long, pre-formed fibrils are injected in young mice, transgene-derived expressions of human 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn used by the Meyer-Luehmann and Lesné groups do not induce 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn fibrillization. Therefore, it is likely that the crosstalk between Aβ and 
 <italic>α</italic>Syn differs based on the conformational nature of each component, i.e., oligomers vs. fibrils, and with dramatically distinct functional consequences.
</p>
