<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Mounting evidence demonstrates the role of genetic predispositions in PD pathogenesis, and the prevalence and penetrance of each variant start to emerge. Typically, it appears that the most common PD gene variants found in the global population have the lowest penetrance. On the other hand, most penetrant mutations are rare, and most often associated with familial PD. Variants on at least 16 PARK genes, referred to as “causal” because they instigate a relatively high familial inheritance of PD or early-onset PD symptoms, have been identified and are highlighted in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147">147</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR168">168</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178">178</xref>
 </sup>. To estimate the frequency of these mutations in the Parkinson’s population, we examined the published reports from 50 epidemiological studies. The high penetrance and hereditary nature of causal mutations can amplify their occurrence in specific ethnic groups (i.e., Japanese
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">134</xref>
 </sup>, Chinese
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>
 </sup>, and Ashkenazi Jews
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>). However, globally our analysis shows that the presence of any known causal PD mutation is rare, occurring in less than 2% of the PD population (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). The two most common mutated genes associated with familial PD are 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> and 
 <italic>PRKN</italic> and are reported in 0.7% and 0.3% of all the people showing PD symptoms, respectively (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). However, the frequency of at least some risk variants (OR &gt; 1.5), which we measured in a large genomic data set including 25,243 total PD cases (combination of NHGRI-EBI catalog and 24 independent genetic studies), appears higher than in the epidemiological studies, which would tend to focus on the variants with the highest penetrance. For example, 
 <italic>LRRK2 G2385R</italic> is present in &gt;10% of the PD patients and 
 <italic>PRKN</italic> exon rearrangements are present in &gt;3% of the patients (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Our analysis also highlights that known mutations in familial PARK genes confer a broad range of risks to develop PD symptoms. 
 <italic>PRKN(exon rearrangements)</italic>, 
 <italic>LRRK2(G2019S)</italic>, 
 <italic>GBA (L444P, N370S)</italic>, and 
 <italic>CHCHD2(P2L)</italic> appear to be the most penetrant mutations, increasing the chances of getting PD symptoms by up to a factor 14, 10, 8 and 5, respectively (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). However, these penetrant variants are relatively rare, occurring in ~4%, 2%, 5%, and 2% of the PD population, respectively (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Overall, the data tends to confirm that the most prevalent variants are less penetrant (See DJ-1 variants for example in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Recent GWAS allowed for the detection of common low penetrance mutations associated with PD. To date, over 44 novel risk loci have been identified and associated with sporadic PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR179">179</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">180</xref>
 </sup>. Mutations within these risk loci can be disease modulating (OR &gt; 1) or protective (OR &lt; 1) for PD (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). Despite GWAS and genetic studies pointing to several novel molecular targets and pathways in sporadic PD, many of them remain unconfirmed. The presence of mutations on a single risk locus often poses a low risk for disease, yet mutations in multiple risk loci can collectively be disease modulating. The lack of a preponderant single definitive causative gene for most PD patients is a challenge for both the design of experimental models and the discovery of well-targeted treatments. Novel approaches for disease modeling in vitro are required to unravel the polygenic and complex mechanisms underlying sporadic disease successfully. Brain tissue engineering from patient-derived stem cells provides a unique opportunity to fulfill such need.
</p>
