<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The importance of the dissection of genetic risk in non-European ancestry populations has led us to invest more in establishing research in underrepresented groups. With the support of the Michael J Fox Foundation for Parkinson’s Research, the IPDGC has initiated large efforts in South East Asia and China, and across Africa. We are also working closely with collections centered in India (LUX-GIANT; Luxembourg-German-Indian Alliance on Neurodegenerative diseases and Therapeutics) and the well-established effort LARGE-PD (Latin American Research Consortium on the Genetics of Parkinson’s Disease; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://large-pd.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://large-pd.org/</ext-link>), led by Dr. Ignacio Mata (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-10-jpd191854-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). To facilitate research across populations we have been working with Illumina Inc. to create an affordable genotyping array that is capable of maximizing information across different ancestral groups. As with the previous arrays developed by us this commercial array will include a large number of neurological disease relevant variants; however, this time the array will be placed on the backbone of popular genotyping platforms such as the Multi-Ethnic Genotyping Array (MEGA) or the Global Screening Array (GSA) creating the power to assess both common and rare variants in diverse populations. Thus, in the first instance our approach will be to facilitate the generation of large-scale and unified genotyping data across diverse populations, with the explicit goals of 1) identifying genetic risk for PD in each population, 2) determining the differences in genetic architecture of PD between populations, and 3) combining data to fine map genetic risk loci. A limitation in this space is the lack of reference whole genome sequence data in certain groups, thus limiting the capacity to capture the genetic diversity in these underserved groups; we will contribute to filling this need by generating whole genome sequence in select ancestral groups.
</p>
