<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene (OMIM ID: 608397) spanning at least 1 Mb on chromosome 8p23.2 [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] is considered to be an inhibitor of complement activation and a regulator of inflammation in the developing central nervous system and highly expressed in the central nervous system [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The complement cascade not only involves defending against pathogens in the immune system but also plays a crucial role in synaptic pruning and synaptic plasticity [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], which seem to be involved in cognitive functions and psychiatric disorders [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A previous 
 <italic>GWAS</italic> [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] suggested that 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene was significantly associated with PD risk. In addition, a complete exon sequencing in Spanish population showed a link between mutations in the 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene and familial Parkinson's disease [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Based on the previous studies and the close relationship between 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene with complement pathway and inflammatory response, we hypothesized that 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> may be a candidate gene for idiopathic Parkinson's disease. The 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> variant rs10503253, the SNP, has been reported to be associated with cognitive function and executive ability in healthy individuals [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Another polymorphism of rs12681349 within 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> has been explored in Iranian population [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The rs1983474 within 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> has been revealed to be connected with variation in urinary C-telopeptide of type II collagen (u CTX-II) levels in patients with osteoarthritis [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The above three SNPs are all missense mutation points of 
 <italic>CSMD1</italic> gene (NCBI: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_ref.cgi?locusId=64478" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_ref.cgi?locusId=64478</ext-link>). However, they have never been studied in Chinese Parkinson's disease population.
</p>
