<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Parkinson's disease (PD) is a progressive neurodegenerative condition pathologically characterized by the presence of α‐synuclein (αsyn) containing Lewy bodies.
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> The defining motor symptoms of PD are associated with the loss of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra, but patients can also suffer numerous nonmotor symptoms that include cognitive impairment. The disease affects more than 7 million individuals worldwide,
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> and the rising incidence of PD will increase the burden of this incurable disease on healthcare systems.
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> The current therapy for PD provides only symptomatic relief with no therapeutics demonstrated to attenuate disease progression, although the potential for drug discovery and/or repurposing is increasing as research continues to elucidate the pathways underlying PD pathogenesis.
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> PD is predominantly considered an idiopathic disease, but recent studies support a much stronger influence of genetic determinants in the idiopathic cases of PD (10%–30% heritability).
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Among the ~90 genetic loci associated with PD, the 
 <italic>GBA</italic> locus is the most common genetic risk factor with mutations in 2.3% to 9.4% (11%–31% in Ashkenazi Jews) of PD cases,
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> with ethnicity playing a large role in determining the risk range.
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> However, the estimated lifetime risk ratio of a 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutant carrier developing PD is only 21% to 29%, consistent with the variable penetrance of the 
 <italic>GBA</italic> coding variants.
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> Furthermore, recent observations identified reduced 
 <italic>GBA</italic>‐encoded protein, β‐glucocerebrosidase (GCase) activity in patients with idiopathic PD (IPD) in the absence of loss‐of‐function (LoF) 
 <italic>GBA</italic> mutations.
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="mds28144-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> Collectively, these observations are consistent with regulatory impacts on 
 <italic>GBA</italic> expression and other modifier genes contributing to PD development.
</p>
