<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="jpd-10-jpd201965-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Fig. 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Proposed model of 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn assemblies in health (‘multimers’) and disease (‘oligomers’). Schematic of one cell and extracellular space. Under physiological conditions 
   <italic>(in blue, bottom left)</italic>, 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn comes off the ribosome as a soluble unfolded monomer (blue ‘
   <italic>α</italic>Syn’), which forms helical monomers (blue circle) upon getting in contact with vesicle membranes. Helical monomers at membranes may assemble into metastable physiological multimers (low-
   <italic>n</italic> assemblies in blue) that eventually fall apart again, initiating a new cycle. Under stress of pathological conditions (
   <italic>in pink shading, starting bottom middle</italic>), excess of unfolded or helical membrane-bound 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn has been proposed to be the starting point for pathological aggregation into oligomers including dimers, tetramers, annular protofibrils and larger oligomers. We propose that two distinct misfolded states of 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn lead to two distinct aggregation pathways, one forming amyloid fibrils (ON pathway; A11
   <sup>–</sup>/OC
   <sup>+</sup>), and one forming large non-fibrillar 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomers (OFF pathway, A11+/OC
   <sup>–</sup>). Endogenous oligomeric 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn are likely to be enriched for β-sheet motifs. The endpoint of intracellular aggregation is the so-called Lewy body (
   <italic>top left</italic>). Mixed intracellular aggregates have also been reported in particular with tau (
   <italic>red baton</italic>), although the exact 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn oligomer interacting with tau is unknown (indicated by ‘?’). Cross-talks between 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn species and huntingtin oligomers (Htt, 
   <italic>orange hexagons</italic>) have also been advanced but require confirmation. Oligomers of 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn may be released into the extracellular space by an ill-defined mechanism (
   <italic>right</italic>). There, they may further aggregate, which may include the formation of mixed aggregates, with amyloid-β peptides (Aβ, 
   <italic>purple stars</italic>) in particular with which 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn can form hybrid 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn/Aβ oligomers. Extracellular aggregates may be taken up by cells and released into the cytosol where they may in turn ‘seed’ 
   <italic>α</italic>Syn aggregation. Release, uptake and seeding of intracellular pathology might be underlying the phenomenon of αSyn spread and release might correspond to a possible protective mechanism adopted by cells to maintain cellular proteostasis.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="jpd-10-jpd201965-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
