<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes notes-type="funding-information">
 <title>Funding</title>
 <p>Study data were provided by the following sources: The Mayo Clinic Alzheimers Disease Genetic Studies, led by Dr. Nilüfer Ertekin-Taner and Dr. Steven G. Younkin, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, FL using samples from the Mayo Clinic Study of Aging, the Mayo Clinic Alzheimers Disease Research Center, and the Mayo Clinic Brain Bank. Data collection was supported through funding by NIA Grants P50 AG016574, R01 AG032990, U01 AG046139, R01 AG018023, U01 AG006576, U01 AG006786, R01 AG025711, R01 AG017216, R01 AG003949, NINDS Grant R01 NS080820, CurePSP Foundation, and support from Mayo Foundation. Study data includes samples collected through the Sun Health Research Institute Brain and Body Donation Program of Sun City, Arizona. The Brain and Body Donation Program is supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (U24 NS072026 National Brain and Tissue Resource for Parkinsons Disease and Related Disorders), the National Institute on Aging (P30 AG19610 Arizona Alzheimers Disease Core Center), the Arizona Department of Health Services (contract 211002, Arizona Alzheimers Research Center), the Arizona Biomedical Research Commission (contracts 4001, 0011, 05–901 and 1001 to the Arizona Parkinson's Disease Consortium) and the Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinsons Research. Autopsy materials used in this study were in part obtained from the University of Washington Neuropathology Core, which is supported by the Alzheimer's Disease Research Center (AG05136), the Adult Changes in Thought Study (AG006781), the Pacific Udall Center 3P50NS062684, and DOD HU00011920008. Research in OA lab was supported by the Danish Alzheimer’s research foundation, the Mærsk-Møller Foundation, the Jascha Foundation, and Aarhus University Graduate School Health. Research conducted in AN lab was supported by PROMEMO—Center for Proteins in Memory, a Center of Excellence funded by the Danish National Research Foundation (Grant DNRF133).</p>
</notes>
