<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As for the risk factors for PD in MENASA countries, age and male sex are risk factors for PD [
 <xref rid="ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] (see 
 <xref rid="jpd-10-jpd191751-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), as seen in Western countries [
 <xref rid="ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Environmental risk factors associated with PD in the United States and Western Europe include pesticide exposure [
 <xref rid="ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], well-water use, rural-dwelling and farming [
 <xref rid="ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and head injury [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], but these risk factors have yet to be ascertained in MENASA countries. Caffeine and tobacco product usage has been associated with a lower risk of PD but this also remains to be proven in non-Western populations [
 <xref rid="ref024" ref-type="bibr">24, 25</xref>]. There are few studies on environmental risk factors for PD in MENASA countries. In many Arab countries, a large proportion of the population lives in rural regions where farming is ubiquitous. As in some studies in Western countries, one study in Egypt found a higher prevalence of PD among rural dwellers [
 <xref rid="ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. One hypothesis is that a large proportion of the population chews on the leaves of Catha edulis (“Khat”) that has been theorized to cause dopaminergic cell toxicity and may be related to the development of parkinsonism [
 <xref rid="ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, another study by the same group in the Assiut and Qena governates of Egypt found a higher prevalence in urban areas, where industrial toxins from factories may drain into the Nile river [
 <xref rid="ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This finding agrees with a large study in the USA (using a comprehensive population-based health care database) that demonstrated a substantially higher prevalence and incidence of PD in urban areas rather than in rural areas [
 <xref rid="ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In another example, a small case-control study in Uttar Pradesh, India found a higher prevalence of self-reported exposure to chemicals and well water drinking among PD cases, but not other factors identified in Western countries [
 <xref rid="ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. On the other hand, a case-control study in Eastern India identified the following risk factors for PD: family history of PD, pesticide exposure, exposure to toxins other than pesticides and herbicides, and rural living [
 <xref rid="ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. These and other data suggest that there may be some shared environmental risk factors for PD in MENASA countries, but there are likely differences as well. Indeed, given the known mediation of environmental risk factors for diseases by genetic factors [
 <xref rid="ref031" ref-type="bibr">31–33</xref>], environmental risk factors for PD identified in Western countries are not necessarily generalizable to other regions of the world, and further studies in MENASA countries are essential.
</p>
