<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding genetic determinants or contributors to PD in MENASA countries, much work has focused on the high prevalence of the G2019S LRRK2 gene mutation in North African countries. While in most populations, mutations in the LRRK2 gene account for only about 1% of sporadic cases of PD, this mutation is more common in Ashkenazi Jews [
 <xref rid="ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and is especially common in the North African Berbers of Morocco, Tunisia, and Algeria [
 <xref rid="ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A small study suggested that this mutation is relatively prevalent in a Northern region of Egypt [
 <xref rid="ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] but may be less common in other regions of the country [
 <xref rid="ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], possibly due to the lower prevalence of Berbers in that region. On the other hand, G2019S LRRK2 mutations were not found to be common in one other Arab country where this has been studied, namely Saudi Arabia [
 <xref rid="ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Otherwise, data on the genetic epidemiology of PD in MENASA countries are limited. Populations of the MENASA countries are significantly under-represented in genome-wide association studies (GWAS) [
 <xref rid="ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. In many MENASA countries, especially Arab countries, there are high rates of consanguinity among first cousins [
 <xref rid="ref040" ref-type="bibr">40, 41</xref>]. Indeed, much insight into PD genetics has been gained from studying families originating in MENASA countries including Jordan [
 <xref rid="ref042" ref-type="bibr">42–44</xref>], Sudan [
 <xref rid="ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and Palestine [
 <xref rid="ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Thus, the high rates of consanguinity in some MENASA countries, combined with the heterogeneous genetic constitution of the MENASA population that is distinct from Western countries, provide great impetus to study the genetic epidemiology of PD in MENASA countries [
 <xref rid="ref047" ref-type="bibr">47, 48</xref>].
</p>
