<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">Clathrin-mediated endocytosis (CME) was the first mechanism identified for DAT regulation and is best characterized by PKC activation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>, which robustly drives the loss of surface DAT in heterologous systems and striatal tissues
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. New data suggests PKC activation may disrupt DAT interactions with Rit2, and with cytosolic nonreceptor tyrosine kinase (TNK2, formerly called activated p21CDC42 kinase; ACK1), that normally stabilize DAT in the plasma membrane
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. AIM-100 may also inhibit TNK2 and lower surface DAT
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. The effect of PKC can be arrested by blocking CME. For example, dynamin interacts with clathrin-coated pits and plays an important role in vesicle budding. Expression of dynamin p.K33E, a dominant-negative form of dynamin, or pharmacological inhibition of dynamin activity prevents phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA)-induced loss of surface DAT in cell lines and 
 <italic>ex-vivo</italic> striatal slices, respectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. Down regulation of clathrin heavy chain by siRNA or acute inhibition of clathrin function by pitstop2 prevents PMA-mediated DAT internalization in DAT expressing cell lines
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. However, dynamin is involved in both clathrin-dependent and clathrin-independent pathways including RhoA- and caveolar-mediated endocytosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Clathrin is also critically involved in a broad range of endocytic pathways including sorting of ubiquitinated proteins for lysosomal degradation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, indirect regulation of clathrin and dynamin on PKC-mediated DAT internalization cannot be excluded. DAT complexes with Eps15, a component of clathrin-coated pits, in heterologous systems and midbrain neuronal cultures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. However, immunogold-labeling has failed to observed DAT localization in clathrin-coated pits in the axonal terminals and soma of dopaminergic neurons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. Assessing DAT’s interaction with clathrin and scaffold proteins, such as adaptor protein-2, in endogenously expressing systems may further clarify their role in DAT endocytosis.
</p>
