<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The QPN’s success in building a robust patient registry with associated epidemiological and clinical data and in establishing standardized processes for facilitating research projects has served as the model for the creation of a Canadian national PD network. The recently funded Canadian Open Parkinson Network (C-OPN) will involve 8 major movement disorder centres across 4 Canadian provinces: the Hotchkiss Brain Institute and Movement Disorders program at the University of Calgary; the McGill Parkinson Program at the MNI and Montreal General Hospital (McGill University); L’Unité des Troubles du Mouvement André Barbeau at the Université de Montréal; La Clinique des Troubles du Mouvement du Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Québec at the CHU de Québec-Université Laval; the Parkinson Research Consortium (University of Ottawa); the Movement Disorders Centre at Toronto Western Hospital (University of Toronto); the Movement Disorders Program at the University of Alberta; and the Pacific Parkinson’s Research Centre at the University of British Columbia. C-OPN aims to create an open-access panel of patient-derived PD stem cell lines with associated clinical and imaging data, in partnership with the Open Science iPSC Platform and C-BIGR at the MNI. Similarly to QPN, C-OPN has 3 major research initiatives. First, C-OPN will establish a national registry of patients with PD and PD-related disorders containing comprehensive longitudinal clinical information to facilitate patient recruitment for large-scale projects or clinical trials. Second, C-OPN will set up an anonymized database for neuropsychological information, imaging data, and second-generation wearable device data. Third, C-OPN will store biological samples in an open biorepository from which genetic and cellular samples and data will be processed, curated, and made available to the scientific community in Canada and beyond. The goals of C-OPN are to find new technological platforms for imaging and wearable data, identify biomarkers and platforms for drug discovery, and ultimately develop novel stratification methods based on multidimensional data to better predict disease trajectory and inform treatment strategies for PD.</p>
