<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Background:</title>
  <p>Understanding the regional needs and available healthcare resources to treat Parkinson’s disease (PD) is essential to plan appropriate future priorities. The International Parkinson and Movement Disorder Society (MDS) Task Force for the Middle East was established to raise awareness and promote education across the region on PD and other movement disorders. Broadly, the task force encompasses the countries of the Middle East but has included North Africa and South Asia as well (MENASA).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Objective:</title>
  <p>To create a list of needs and priorities in the advancement of PD in MENASA countries based on consensuses generated by the MDS task force for the Middle East.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Methods:</title>
  <p>A Strengths Weaknesses-Opportunities-Threats (SWOT) analysis was conducted by the task force members to generate consensus about PD care this region.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p>Eight overarching principles emerged for the consensus statement on current needs: more movement disorders specialists, multidisciplinary care, accurate epidemiologic data, educational programs, availability of drugs, and availability of more advanced therapy, enhanced health care resources and infrastructure, and greater levels of awareness within the general population and among health care professionals.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec specific-use="heading-level-1">
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p>This pilot study sheds light on unmet needs for providing care to people with PD in the MENASA region. These data offer directions on priorities to increase awareness of PD, to develop better infrastructure for research and management of PD, to foster healthcare policy discussions for PD and to provide educational opportunities within these countries.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
