<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3">
 <label>Fig. 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Using brain cells generated from patient-derived iPSC to study PD in vitro.</title>
  <p>Data from this figure was extracted and analyzed from 67 iPSC-PD studies, refer to “Methods”. 
   <bold>a</bold> A schematic pipeline of in vitro disease modeling and preclinical drug screening with patient-derived brain cells. 
   <bold>b</bold> The number of iPSC studies that used human neuronal lines with corresponding mutations on specific genes associated with PD (also refer to Table 
   <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Categories in bold and darker bars represent the total number of studies examining that gene. 
   <bold>c</bold> The types of control and PD cell lines are displayed as the percentage of total cell lines. 
   <bold>d</bold> The number of PD and control cell lines used in iPSC-PD studies. Data presented as the mean ± SEM. 
   <bold>e</bold> Donor cell types and reprogramming methods used in hiPSC-PD studies. N/R indicates that details were not reported in these studies. 
   <bold>f</bold> The diagram summarizes the different type of tissue culture trajectories used to differentiate cultures of iPSCs into midbrain neurons. Line thickness and percentages (in the “neurons” box) represent the proportion of studies in corresponding trajectories. The percentage displayed for each intermediate stage shows the proportion of studies that uses the corresponding cell type. EB embryoid bodies, NPCs neural progenitors 
   <bold>g</bold> Neural induction duration indicates the number of days (average + range) required for the generation of terminal neural precursor cell types (last stage before neuronal maturation: NPCs, neurospheres, rosettes, or EZ spheres depending the stages that were skipped) from iPSC. 
   <bold>h</bold> Neural maturation duration indicates the average number of weeks from terminal neural precursor cell type (NPCs or previous stage if NPC stage was skipped) to the neuronal cells used for phenotypic evaluation. 
   <bold>i</bold> Small molecules and growth factors were used at various stages of midbrain dopaminergic neuronal differentiation. Data presented as the percentage of hiPSC-PD studies that report the corresponding factors in the tissue culture media composition. 
   <bold>j</bold> The proportions (mean + SEM) of neurons (bIII-Tub/DAPI) and midbrain dopamine neurons (TH/DAPI) in cultures vary between differentiation protocols and trajectories. Each data point is the average percentage reported in a single study (
   <italic>n</italic> = 33 independent studies, refer to “Methods”). The first column labeled as “all” groups all the studies regardless of their differentiation trajectories. Relevant immunohistochemistry quantification was not reported in studies using neural differentiation trajectories A and D.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41531_2020_110_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1216" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
