<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In parallel, integration of the currently available microbiome data in PD would allow for the discovery of robust microbial associations and confounder adjustment necessary to address the current variability of the results. Currently, a meta-analysis of differentially abundant taxa in PD is hampered by the lack of descriptive statistics and an overemphasis on statistically significant results, ignoring the effect estimates of previously reported taxa. To adequately assess effect sizes and their respective degree of uncertainty, results on differentially abundant taxa should include all previously reported taxa, regardless of effect size or statistical significance. Nonetheless, the variety of bioinformatic and analytical tools used in microbiome studies can still impact inter-study comparability due to different annotation pipelines, clustering cut-offs and compositional metrics, as well as statistical methods. Ideally, raw sequencing data should be made publicly available to aid meta-analyses using standardized analytical pipelines. A meta-analysis of sequencing data from different variable regions of the 16S rRNA gene is possible through closed-reference operational taxonomic unit (OTU) picking [
 <xref rid="ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Even though this will not resolve differences in the resolution of the variable regions, the predominant use of the V4 region in twelve out of fourteen 16S studies in PD, including the re-sequenced baseline samples of Aho et al., increases the inter-study comparability. More importantly, the increase in sample size would allow for more robust conclusions on the gut microbiome composition of PD subjects: a total sample size of 874 PD and 665 HC subjects could be achieved through integration of the raw sequencing data of all PD microbiome studies using 16S sequencing data. In addition, disclosure of per sample technical, phenotypical and environmental data would aid adjusting for confounders that could possibly not be adjusted for within a given study due to low sample size. As public availability of subject information might be restricted due to privacy and confidentiality legislation, sample metadata can still be made available upon request. Currently, seven studies have made their raw sequencing data publicly available.
</p>
