<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">Human genetic variation is a significant contributor to phenotypic variation among individuals and populations, with single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) being the most common form of genetic variation. Of the entire human genomic variation, only a paucity (12%) is between continental populations and even less genetic variation (1%) is between intra-continental populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In other words, a relatively small group of SNPs are geographically differentiated, whilst a much larger group of SNPs vary among individuals, irrespective of geography. However, most of these variants are rare and non-functional [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Both common and functional variants are strong predictors of geography, phenotypes and cultural practices that may be linked with the risk for a disease. Thereby, geographical and ancestral origins can not only inform us of what risk of disease an individual has, but also modify the effect of treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In general, and with the clear exception for high admixture or migration followed by relative isolation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], most associations between geographic location and genetic similarity are expected to hold worldwide (e.g., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]). This is due to the exchange of genes and migrants between geographically proximate populations (e.g., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]). These relationships are also expected to hold for common and rare variants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The geographic differentiation between populations underlies their genetic variation or population structure, and studies in the field aim to analyse, describe or account for the genetic variation in time and space, within and among populations.
</p>
