<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ACMSD is a decarboxylase that was first cloned in 2002 [
 <xref rid="ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and later confirmed to contain a zinc metal-dependent hydrolase and amidohydrolase domain [
 <xref rid="ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Its expression in different tissue types and disease conditions has still not been fully characterized, although it is highly expressed in the liver, kidney and to a lower degree in brain under physiological conditions [
 <xref rid="ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The enzyme is primarily cytosolic and is positioned at a critical branching point in the kynurenine pathway, wherein it influences the fate of the precursor 2-amino-3-carboxymuconic-6-semialdehyde (ACMS). Quinolinic acid results from the spontaneous conversion of ACMS. However, when the enzyme ACMSD is present, it instead catalyzes the conversion of ACMS to aminomuconic semialdehyde (AMS) [
 <xref rid="ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Thus, ACMSD limits and regulates the formation of quinolinic acid (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-7-jpd171240-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The product of ACMSD, AMS, can enter another metabolic pathway, acting as a substrate for the formation of glutaryl-CoA and subsequently acetyl-CoA, which then enters the citric acid cycle [
 <xref rid="ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Concordant with this, the expression of the enzyme ACMSD is known to be upregulated in response to metabolic conditions such as animal models of diabetes [
 <xref rid="ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Picolinic acid is a stable end-product formed from AMS that is not further metabolized. This metabolite is a metal chelator that has been suggested to protect neurons against quinolinic acid-induced toxicity [
 <xref rid="ref033" ref-type="bibr">33–35</xref>], but the underlying mechanism has not been determined. Thus, ACMSD is located at a key branching site of the kynurenine pathway, where it limits the metabolism of tryptophan into NAD
 <sup>+</sup> by preventing the formation of quinolinic acid. Instead, ACMSD catalyzes the production of metabolites that subsequently enter the citric acid cycle, or can form picolinic acid.
</p>
