<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">A variety of signaling pathways have been identified that dynamically regulate dopamine reuptake through DAT plasma membrane trafficking, and many overlap with key molecular mechanisms compromised by PD-linked mutations as illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Down regulation of DAT-mediated dopamine reuptake and increase in striatal dopamine release are often observed in genetic models of parkinsonism. Why would the neurons employ so many complicated signaling pathways to regulate DAT trafficking? DAT critically maintains dopamine homeostasis to regulate dopamine signaling that is absolutely required for movement initiation and survival. Cytosolic dopamine is also easily oxidized, may lead to the production of free radicals, and drives neuromelanin biosynthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR173">173</xref>
 </sup>. Direct administration of dopamine and overexpression of dopamine transporter both lead to neuronal loss
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174">174</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR175">175</xref>
 </sup>. Conversely, dopamine reuptake by DAT is the primary mechanism for the maintenance of dopamine storage, and loss of DAT leads to dopamine depletion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. The depolarizing currents generated by dopamine reuptake also directly regulate the excitability of presynaptic boutons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, DAT surface expression must be controlled to allow dopaminergic neurons to optimally function. The complexities of DAT regulation may enable multiple compensatory mechanisms to maintain dopamine signaling despite early dysfunction. Given the role of DAT in the regulation of dopamine release and the long-hypothesized connection between altered dopamine neurotransmission and PD, studies of DAT regulation in physiological and pathological conditions remain a promising avenue to identify early biomarkers and therapeutic targets for PD.
</p>
