<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Several structurally different LRRK2 inhibitors from Genentech, GSK, Merck, and Pfizer are in the pipeline (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The compounds developed by Denali are already in clinical trials and a phase 1b trial in healthy individuals has been completed which included pulmonary and renal safety parameters. The company is advancing DNL201 (GNE-7915) to a phase 1b safety and biomarker study in 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic>-linked PD and iPD (idiopathic PD). Twenty-nine mild to moderately affected PD patients with or without 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation were randomized to either low dose DNL201, high dose DNL201, or placebo in this 28-day randomized placebo-controlled trial. In January 2020, Denali announced that both doses achieved more than 50% inhibition of pS935 LRRK2 and pRab10 phosphorylation in blood, and improved the lysosomal biomarker BMP in urine (by 20% or 60% at the low and high dose) 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">(https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf</ext-link> [online]). The same company also is testing another compound, DNL151. In a trial in 150 healthy volunteers, safety and biomarker goals were met 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">(https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf</ext-link> [online]). The compound is now being tested in PD patients with recruitment in Belgium, the Netherlands, and the UK; however, the trial is delayed because of the COVID-19 pandemic. According to the press release, Denali intends to select either DNL201 or DNL151 in mid-2020 to advance into phase 2/3 clinical trials in patients with Parkinson’s disease 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">(https://denalitherapeutics.gcs-web.com/node/7361/pdf</ext-link> [online]). To facilitate recruitment, a “direct-to-consumer” approach for testing and counseling will be available [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]—a strategy that proved successful in genetic testing with the PPMI initiative. Most recently, Denali has announced a strategic collaboration with Centogene, a gene diagnostic lab, to enhance recruitment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Pharmaceutical companies and academic centers are also conducting observational studies to identify best endpoints related to the 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic> mutation, e.g. typical neurocognitive abnormalities 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01424475?term=lrrk2&amp;draw=2&amp;rank=8" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">(https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01424475?term=lrrk2&amp;draw=2&amp;rank=8)</ext-link>.
</p>
