<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over the past decade, the emergence of iPSCs has opened up new avenues in PD research. With their self-renewal ability and potential to differentiate into many lineages, iPSC represent an opportunity to study the pathogenesis of PD at the cellular level in a human model, without raising the ethical concerns previously triggered by the use of embryonic stem cells [
 <xref rid="ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. iPSCs can be directly generated from somatic cells, obtained from the skin, blood or urine of an individual, by expressing the reprogramming factors OCT4, SOX2, KLF4, and c-MYC. This technology was first described in 2006 in a seminal study by Kazutoshi Takahashi and Shinya Yamanaka as a technique to create mouse iPSCs [
 <xref rid="ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], and followed up with two studies in 2007 describing the generation of human iPSCs samples in follow-up studies in 2007 by Yamanaka and Thomson, respectively [
 <xref rid="ref049" ref-type="bibr">49, 50</xref>]. In 2009, Soldner and colleagues were the first to describe generation of an iPSC cell-line from a patient with sporadic PD, and the subsequent differentiation of these cells into DA neurons [
 <xref rid="ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Nguyen and others, in 2011, described for the first time a pathological phenotype manifesting in iPSC-derived DA neurons from a PD patient bearing a mutation in the LRRK2 gene [
 <xref rid="ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Since then an increasing number of iPSC lines have been generated, including iPSCs from patients with mutations in familial PD genes, as well as from patients with sporadic PD without an identified causative genetic mutation. Currently, several organizations, such as the European Bank for induced pluripotent Stem Cells (EBiSC) and the New York Stem Cell Foundation (NYSCF), are centralizing and making iPSC lines derived from patients with PD available to researchers and industries. Taking advantage of such lines, many studies have started to focus on dissecting the pathological mechanisms of PD in iPSC-derived DA neurons from patients compared to neurons from healthy individuals (
 <xref rid="jpd-9-jpd181515-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="ref052" ref-type="bibr">52–76</xref>].
</p>
