<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<funding-group>
 <funding-statement>The Framingham Heart Study is funded by National Institutes of Health contract N01-HC-25195. The laboratory work for this investigation was funded by the Division of Intramural Research, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health. The analytical component of this project was funded by the Division of Intramural Research, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, and the Center for Information Technology, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD. EGCUT is supported by targeted financing from the Estonian Ministry of Science and Education [SF0180142s08]; the Development Fund of the University of Tartu (grant SP1GVARENG); the European Regional Development Fund to the Centre of Excellence in Genomics (EXCEGEN; grant 3.2.0304.11-0312); and through FP7 grant 313010. AD is supported by NWO grant (veni, 916.12.154) and the EUR Fellowship. The Rotterdam Study is funded by Erasmus Medical Center and Erasmus University, Rotterdam, Netherlands Organization for the Health Research and Development (ZonMw), the Netherlands Organisation of Scientific Research NWO Investments (nr. 175.010.2005.011, 911-03-012), the Research Institute for Diseases in the Elderly (014-93-015; RIDE2), the Ministry of Education, Culture and Science, the Ministry for Health, Welfare and Sports, the European Commission (DG XII), and the Municipality of Rotterdam. The generation and management of RNA-expression array data for the Rotterdam Study was executed and funded by the Human Genotyping Facility of the Genetic Laboratory of the Department of Internal Medicine, Erasmus MC, the Netherlands. The InCHIANTI study was supported in part by the Intramural Research Program, National Institute on Aging. DM was generously supported by a Wellcome Trust Institutional Strategic Support Award (WT097835MF). The KORA research platform and the KORA Augsburg studies are financed by the Helmholtz Zentrum München, German Research Center for Environmental Health, which is funded by the BMBF and by the State of Bavaria. Furthermore, KORA research was supported within the Munich Center of Health Sciences (MC Health), Ludwig Maximilians-Universität, as part of the LMU innovative and in part by a grant from the BMBF to the German Center for Diabetes Research (DZD). The German Diabetes Center is funded by the German Federal Ministry of Health and the Ministry of School, Science and Research of the State of North-Rhine-Westphalia. Additional support was obtained from the BMBF (National Genome Research Network NGFN plus Atherogenomics, 01GS0834), by the DZHK (Deutsches Zentrum für Herz-Kreislauf-Forschung – German Centre for Cardiovascular Research) and from the European Commission’s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013, HEALTH-F2-2011, grant agreement No. 277984, TIRCON and HEALTH-F2-2013, grant agreement No. 603288, SysVasc). SHIP is supported by the BMBF (German Ministry of Education and Research) and by the DZHK (German Centre for Cardiovascular Research) within the framework of the MetaXpress consortium. SHIP is part of the Community Medicine Research net of the University of Greifswald, Germany, which is funded by BMBF (grants no. 01ZZ9603, 01ZZ0103, and 01ZZ0403), the Ministry of Cultural Affairs as well as the Social Ministry of the Federal State of Mecklenburg-West Pomerania, and the network ‘Greifswald Approach to Individualized Medicine (GANI_MED)’ funded by the BMBF (grant 03IS2061A). Generation of genome-wide data has been supported by the BMBF (grant no. 03ZIK012). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
