<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over the past 2 decades, there has been considerable interest in the use of transcranial sonography (TCS) in PD— a method which is less expensive, time consuming and more widely available compared to radiotracer or MR imaging [
 <xref rid="r82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. An enlarged echogenic area at the anatomical site of the SN in the mesencephalic scanning plane, termed SN-hyperechogenicity, has consistently been found in at least 82% of PD cases but only in up to 23% of healthy controls [
 <xref rid="r82" ref-type="bibr">82, 83</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jpd-5-4-jpd150685-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In PD patients, the SN-echogenic sign is neither related to disease severity nor does it change over time [
 <xref rid="r82" ref-type="bibr">82, 84</xref>] and its longitudinal stability has also been reported in healty controls [
 <xref rid="r85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] and idiopathic RBD patients [
 <xref rid="r86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Although the pathophysiologic underpinnings of this echo feature are not entirely clear, histopathological studies have shown a relation of SN-echogenicity with an increased SN iron and ferritin content [
 <xref rid="r87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] as well as with decreased neuromelanin and microglial activation in the SN in healthy subjects [
 <xref rid="r88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Functional imaging studies demonstrated its association with a decreased 
 <sup>18</sup>F-Dopa uptake in healthy controls and SN-hyperechogenicity may therefore represent a surrogate marker of an increased vulnerability of the nigrostriatal dopaminergic system [
 <xref rid="r87" ref-type="bibr">87, 89, 90</xref>]. Whether SN-hyperechogenicity issuitable as a preclinical risk marker for PD in healthy elderly populations has recently been investigated in the PRIPS (Prospective validation of risk markers for the development of parkinsonian syndromes) study, a large population-based cohort study with promising results. Data from the 3- and 5-year follow-up investigations revealed a 17- and 21-fold increased risk of developing clinically defined PD in subjects exhibitingSN-hyperechogenicity compared to those without this echo-signal [
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16, 91, 92</xref>]. Interestingly, in a subset of this cohort, SN-hyperechogenity has even been shown to increase the risk for incident mild parkisonian signs over 5 years by about 2-fold, which increased to a 3-fold risk when combined with hyposmia [
 <xref rid="r93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>].
</p>
