<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Early biochemical characterization identified αS as soluble
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> and brain extract fractionation showed only a weak association with synaptic vesicles,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> confirming immunogold-EM that had detected αS throughout cytoplasmic matrices in axon terminals.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> Photobleaching microscopy also indicated that αS interacts only weakly with membranes of the nerve terminal and switches rapidly between the cytosol and membrane.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup> The earliest characterizations of αS already suggested that binding of αS to membranes may occur via the formation of amphipathic helices mediated by an 11-amino acid repeat motif having the core consensus sequence KTKEGV.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> This motif appears imperfectly six to nine times in the first two-thirds of the protein
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a–c</xref>) and resembles lipid-binding domains often observed in apolipoproteins.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup> “Cis” and “trans” factors mediate the transient αS–membrane interaction when the N-terminal two-thirds of αS form an 11/3 helix (11 amino acids/three turns)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). Nonpolar amino acid residues in the hydrophobic half of the αS amphipathic helix “dip” into the membrane bilayer (~1–5 Å below lipid head groups),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup> interacting with the lipid “tails” via van der Waals forces (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). Lysine residues (+) in the 
 <underline>K</underline>T
 <underline>K</underline>EGV motifs interact with membrane lipid head groups (−).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup> On the “trans” side, vesicle membrane composition
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup> and vesicle size affect αS binding: negatively charged head groups promote the interaction with lysine residues (see above) and small vesicles that exhibit “lipid packing defects” promote αS “insertion” into the membrane.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> The helix formation is only transient, not stable, because some nonpolar residues are found in the hydrophilic half of the helix and some polar residues interact with lipid bilayer, most importantly threonine residues (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). This imperfect helix formation seems to underlie the transient nature of αS–membrane binding.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup> A recent, elegant in vitro study suggests αS that comes off the membrane does not immediately lose its fold, but may actually retain it, and this may go hand-in-hand with native αS–αS assembly.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> The authors studied αS binding to small unilamellar vesicles composed of phosphatidylcholine (PC) with 13:0 fatty acyl side chains. Modulating αS binding via phase transitions of the vesicle lipids allowed the reconstitution of soluble helical αS species that behaved as multimers. These observations are in agreement with previous descriptions of soluble αS multimers (and tetramers might be the most abundant species among them).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup> Membrane-associated αS multimers, however, have also been described, e.g., in the context of mediating SNARE complex assembly
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup> and vesicle clustering.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup> Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref> illustrates a model of dynamic cellular αS behavior in health, centered on the idea of membrane-assisted, transient αS helical folding and resultant multimer formation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> Research from our department and other labs suggests that perturbations of a complex equilibrium between monomers and multimers, as well as between free and membrane-bound states, may represent an initial biochemical change that eventually leads to αS- and membrane-rich cytoplasmic inclusions (LBs/neurites) and progressive neurotoxicity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
