<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">We first demonstrate that a proportion of the “missing heritability” of sporadic PD can be explained by additive common genetic variation within genes implicated in mitochondrial function, even after exclusion of genes previously linked to PD through linkage disequilibrium with the top risk variants.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup> We identify that the overall heritability of PD is approximately 23% (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and that when heritability is calculated for the secondary gene list regions alone we can attribute around 7% of the overall heritability (23%) to common variation within the mitochondria function associated genes. Although this initially looks like a low estimate, to put this into context, when heritability was calculated in the most recent meta-analysis using the top PD risk hits, this estimate explained only 26–36% of the overall heritability.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> In addition, using PRS, which efficiently incorporates information from sub-significant hits, we showed that cumulative small effect variants within only 196 genes linked to monogenic mitochondrial disease significantly associated with increased PD risk (with odds ratios of 1.12 per standard deviation increase in PRS from the population mean). These findings are important for two main reasons. Firstly, given that risk profiling performed in the recent PD meta-analysis did not identify a significant association with mitochondrial function.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup> Secondly, since the primary gene list consisted solely of the 196 genes mutated in monogenic mitochondrial disorders, this analysis highlights the increasingly close relationship between Mendelian and complex disease.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
