<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">In order to maximize the utility of this study, we used MR, which identified 14 specific mitochondrial genes of interest with putative functional consequences in PD risk. We found that although a number of the genes we identified are clearly linked to known PD-related pathways, such as lysosomal dysfunction in the case of 
 <italic>CLN8</italic> and 
 <italic>LMBRD1</italic> or autophagy in the case of 
 <italic>ATG14</italic>, others appeared to point towards new processes. In particular, this analysis highlighted the mitochondrial ribosome through the identification of the genes, 
 <italic>MRPL43</italic> and 
 <italic>MRPS34</italic>, encoding components of the large and small mitochondrial ribosome subunits, respectively. Interestingly, biallelic mutations in 
 <italic>MRPS34</italic> are known to cause a form of Leigh syndrome, characterized by neurodegeneration in infancy with dystonia and choreoathetoid movements due to basal ganglia dysfunction. Furthermore, we note that a recent study that utilized whole exome sequencing (WES) data from two PD cohorts to investigate
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> rare variation in nuclear genes associated with distinct mitochondrial processes, not only provided support for the involvement of mitochondrial function in sporadic PD, but also identified the gene, 
 <italic>MRPL43</italic>, which encodes a component of the large mitochondrial ribosomal subunit.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> Interestingly, 
 <italic>MRPL43</italic> and 
 <italic>MRPS34</italic> were amongst five genes, which were also highly co-expressed in human brain with genes already known to cause monogenic forms of PD. Whereas 
 <italic>MRPL43</italic> and 
 <italic>MRPS34</italic> were highly co-expressed with 
 <italic>PARK7</italic> in modules enriched for neuronal markers, 
 <italic>FASN</italic> and 
 <italic>MPI</italic> were co-expressed with 
 <italic>ATP13A2</italic>, and 
 <italic>CLN8</italic> was located in modules containing 
 <italic>FBXO7</italic> and enriched for oligodendrocyte markers. While this form of analysis does not provide information at the single-cell level, it points to the possibility of pathway interactions between these gene sets. However, most importantly it implicates entirely distinct mitochondrial processes in PD risk.
</p>
