<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lipid and lipoprotein signaling functionally integrates, regulates and is regulated by the key landscape processes and cascades. Any disturbance of these processes and cascades can (eventually) result in DA neuron death, which is further aggravated or initiated by an increased (auto-)immune response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> The involvement of deficient lipid and lipoprotein signaling in PD pathophysiology is corroborated by a number of environmental risk factor studies. Increased plasma levels of total cholesterol are associated with a lower PD risk.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> Nevertheless, a recent meta-analysis did not show an effect of higher or lower dietary cholesterol intake on PD risk,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> suggesting that direct cholesterol intake through food may not play a major role in PD etiology. Further, low plasma levels of LDL are linked to a higher PD risk,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> whereas high-plasma HDL and CSF oxysterol levels are associated with increased PD risk and duration.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup> In addition, the levels of 
 <italic>oxidized</italic> LDL, oxysterols and sphingolipids are increased in the plasma of PD patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup> Thus, PD patients have a lower LDL:HDL ratio that is associated with a lower risk of cardiovascular disease (CVD)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup> and could at least to some extent explain why the PD population is indeed less susceptible to developing CVD.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup> Apart from the observed dysregulated levels of cholesterol (metabolites) and cholesterol-containing lipoproteins in PD patients, lower serum levels of triglycerides—which are highly enriched in VLDL particles—associate with an increased PD risk.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
