<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given the converging evidence for lipid and lipoprotein signaling playing a key role in PD etiology, compounds that modulate lipid/lipoprotein levels could represent effective novel PD treatments. In this respect, statins—inhibitors of peripheral cholesterol synthesis that are used to treat hypercholesterolemia and hence prevent cholesterol-associated CVD—have a neuroprotective effect in the rat brain,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup> but their effect on PD risk remains unclear.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> Interestingly, the only published prospective study that has adjusted for baseline cholesterol levels before statin treatment has found that statin use is associated with a significantly higher PD risk,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> which is in keeping with the observation that higher total plasma cholesterol levels—which are lowered by statins—are protective against PD. Other signaling molecules from the landscape that affect cholesterol and lipoprotein levels are testosterone and vitamin D3. Caucasian male PD patients show significantly reduced testosterone levels,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup> and free testosterone levels are positively correlated with LDL, HDL, and total cholesterol levels.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, decreased testosterone levels may impact on several key PD landscape processes, as testosterone regulates the efflux of LDL and HDL to the circulation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup> Hence, testosterone could be used for treating PD in male patients and indeed, testosterone treatment has some modest beneficial effects in men with PD.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup> Deficiency of vitamin D3—which affects cholesterol metabolism through downregulating SREBF1 (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>), the main transcriptional activator of lipid homeostasis and key landscape protein—has been consistently associated with an increased PD risk
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup> and its supplementation may stabilize PD symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
