<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The chronic use of anti-inflammatory medications by RA patients is a particularly interesting potential explanation as to why people with RA have a reduced risk of developing PD later in life. A common aim of RA treatments is to reduce the chronic inflammation that may otherwise result in joint damage and extra-articular features, and impairment to other organs and systems. TNF-alpha has been recognized as one of the major mediators of the inflammatory process that occurs in RA patients. Since the 1930s, the first disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs) such as gold salts, sulfasalazine and, some years later, antimalarials, such as hydroxychloroquine, have been in use, to treat RA patients who did not respond to treatment with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). In the 1950s, the Nobel prize awarded discovery of corticosteroids provided the physicians with a strong anti-inflammatory treatment against RA, but the adverse events of these drugs stimulated further efforts aiming at the development of new drugs, currently grouped as conventional synthetic DMARDs (csDMARDs). The introduction of the immunosuppressive drug methotrexate, in the 1980s, and of targeted biologic drugs (bDMARDs), in the 1990s, revolutionized the treatment of RA. A study of RA treatments in Sweden from 2011 [
 <xref rid="ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported that 15% of the RA patients were prescribed bDMARDs, 62% received csDMARDs, 49% were on glucocorticoids and 13% on NSAIDs. Only 11% of RA patients had no record of prescriptions for any anti-rheumatic drug. There is now a trend for earlier and wider use of bDMARDs. The last decade has also seen the introduction of biosimilars (bsDMARDs) and JAK-inhibitors (tsDMARDs), but considering that the time window of our study closed in 2016, these new medications are unlikely to have impacted our results. The evidence that systemic inflammation and neuroinflammation play roles in PD pathogenesis is growing rapidly and has been reviewed extensively by others [
 <xref rid="ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For example, TNF-alpha-mediated mechanisms have been suggested to contribute to the pathogenesis of PD [
 <xref rid="ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. A 78% reduction in PD risk has been reported in a retrospective study among the patients with inflammatory bowel diseases who received TNF–alpha inhibitors, compared with those who did not [
 <xref rid="ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Taken together, we propose that the successive increased use of such drugs and other targeted biological agents that reduce chronic inflammation in the treatment of RA patients are likely to, at least partially, account for the reduced PD risk that we observe in our study.
</p>
