<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Parkinson’s disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disease affecting 1% of the population over 60 years of age
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. PD pathology is characterised by the loss of dopaminergic neurons from the substantia nigra and the formation of neuronal inclusions called Lewy bodies. The primary symptoms are related to motor dysfunction (bradykinesia, resting tremor, rigidity, and postural instability), however, individuals with PD can also develop a range of non-motor symptoms that include sleep disturbances, constipation and impaired olfaction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. The precise mechanisms underlying the development of PD are unknown. Genetic studies have played a key role in highlighting pathways involved in disease pathogenesis that include autophagy, mitophagy, and the innate immune system
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. There are highly penetrant mutations in several genes that cause rare monogenic forms of PD in either an autosomal dominant (e.g., 
 <italic>SNCA</italic> and 
 <italic>LRRK2</italic>) or an autosomal recessive (e.g., 
 <italic>PRKN</italic> and 
 <italic>PARK7</italic>) manner
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. However, monogenic forms of the disease contribute a small percentage to the total incidence of the disease, with the majority of cases classed as sporadic and likely caused by a complex interaction of genetic and environmental risk factors. Large-scale genome wide association studies (GWAS) have been crucial in identifying genetic risk factors of idiopathic disease, however, a large proportion of the disease heritability has yet to be identified
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, many of the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that are associated with disease development are in non-coding regions of the genome and their functional impact is often unknown. We aim to investigate the genetic component of PD further by studying other types of variation and their functional consequences and this study focuses on variation generated by a specific family of retrotransposons.
</p>
