<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">The theory we emphasize here that lipid metabolism is central to αS homeostasis is particularly well supported by human genetic evidence that strongly suggest a key αS-lipid interplay (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and a major role for certain lipids in modulating αS physiology and consequent toxicity in the brain.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
 </sup> This concept is in line with a systematic analysis of GWAS data and genetic networks that revealed lipid homeostasis as a common link between several processes involved in PD pathogenesis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>
 </sup> GWAS have identified—and postmortem brain analyses have confirmed—several proteins that help regulate lipid metabolism, including LD biology, to be associated with PD. First and foremost, mutations in 
 <italic>GBA</italic> (GCase), a key gene in glycolipid metabolism, significantly increase PD risk
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>—and certain other genes in related pathways have also been implicated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> (see below). In addition, a diacylglycerol kinase, 
 <italic>DGKQ</italic>, which controls diglyceride and phosphatidic acid content, emerged from several GWAS as a PD risk factor.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> FA elongase 7, a determinant of fatty acyl side-chain length, and hence membrane composition and fluidity, was recently designated as another significant PD risk gene.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>
 </sup> A phospholipase, 
 <italic>PLA2G6</italic>, has been proposed to affect risk for PD and other brain diseases with “high brain iron”
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, seipin, an integral membrane protein localized at endoplasmic reticulum (ER)/LD contact sites and involved in LD biogenesis and maintenance,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>
 </sup> may be differentially expressed in the brains of PD vs. control subjects.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>
 </sup> These findings suggest phospholipid group and side-chain nature (dictated by FA type) play a critical role in PD, likely through αS interaction alterations. As far as non-cell-autonomous lipid homeostasis is concerned, variants in LRP10, a low-density lipoprotein receptor protein, were also reported be linked to PD dementia, DLB, and Lewy pathology,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>
 </sup> but this remains controversial
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>
 </sup> (LRP10 mutations have also been associated with increased Alzheimer’s disease pathogenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>
 </sup>). Moreover, 
 <italic>SREBF-1</italic>, a transcription factor that binds sterol regulatory element-1 and controls lipid homeostasis through sterol biosynthesis, has been identified in GWAS as a PD risk factor.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup> This finding, in addition to certain studies on statin use, suggests that sterol pathways in PD pathogenesis should not be ignored either.
</p>
