<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RBD is a parasomnia clinically characterized by dream-enacting behaviours related to loss of physiological atonia during REM-sleep [
 <xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The prevalence of idiopathic RBD in the population is not well defined as definite diagnosis requires polysomnography. A commonly cited figure of 0.4% , however, may well be an underestimate [
 <xref rid="r60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Indeed, when using two validated screening questionnaires in an elderly population-based sample of 476 subjects, we recently found a prevalence of probable RBD of 5–8% in a Caucasian population aged &gt;60 years [
 <xref rid="r61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In this particular cross sectional study, probable RBD was associated with multiple other nonmotor markers of PD, while polysomnography was not available. Idiopathic RBD is increasingly recognized as a harbinger of neurodegenerative diseases, including not only PD but also other synucleinopathies like DLB or MSA. Several follow-up studies have found that the majority of subjects with idiopathic RBD (&gt;80%) will convert into one of these disorders –most commonly PD or DLB - with extended follow-up over decades [
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15, 54, 62</xref>]. Two recent prospective cohort studies have further substantiated these observations. Postuma and colleagues collected follow-up data in a multicentre sample of 305 patients with idiopathic RBD over up to 6 years and found an overall conversion to neurodegenerative diseases of 33% [
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], which was time-dependent at 15% after 2 years, 25% after 3 years, and 41% after 5 years. Conversion to PD or DLB was common (42% and 50% , respectively), while only 8% converted to MSA. Idiopathic RBD patient who converted over the observational period were older, more likely to report a family history of dementia, and more frequently endorsed autonomic and/or motor symptoms on questionnaires compared to those who remained disease free, whereas many baseline characteristics including caffeine and nicotine exposure were not different between these groups [
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. With the aid of thorough testing batteries, conversion from RBD to PD or PD Dementia/DLB appears to be more predictable. One recent prospective study in 89 idiopathic RBD patients found that smell identification loss (hazard ratio (HR) 2.8), abnormal colour vision (HR, 3.1), and subtle motor impairment (HR, 3.9), as well as advanced age (HR, 1.1) and non-use of anti-depressants (HR, 3.5) was associated with conversion to one of these synucleinopathies (including MSA) over the 7.5 year observational period.
</p>
