<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Taken together, current evidence shows that RBD is the most specific among the different risk factors for PD (see 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="jpd-5-4-jpd150685-t002">Table 2</xref>) and RBD cohorts seem obvious candidates for future disease-prevention studies for PD. However, the median latency to conversion into clinically defined PD can be as long as 12 to 14 years [
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15, 54</xref>], seriously limiting the feasibility of such trials. Therefore, we recently investigated whether olfactory impairment can predict early conversion to PD or PDD/DLB among 35 idiopathic RBD patients prospectively followed over 5 years [
 <xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Indeed, abnormal baseline performance on the multidimensional SniffinSticks test assessing odour identification, odour discrimination, and olfactory threshold predicted conversion to a Lewy body disorder with an accuracy of 82.4% , and this was also true for poor performance on the identification subscore only. Based on the findings from this cohort, sample sizes for a hypothetical neuroprotection trial in RBD with conversion to a Lewy body disorders as an endpoint could be reduced by 74–80% for a 5-year trial if idiopathic RBD patients were pretested for baseline olfactory dysfunction. For example, a total of 760 patients with idiopathic RBD versus 188 patients with idiopathic RBD and olfactory dysfunction would be required to have an 80% chance to detect a 30% decrease in the primary outcome measure of conversion to a Lewy body disease [
 <xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Similar data were also reported by Postuma et al. who found that by excluding idiopathic RBD subjects &lt;55 years of age or using antidepressants reduced estimated sample sizes for 3-year neuroprotection trials with the same outcome measure by ≥25% when further pretesting for olfactory dysfunction, impaired colour vision, or subtle motor impairment and by ≥40% when using combinations of these markers [
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
