<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab2">
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Cellular stressors used in hiPSC-PD models.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Type of stressor</th>
    <th>Reagent</th>
    <th>What is it?</th>
    <th>Mechanism of action</th>
    <th>Environmental and biological relevance</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="9">Proteostatic</td>
    <td>MG132</td>
    <td>Peptide-aldehyde (proteasome inhibitor)</td>
    <td>Initiates apoptosis and reduces degradation of ubiquitin-conjugated proteins by inhibiting 20S proteasome activity</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Cycloheximide</td>
    <td>Naturally occurring fungicide</td>
    <td>Inhibits global transcriptional function</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Lactacystin</td>
    <td>Proteasomal inhibitors</td>
    <td>Inhibits ubiquitin–proteasome proteolysis pathway</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Epoxomicin</td>
    <td>Naturally occurring proteasome inhibitor</td>
    <td>Inhibits protein degradation by inhibiting chymotrypsin-like proteasome</td>
    <td>Used to induce PD-like symptoms in animal models</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Leupeptin</td>
    <td> Naturally occurring protease inhibitor</td>
    <td>Inhibits lysosomal proteolysis by inhibiting cysteine protease</td>
    <td>Used to induce aging associated degeneration of neural processes in animal models</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Ammonium Chloride</td>
    <td> Weak Base</td>
    <td>Inhibits lysosomal proteolysis by altering pH of lysosomes</td>
    <td>Component of fertilizers</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Bafilomycin</td>
    <td> Toxic macrolide antibiotic</td>
    <td>Inhibits autophagy by preventing maturation of autophagic vacuoles. Targets vacuolar type H+-ATPase causes lysosome neutralization and inhibition of autophagosome and lysosome fusion.</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Chloroquine</td>
    <td>Prototype anti-malarial drug</td>
    <td>Inhibits autophagy by increasing lysosomal pH and preventing fusion of autophagosomes and lysosomes.</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Rapamycin</td>
    <td>Macrolide compound</td>
    <td>Increases autophagy by inducing autophagosome formation via inhibition of mTOR</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="9">Mitochondrial</td>
    <td>FCCP/CCCP</td>
    <td>Protonophore (respiratory chain uncoupler)</td>
    <td>Reduce cell respiratory capacity by inhibiting mitochondrial cell volume and membrane potential</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Rotenone</td>
    <td>Insecticide</td>
    <td>Inhibits mitochondria respiration and ATP generation via inhibition of mitochondrial complex I</td>
    <td>Insecticide associated with PD epidemiology</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Valinomycin</td>
    <td> Antibiotic/Ionophore</td>
    <td>Induced loss of mitochondrial membrane potential and mitochondrial translocation via facilitating potassium transfer across lipid layers</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Oligomycin</td>
    <td> Antibiotic</td>
    <td>Blocks ATP synthesis via inhibition of ATP synthase preventing oxidative phosphorylation of ADP</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Antimycin A</td>
    <td>Antibiotic</td>
    <td>Inhibits mitochondrial electron transport by inhibition of complex III</td>
    <td> *</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Paraquat</td>
    <td> Herbicide</td>
    <td>Increases ROS</td>
    <td>Herbicide associated with PD epidemiology</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>MPTP</td>
    <td>Impure by-product of recreational drug design</td>
    <td>Induces cell death due to ATP depletion via inhibition of mitochondrial complex I</td>
    <td>Causes Parkinsonism in users</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Maneb</td>
    <td> Fungicide</td>
    <td>Alters cellular redox reactions by catalysing DA oxidation and chelation of metals</td>
    <td>Fungicide used to generate PD in animal models</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Concanamycin A</td>
    <td> Antibiotic</td>
    <td>Inhibits mitophagy by preventing acidification of organelles via inhibition of H+-ATPase</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="4">Synaptic</td>
    <td>KCl</td>
    <td> Metal halide salt</td>
    <td>Induces dopamine release by increasing calcium response</td>
    <td>KCl found in some foods and used as a salt substitute</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Glutamate</td>
    <td> Neurotransmitter</td>
    <td>Activates extra-synaptic and synaptic excitatory glutamatergic receptors via AMPA, NMDA Kainite receptors, and alterations in intracellular calcium</td>
    <td>Main component of food flavourer monosodium glutamate (MSG)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Caffeine</td>
    <td>CNS stimulant</td>
    <td>RyR agonist that increases the calcium release from the calcium-sensitive internal stores</td>
    <td>Widely consumed psychoactive drug present in many foods</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Colchicine</td>
    <td>Microtubule depolarizing agent</td>
    <td>Inhibits microtubule polymerization by binding to tubulin</td>
    <td>Promote neurite retraction in vitro</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="6">Oxidative</td>
    <td>Hydrogen Peroxide</td>
    <td>Strong oxidizer</td>
    <td>Directly increase oxidation and ROS</td>
    <td>Induce oxidative stress linked to aging</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>No antioxidants</td>
    <td>Removing antioxidants from neuronal culture media</td>
    <td>Reduce the prevention of the oxidation of molecules</td>
    <td> Antioxidants in food</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>6-OHDA</td>
    <td>Synthetic compound (enters neurons via neurotransmitter uptake transporters)</td>
    <td>Produce ROS specifically in dopaminergic and noradrenergic neurons; inhibition of mitochondrial complexes I and IV</td>
    <td>Selective destruction of DAn used to generate PD in animal models</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Dopamine</td>
    <td>Neurotransmitter</td>
    <td>Induced dopamine toxicity by increased dopamine oxidation by monoamine oxidases (MAO) in cytoplasm</td>
    <td>Mimic chronic use of Levodopa</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Cadmium</td>
    <td> Transition metals</td>
    <td> Induce oxidative stress by depleting cells’ antioxidants</td>
    <td>Heavy metals present in contaminated air, water. soil and food</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Exogenous a-synuclein</td>
    <td>Major component of Lewy bodies</td>
    <td>Increase basal ROS levels</td>
    <td>Mimic effect of a-synuclein accumulation in vitro</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="3">ER</td>
    <td>A23187</td>
    <td> Calcium ionophore</td>
    <td>Induced ER stress by increasing cytosolic calcium concentrations</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Brefeldin A</td>
    <td> Fungal metabolite</td>
    <td>Inhibits intracellular protein transport by preventing association of COP-I coat to the Golgi membrane</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>DTT</td>
    <td> Reducing agent</td>
    <td>Induces ER stress by preventing inhibition of disulfide bonds</td>
    <td>*</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Age-inducing</td>
    <td>Progerin</td>
    <td>Truncated version of the lamin A protein</td>
    <td>Increases the frequency of unrepaired double-strand breaks in DNA</td>
    <td>Mimics aging processes</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Inflammation</td>
    <td>IL-17</td>
    <td>Hematopoietic growth factor (cytokine)</td>
    <td>Induces inflammation through IL-17–IL-17R signaling and activation of NFkB</td>
    <td>Naturally occurring inflammatory cytokine</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <p>These compounds were used to stress cells to explore mechanisms of PD not to cause PD in models.</p>
  <p>An asterisk indicates a synthetic compound not naturally occurring or that does not have environmental or biological relevance.</p>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
