<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Within a single country, there is good evidence that healthcare inequalities exist in the detection, diagnosis and treatment of PD. The only studies comparing national healthcare inequalities in PD have been conducted in the USA, a country with greater healthcare inequalities than many other countries in the world [
 <xref rid="ref153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. It is unknown whether the findings are applicable to other countries and it would be interesting to know whether the results reproduce in countries with universal healthcare systems. For other medical conditions, ethnic health inequalities exist even in countries such as the UK which have universal healthcare systems [
 <xref rid="ref154" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. Black patients in the USA are less likely to be treated by a neurologist than White patients [
 <xref rid="ref155" ref-type="bibr">155, 156</xref>]. This may in-part explain some of the suspected under-ascertainment of PD in patients from certain ethnic backgrounds. For PD patients, being treated by a neurologist was inversely associated with residing in a nursing home, hip fractures and likelihood of death [
 <xref rid="ref155" ref-type="bibr">155, 157</xref>]. Dahodwala et al., showed that African-Americans are four times less likely than White PD patients to receive PD treatment (OR 0.24; 95% CI 0.09–0.64) [
 <xref rid="ref158" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. This finding has been replicated [
 <xref rid="ref157" ref-type="bibr">157, 159</xref>] and there is evidence the inequalities extend to the treatment of depression and advanced therapies in PD patients as well [
 <xref rid="ref160" ref-type="bibr">160–162</xref>]. Amongst the minority ethnic patients that do receive treatment prescribing errors are more likely; Hispanic PD patients have an increased probability of being co-prescribed an anticholinesterase inhibitor and a high potency anticholinergic; a frank prescribing error [
 <xref rid="ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. To summarise, PD patients from minority ethnic backgrounds in the USA are less likely to be cared for by a neurologist, receive a diagnosis and be treated adequately for their PD.
</p>
