<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>We would like to thank all of the subjects who donated their time and biological samples to be a part of this study. This work was supported in part by the Intramural Research Programs of the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS), the National Institute on Aging (NIA), and the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences both part of the National Institutes of Health, Department of Health and Human Services; project numbers Z01-AG000949-02 and Z01-ES101986. In addition this work was supported by the Department of Defense (award W81XWH-09-2-0128), and The Michael J Fox Foundation for Parkinson’s Research. We would also like to thank all members of the International Parkinson Disease Genomics Consortium (IPDGC). For a complete overview of members, acknowledgements and funding, please see 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pdgenetics.org/partners" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pdgenetics.org/partners</ext-link>. We would like to thank the Accelerating Medicines Partnership initiative (AMP-PD) for the publicly available whole genome sequencing data. This work utilized the computational resources of the NIH HPC Biowulf cluster. (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hpc.nih.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hpc.nih.gov</ext-link>).
 </p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>International Parkinson Disease Genomics Consortium</title>
  <p id="Par42">We thank contributors who collected samples used in this initiative, as well as patients and families, whose help and participation made this work possible. Part of the data used for the analyses described in this manuscript was obtained from dbGaP at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=gap" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=gap</ext-link> through dbGaP accession phs000200, we thank members of the North American Brain Expression Consortium (NABEC) for providing DNA samples derived from brain tissue. Brain tissue for the NABEC cohort was obtained from the Baltimore Longitudinal Study on Aging at the Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, and from the NICHD Brain and Tissue Bank for Developmental Disorders at the University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD, USA. We would like to thank the United Kingdom Brain Expression Consortium (UKBEC) for providing DNA samples. This study acknowledges the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS) supported Parkinson’s Disease Biomarkers Program Investigators (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pdbp.ninds.nih.gov/sites/default/files/assets/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pdbp.ninds.nih.gov/sites/default/files/assets/</ext-link> PDBP_investigator_list.pdf). A full list of PDBP investigators can be found at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pdbp.ninds.nih.gov/policy" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pdbp.ninds.nih.gov/policy</ext-link>. Data and biospecimens used in the preparation of this manuscript were obtained from the Parkinson’s Disease Biomarkers Program (PDBP) Consortium, part of the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke at the National Institutes of Health. Investigators include: Roger Albin, Roy Alcalay, Alberto Ascherio, Thomas Beach, Sarah Berman, Bradley Boeve, F. DuBois Bowman, Shu Chen, Alice Chen-Plotkin, William Dauer, Ted Dawson, Paula Desplats, Richard Dewey, Ray Dorsey, Jori Fleisher, Kirk Frey, Douglas Galasko, James Galvin, Dwight German, Lawrence Honig, Xuemei Huang, David Irwin, Kejal Kantarci, Anumantha Kanthasamy, Daniel Kaufer, James Leverenz, Carol Lippa, Irene Litvan, Oscar Lopez, Jian Ma, Lara Mangravite, Karen Marder, Laurie Ozelius, Vladislav Petyuk, Judith Potashkin, Liana Rosenthal, Rachel Saunders-Pullman, Clemens Scherzer, Michael Schwarzschild, Tanya Simuni, Andrew Singleton, David Standaert, Debby Tsuang, David Vaillancourt, David Walt, Andrew West, Cyrus Zabetian, Jing Zhang, and Wenquan Zou. The PDBP Investigators have not participated in reviewing the data analysis or content of the manuscript. This work was supported by Scripps Research Translational Institute, an NIH-NCATS Clinical and Translational Science Award (CTSA; 5 UL1 RR025774). We are grateful to the NIH NeuroBioBank for providing brain tissue samples for Parkinson’s disease cases. We are grateful to the Banner Sun Health Research Institute Brain and Body Donation Program of Sun City, Arizona, for the provision of human brain tissue (PI: Thomas G. Beach, MD). The Brain and Body Donation Program is supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (U24 NS072026 National Brain and Tissue Resource for Parkinson’s Disease and Related Disorders), the National Institute on Aging (P30 AG19610 Arizona Alzheimer’s Disease Core Center), the Arizona Department of Health Services (contract 211002, Arizona Alzheimer’s Research Center), the Arizona Biomedical Research Commission (contracts 4001, 0011, 05-901 and 1001 to the Arizona Parkinson’s Disease Consortium) and the Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson’s Research.
  </p>
 </sec>
</ack>
