<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Emerging evidence suggests that disruption of circadian rhythms may not only be a consequence of neuronal loss in PD, but may itself contribute to the neurodegenerative process [
 <xref rid="ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Circadian rhythms are physiological and behavioral cycles generated by an endogenous biological clock in the suprachiasmatic nucleus [
 <xref rid="ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Circadian rhythms regulate many physiological and behavioral functions, such as 24-h rhythmicity in rest-activity behavior, body temperature, hormone levels, and homeostasis [
 <xref rid="ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Numerous studies have reported that the symptoms and behaviors associated with PD, such as disruption in motor activity, sleep dysfunction, and responsiveness to dopaminergic treatments, show diurnal fluctuation [
 <xref rid="ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. These observations indicate there are circadian influences on the expression of PD’s clinical features. Genes that control circadian rhythms are known as clock genes. Several clock genes have been identified including period (PER1, PER2, and PER3), cryptochrome (
 <italic>CRY1</italic> and 
 <italic>CRY2</italic>), 
 <italic>CLOCK, BMAL1</italic>, and 
 <italic>NPAS2</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Histone modifications and DNA modifications regulate many of these clock genes and can exhibit circadian fluctuations [
 <xref rid="ref028" ref-type="bibr">28, 98–100</xref>]. In PD, a circadian regulator, the 
 <italic>NPAS2</italic> gene promoter, was shown to have a 13% decrease in DNA methylation relative to controls [
 <xref rid="ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Clock genes are known to greatly interact through complex feedback loops to generate and sustain circadian rhythms. Hence, aberrant DNA methylation of key clock genes in the PD brain may potentiate widespread circadian deregulation and neuronal dysfunction.
</p>
