<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P8">Here, we took an integrative systems biology approach to identify neurodegenerative dementia-associated protein networks in post-mortem brain across multiple AD cohorts (
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Hodes and Buckholtz, 2016</xref>). To detect robust disease-associated changes, we used the same processing scheme to harmonize data across studies and applied a consensus network analysis approach to identify conserved co-expression modules (
 <xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">Langfelder and Horvath, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr">Langfelder et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R115" ref-type="bibr">Swarup et al., 2019</xref>). We subsequently characterized the temporal trajectories of distinct biological processes over disease progression by distinguishing early and late disease changes and identifying several co-expression modules correlated with neuropathology and cognitive decline. We validated these findings in an orthogonal dataset (
 <xref rid="R97" ref-type="bibr">Ping et al., 2018</xref>) and extended our initial findings across multiple neurodegenerative diseases, including FTD with TDP-43 (FTD-TDP), PSP with corticobasal degeneration (PSP-CBD), PD, PD with dementia (PD-D), multiple system atrophy (MSA), and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS). We found protein co-expression modules that were dysregulated in neurodegenerative dementias (AD, FTD-TDP, PSP-CBD, and PD-D), but not in related neurodegenerative diseases (PD, MSA, and ALS) where dementia is not the defining feature. We evaluated concordance of transcriptomic and proteomic signatures in a subset of samples, finding high correspondence overall, as well as proteome-specific changes. To understand the relationship of these core molecular processes with causal genetic drivers, we placed common variants associated with disease risk within co-expression modules to identify specific biological processes enriched in disease-specific risk variants.
</p>
