<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Through direct or indirect interactions of Parkin/PINK1 with the fusion factors Mfn1, Mfn2, and OPA1 and the fission factor Drp1, these proteins regulate mitochondrial dynamics, which is linked to the maintenance of mitochondrial function [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>–
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Furthermore, Parkin and PINK1 have been implicated in another, autophagy-independent, mitochondrial QC mechanism, which is the transport of specific protein cargo as membrane-derived vesicles (MDVs) to the lysosomes. The formation of MDVs is stimulated as an early response to oxidative stress, and damaged mitochondrial regions are excised and transported to the endolysosomal compartments for degradation [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. In addition to degradative pathways, Parkin and PINK1 proteins play a crucial role in the regulation of mitochondrial biogenesis through the degradation of the Parkin substrate PARIS, which acts as a transcriptional repressor of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma coactivator-1 alpha (PGC-1
 <italic>α</italic>), a transcriptional coactivator and master regulator of mitochondrial biogenesis [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Moreover, an involvement of both Parkin and PINK1 in mitochondrial trafficking and QC has been suggested by reporting their association to Miro/Milton/dynein complex [
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Miro is an outer mitochondrial membrane protein that anchors mitochondria to microtubule motors. As a consequence of Miro phosphorylation mediated by PINK1, Miro is ubiquitylated by Parkin and degraded by the proteasome. This leads to blockage of mitochondrial motility, which facilitates the isolation and sequestration of damaged mitochondria for degradation [
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. For example, an increase in anterograde transport was shown in axons of pink1 knockdown 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic> [
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>], while mitochondrial trafficking was blocked by overexpression of both Parkin and Pink1 in 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic> and in mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. More recently, it has been shown that also LRRK2 promotes Miro removal. The pathogenic G2019S mutation disrupts this function, delaying the motility blockage of damaged mitochondria and consequently slowing the initiation of mitophagy [
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Remarkably, Miro degradation and reduced mitochondrial motility were also detected in sporadic PD patients, pointing to Miro and its interaction with PD-related proteins as a common molecular mechanism in different forms of PD. Recently, we have identified Stomatin-like protein 2 (SLP-2) as a novel Parkin interactor that upon overexpression rescued mitochondrial dysfunction of Parkin-deficient neuronal cells. Double knockdown flies showed a genetic interaction between Parkin and SLP-2, and SLP-2 transgenic flies attenuated loss of DA neurons, mitochondrial network structure, and flight and motor dysfunctions. This interaction might promote optimal activity of mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I and mitochondrial integrity in induced pluripotent stem cell-derived neurons and 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic> [
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. SLP-2 was described as part of a new mitochondrial protein complex named SPY, which regulates proteolysis of PINK1 by the mitochondrial protease PARL linking SLP-2 to both Parkin and PINK1 [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>].
</p>
