<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our findings support previous reports that the genotype at rs6812193 SNP is associated with PD. This SNP, which is in linkage disequilibrium with the 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> gene, was found in association with PD in two large multi-ethnic genome-wide association studies (OR=0.84; 
 <italic>P</italic>=7.6×10
 <sup>−10</sup> and OR=0.907; 
 <italic>P</italic>=2.95×10
 <sup>−11</sup>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>
 </sup> and in a German association study (OR=0.86; 
 <italic>P</italic>=0.02).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>
 </sup> However, the association was not replicated in a Chinese
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>
 </sup> or a Greek cohort,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>
 </sup> likely due to either population differences or insufficient power. Here, we confirm the association in a clinic based New York cohort, which consists of 40% AJ PD patients. An association between the 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> gene and PD was hypothesized to be due to differential trafficking of GCase to the lysosome.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>
 </sup> In the current study we hypothesized that if indeed rs6812193 is associated with PD risk via 
 <italic>SCARB2,</italic> then carriers of the protective nucleotide (T) should have higher GCase activity than carriers of the PD susceptibility allele (C). We have previously shown in dried blood spots that heterozygous 
 <italic>GBA</italic> carriers have lower GCase activity than non-carriers (by ~33%), and that idiopathic PD cases have slightly lower GCase activity (by ~5%) than controls.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>
 </sup> Our current findings do not support the link between rs6812193 and PD through a mechanism of reduced GCase activity (at least not as measured in dried blood spots). There are several possible explanations for our findings. First, rs6812193 is associated with PD via a different gene/mechanism not linked to 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> or GCase. This explanation is supported by a prior study showing that variants in this SNP do not correlate with LIMP-2 messenger RNA or protein levels in leukocytes from a small sample of controls.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>
 </sup> Second, rs6812193 is associated with PD through 
 <italic>SCARB2,</italic> but its biological effect is not mediated by GCase activity. Finally, rs6812193 is associated with PD through 
 <italic>SCARB2</italic> and GCase pathways but this effect is either present in selected tissues (e.g., brain) and not leukocytes, or it involves altered intracellular routing and localization of GCase that is not apparent in the DBS assay.
</p>
